<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anōthekrypta, or, Glorious mysteries wherein the grand proceedings betwixt Christ and the soule ... : is clearly laid open ... / by S.M., minister of the Gospel of God.</title>
            <author>Moore, Samuel, b. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12963157</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12963157</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 392:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anōthekrypta, or, Glorious mysteries wherein the grand proceedings betwixt Christ and the soule ... : is clearly laid open ... / by S.M., minister of the Gospel of God.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Samuel, b. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 235 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Symmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Appears also in his Theosplanchnistheis. London, 1647.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Regeneration (Theology)</term>
               <term>Sanctification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96098:1"/>
ΑΝΩΘΕΚΡΥΠΥΑ, OR GLORIOUS MYSTERIES. <hi>WHEREIN</hi> The grand proceedings betwixt Chriſt and the Soule: As alſo the Diſcoveries, of thoſe his hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſecrets of <hi>Renovation,</hi> with the Saints <hi>Peregrination,</hi> laſt <hi>Mutation,</hi> and <hi>Glorification,</hi> their graces <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation:</hi> is clearly laid open to the great ſupportation, and comfort of all drooping, ſtooping, and unſetled hearts; by which they may fully ſee, what they have been, are, and ſhall be, to their everlaſting contentment.</p>
            <p>BY S. M. <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Saints is made knowne, what is the riches of the glory of this Myſtery among the</hi> Gentiles; <hi>which is Chriſt in you, the hope of Glory.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Col. 1. 27.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreover, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called: and whom he called, them he alſo Juſtified: and whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Rom. 8. 30.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Symmons,</hi> in the yeare 1647.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96098:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96098:2"/>
            <head>GLORIOUS MYSTERIES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>I CORINTH. 15. 8.</bibl>
                  <q>And laſt of all, he was ſeen of me alſo, as of one borne out of due time.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the viſions of Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ivine patience hath a large latitude. God can ſuffer, and ſuffer long</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Tardus ad poenam, ad ſalutem cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis celer eſt Deus.</note>; <hi>would men returne at laſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an everlaſting ſtay: his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsions faile not, that's the cauſe that all conſume not: Servants of the 'leventh houre ſhall have equall pay with thoſe that are of the third, ſixt, and ninth: as</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96098:3"/>
                  <hi>the firſt may bee laſt, ſo</hi> the laſt ſhall be firſt, <hi>as Chriſt ha's ſaid. Reſiſtance againſt ſweeteſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and releeving mercy may be long laſting, yet if it ha's a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod Chriſt cannot caſt off, will in nowiſe caſt out, ſuch as come unto him. A man may be laſt in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Regeneration, and yet equall to the firſt in the apprehenſion, and participation of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> viz. <hi>beyond which time he could proceed no farther againſt Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> à continendo, &amp; cohibendo id <hi>viz.</hi> in quo neceſſe eſt, ut conſiſtamus ultrà quod pergerenon liceat. <hi>Beza. Mat.</hi> 19. 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>: I was not among the firſt that ſaw him; that's my griefe; yet ſee I did, and ſee I doe, him that's inviſible. He that ſees leaſt and the laſt does as truly ſee, and as freely injoy the Lord Jeſus, as he who ſees moſt; apprehended with the firſt. Deſpaire then! where art thou? and what ground haſt thou to ſurvive in man? Who would deſpaire of the hope of life, when God's ſo good to a man ſo bad as</hi> Paul <hi>was before Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96098:3"/>
                  <hi>Preſumption! thou mayſt not live neither; for though true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be never late; yet late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is ſeldome true</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Poenitentia vera nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſera, at poenitentia ſera rarò ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>: as he once ſaid. Chriſt ſpar'd one Thiefe at laſt, that none ſhould deſpaire: and but one that none may preſume: this digreſsion is for caution to preſumptuous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THree things concur to make up a right ſight naturall. An Object: a medium (as the aire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, or ſome ſuch thing) and a ſeeing facultie. 'Tis ſo in all ſpirituall ſight that's right too.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians! Conſider Firſt, God in his Glorie is the object of your ſpirituall ſight: and know you not, that the more glorious your object is, the more is your ſight gladded, ſo long as 'tis not overwhelmed? for there is a time, when glorious Majeſtie is an object too ſtrong for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſight. <note n="d" place="margin">Excellens ſenſibile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruit ſenſum.</note> God is inviſible,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96098:4"/>
not becauſe obſcure; but for that he's too glorious for mortal ſight, put on immortality then, that you may ſee aright, him in whom you beleeve. But in Heaven, the eye of the ſoule ſhall bee inlarg'd and made capatious, ſuitable, to its glorious object to take in much of God. What ſay yee? Is't not evident in created light, that the more light the eye has, the better 'tis pleas'd, if the eye it ſelfe be ſound and right? even ſo 'tis in the things of the Spirit. Will you heare what a ſoule, reſtleſſe without God, ſaid. 'Tis this, <hi>One thing have I deſired of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord, that will I ſeeke after, that I may dwell in his houſe all the dayes of my life.</hi> And why? <hi>to behold his beautie:</hi> dwell with him; but 'twas that he might ſee him, ſtill be in his preſence, have his eye upon him: He lookes, and likes, elects, and loves, when God ſets himſelfe in ſight. Does not the glorie of God, who is beautie it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96098:4"/>
ſelfe, comelineſſe it ſelfe, keepe a God-like mans eye upon the object? What can be more allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring then the lovelineſſe of the lovelieſt Lord? What can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the ſpirituall ſight more? Chriſtians! are you not aſtoniſh'd with the perfections of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, when you looke upon't in earneſt? if you be not, 'tis your ſinne, and let it cauſe many thoughts of heart within your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret parts. Deare friends<hi>!</hi> 'tis a ſad thing to have ſo bad an eye, as that ſo good an object ſhould not be of greateſt force to raviſh both ſight and ſenſe, bringing the whole ſoule into a glorious rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the beholding of ſuch a glorious aſpect.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſpirituall ſight hath a medium too; Jeſus Chriſt's that medium: the good God may be ſeen; but 'tis <hi>in, and through a good Chriſt</hi> *. Chriſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the very beame, ſplendour, and brightnes of his Fathers glorie, the expreſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96098:5"/>
                  <hi>Image of his perſon</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. Eſt magna gratia in hac voce. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ab <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſplendorem emitto<hi>:</hi> propriè eſt ſplendor ad res externas reſultans ex interna facultate: quemadmodum ſplendor à ſole promanat, <hi>Polan. Syntag.</hi> Refulgentia qualis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſplendor eſt autem ſolis: &amp; radiorum ejus ſplendoris<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem natura. <hi>Aret.</hi> in loc.</p>
                     <p>Effulgentia relucentia <hi>Greg.</hi> in loc. Significat etiam ſplendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ab alla luce editum; ſic filius eſt ſplendor a luce paterna e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus: ſicut in Symbola legitur lumen de lumine Victorin. <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</hi> in Nor. Teſt. ſuperloc.</p>
                  </note>
                  <hi>:</hi> For Chriſt proceeds from the Father, as Light, brightneſſe, raies, and beames from the Sunne, in the Firmament of Heaven <note n="f" place="margin">Chriſtus à Patre proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ſicut lux, ſplendor, &amp; radii à Sole. <hi>Hyperius</hi> in locum.</note>. The Sunnes beames and ſtreames of light are pure: darknes comes not nigh them: ſo is Chriſt, who's the <hi>brightneſſe of the Father.</hi> O glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God<hi>!</hi> thou art the greateſt good.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt ha's told you (you ſeeing Chriſtians<hi>!)</hi> that <hi>he who ha's ſeen the Sonne, ha's ſeen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 14. 7. 9. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>alſo, and that no man knowes the Father, but the Sonne, and him to whom the Son reveales him.</hi> And is not the Father beſt ſeen in the Sonne? who dare ſee the face of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96098:5"/>
Majeſtie, without a Jeſus? no mortall man can ſee the face of the immortall God, and live: onely God-man, the man Chriſt Jeſus, is found worthy, as Gods equall, to mediate betwixt an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Lord, and offending man. Bleſſed Meſſiah! thou art a ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good to thine in this reſpect. Chriſt is the medium to this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious object of ſpirituall ſight. Chriſtians! you may have food from Heavens ſtore-houſes: but then forget not to bring the Lord's <hi>Benjamin</hi> with you; for if ſo, you may not ſee his face<hi>:</hi> you may ſee God, and take him in alſo into your ſpirits; but it muſt be in the name and ſtrength of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in whom the Father is reconciling ſoules to his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſelfe, and then 'tis but <hi>aske and receive: ſeeke, and find: knock, and it ſhall be opened to you:</hi> When you draw neere to God. Onely Chriſt is the way to life, and to <note n="*" place="margin">Iter od gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, eſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> the Father of all ſuch mercies;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96098:6"/>
for he's truth and life it ſelfe with the Father. Senſible ſoules! what goe <hi>ye out for to ſee, a reed ſhaken in the wind?</hi> Is there any viſion like this, or ſight compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this? what! is there ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious an object, or <hi>medium</hi> in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſight? <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom &amp; knowledg of God! how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſearchable are his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſpirituall ſight has a light too, a light ſuper-ſenſuall, ſuper-naturall: Naturall light may give inſight into divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of wiſdome, power, and providence in Creation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and preſervation of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things; but can it reach fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Can naturall light give in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in things above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, things of Grace? Can <hi>fleſh and bloud reveale God and Chriſt</hi> to a wanting ſoule? Chriſt ſaith nay to ſuch a thing. <hi>Thou art Chriſt,</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> to Jeſus: and what was the replie? 'twas this. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96098:6"/>
                  <hi>art thou,</hi> and why? <hi>for fleſh and bloud hath not reveal'd this to thee; but my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> 'Tis ableſſed part of bliſſe; that the inviſible God, and the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible good is not to be unfolded by natures light: for were it ſo, what poore diſcoveries then would nature make of myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous grace? <hi>ſpirituall things,</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, <hi>are fooliſhneſſe</hi> to a naturall heart; nor can a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall object be received by it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis <hi>ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things are to a naturall <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 14.</note> heart's ſight and ſenſe like mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, in a dead mans eare, which moves him not, affects him not. What good doth hee find in it? what doth he take in of it? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nothing. Onely Chriſt can reveale himſelfe in a ſoule, to that ſoule. As the Sunne raies reveales its owne luſtre, or as fire reveales its owne heat and vigour by giving heat, making hot, things held unto it. Nature may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96098:7"/>
God as Maker and ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of things, both above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but cannot ſhew you a God, reconciling himſelfe to your ſoules in a Chriſt. The beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and inlarged ſpirit of nature is below this great imployment<hi>:</hi> Light is not ſeen but by the light: darkneſſe cannot diſcover it: the <hi>Light may ſhine in darkneſſe, but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>darkneſſe comprehends it not:</hi> ſo onely grace can diſcover its own originall, Jeſus Chriſt<hi>:</hi> onely ſomething of God in man can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover rightly God himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man. Without <hi>holineſſe ther's no ſight had of holieſt Majeſtie:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14.</note> true ſight of God and Chriſt is had onely by the light of his own perfections; and when <hi>wee ſee light</hi> it ſelfe, 'tis by, and <hi>in his owne light,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> notes: wee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 36. 9.</note> our ſelves, alas! ſee Chriſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely and everie good. We are by nature darkneſſe it ſelfe: which thing ſhewes that the light of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſight is ſuper-ſenſuall.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96098:7"/>
But would you know the parts of this worthy ſight, glorious viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? then your election's good: theſe times have made <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> many, and the great queſtion that now is, is this: friends! what newes have you: but alas for us all! that things of Chriſt are as things unheard of to ſo many. Would you ſee the ſights above the world? weel preſſe after perfection in the principles thus.</p>
               <p>1. Right ſight of Chriſt is to ſee him as he is: <hi>when Chriſt appeares he ſhall be ſeen as he is.</hi> The moſt <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 2.</note> of men ſee the Lords Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly, rudely, untowardly<hi>:</hi> Theſe have no right viſion: Chriſt ha's an inamouring glorie. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! Is it ſo in your eyes? doth his beautie ſteale away your hearts? have you obſerv'd him well? is he the faireſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in your eſteeme? doth this lovely Lord delight your ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſenſe of ſeeing? why ſhould
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96098:8"/>
it not? Chriſtians are not filled with heare-ſaies concerning Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, they will aſcend to live above means in the uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>David</hi> had an <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who <hi>had no blemiſh in him from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foot,</hi> and that <hi>none in Iſrael was ſo much to be prais'd, as he, for his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> but was hee like Chriſt? If compared to him he's nothing, ha's no comelineſſe at all. Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers! can you ſee Chriſt as he is? that's your worke, and that's the ſight of worth: if you cannot now doe it, ere long yee ſhall; when yee come into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of your Father. What though you doe <hi>but ſee in part now,</hi> becauſe Meſſiah's but in part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd? It doth not here appeare what Saints ſhall bee, or what Chriſt is, and will be unto them hereafter. Glorie muſt reveale what grace cannot. Little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! mind theſe thiags, ſee him as he is, ſee his glorie, behold
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96098:8"/>
that. A child of God will beſeech his Father to <hi>ſhew him his glory</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18</note>. So <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt ſaith, <hi>wee beheld his glory.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <p>Verbum non ſimplieitèr videre ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat ſed ſpectare, <hi>i. c.</hi> diligentèr &amp; fixè intueri aliquid ſeu novum &amp; admirandum ſpectaculum <hi>Ianſen</hi> in Concord. Evang.</p>
                     <p>Spectavimus ſeu novum &amp; admirandum ſpectaculum <hi>Eraſ.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> eſt cum admiratione &amp; ſtupore in ueti <hi>Beza</hi> in oecumen. Quaſi in theatro diligentèr, perſpicaè, hilariter, cum dijudicatione &amp; dilectatione. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </note> ſaw it intentively, viſibly. Chriſt's Glory is a Chriſtians Crowne, and his owne glotie ſha'd ſerve Chriſt: veile to Chriſt's glorie, as the Angels cover their faces, <hi>viz.</hi> their glorie in the preſence of his: much glorie gives much light; 'tis light in darkneſſe, life in death, and joy in heavineſſe. When he ſhewes you his glorie 'twill tranſport you, as <hi>Peter</hi> in the transfiguration<hi>:</hi> 'twill force you to ſay, <hi>'tis good to be</hi> there where glorie is reſplendent: 'twill cauſe you to crie out; <hi>let us make this our manſion,</hi> pitch our tents here. Obleſſed Diety! humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96098:9"/>
is beſt lodg'd, when moſt loſt in this matchleſſe glorie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, right ſight of Chriſt is experimentall. To ſee Chriſt for a mans <hi>owne ſelfe,</hi> and ſoule, with a mans <hi>owne eyes</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>and not another.</hi> Hearing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 19.26, 27.</note> of Chriſt by the eare ſerves not Saints turnes: a heartie feeling of his inward workings is that a Chriſt-knowing Chriſtian ſeeks moſt after. Some are all for heads fulneſſe; but a right ſpectatour of Chriſt covets hearts fulneſſe of Chriſts holy preſence; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty motions towards Chriſt, by Chriſts power, ſavour more with ſavorie Chriſtians then headie notions of Chriſt among acuteſt wits. To diſcourſe of Chriſt is ſweet and good; but to ſeed on Chriſt is much better. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<hi>!</hi> doe you feed and eat hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this bread of God? Is it good to you? do's it doe good in you? anſwer for your ſelves, you worthies of the world to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96098:9"/>
come<hi>!</hi> Can you ſay, I <hi>behold the Lamb of God that takes away</hi> my ſinnes, as well <hi>as the ſinnes of</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that come to the Father by him? Can you ſay with <hi>Job: be's my Redeemer:</hi> with <hi>Mary, my God, Lord, and Saviour:</hi> my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, my Interceſſour, and Peace-maker? now <hi>bleſſed are you then; and the eyes that ſee the things that you ſee</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lu.</hi> 10. 22, 23.</note>. You are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Chriſt's owne ſweeteſt lips. Who then can curſe when Chriſt do's bleſſe? Care not then for the worſt of foes; but be ſtrong in the Lord thy ſtrength and thy redeemer.</p>
               <p>Now, to inſix this principle on your ſpirits, note theſe things. Experience hath a teaching and teachable vertue in it, 'tis the beſt teacher, as our Proverb runs. For</p>
               <p>Firſt, it ſtrengthens memorie, can put on, record all, the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, movings, and workings of Chriſt towards a Chriſtian's
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96098:10"/>
ſoule. 'Tis called by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers <hi>Multiplex memoria,</hi> 'tis remembrance upon remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, mercies flowing into the mind of beleevers: experience is the matter of <hi>multitudes of thoughts</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 19.</note>
                  <hi>:</hi> It makes the thoughts of God many in the minds of the good.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it ſtrengthens affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; too one, that hath a heartie <hi>taſt</hi> of <hi>the Lord</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 8.</note> Chriſt from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; ha's a heartie love to him: Will you heare the voice of experience? 'tis this. O taſte and ſee how good the Lord is? ſuch a one's well affected, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting alſo all that follow Chriſt: the warmth, Spirit and life of ſuch his kind of ſpeaking; is found verie taking in the hearts of ſound Diſciples, and doth diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver whence 'tis, whether 'twould, and to what it tends.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it rectifies the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. One that ha's had a through, inward, ſenſible, and inviſible,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96098:10"/>
pledge of Jeſus Chriſt, his dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt love and neareſt communion with his owne ſoule: that man or woman hath right thoughts of Chriſt, and his owne eſtate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; for <hi>the thoughts of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are right</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.5.</note>. And hence, and onely hence, 'tis that he ſpeak's right words of Chriſt? <hi>Job's</hi> friends had not <hi>Jobs</hi> experience, were not ſo much acquainted with God, and the nature of his dealings with himſelfe, and his: and what followes? <hi>God ſaith they ſpake not right things of him as did his ſervant Job</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 42. 7.</note>. All other ſorts of ſayings of men, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt, are the ſpeakings out of a mans ſelfe more than God.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it ſtrengthens the will to elect Chriſt and Chriſt's things. One that hath drawne water out of this well of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the well's owne bucket, and ha's drunck a hearty draught of the water of life; his will, to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96098:11"/>
ſpeake out Chriſt, and his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, goes beyond his power. And ſad he is with <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>hee cannot doe the good hee would.</hi> I ſpeake of one that hath drawne good from Chriſt with Chriſt's owne abilities; ha's received him in his owne manner; ſuffer'd him to abide in him according to his owne order. And now marke well the evill of the contrary ſtate: by what a man ha's when he wants experience.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'twill be but a borrowed light, ſight, and apprehenſion that you'l be proved to have uſed; and the evill of that's very great: in theſe reſpects. Firſt, 'twill be your ſinne: for you are bound to uſe and improve your owne talents, not to build upon another's foundation *: a ſnare, which (to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 20.</note> the Apoſtles comfort) hee did eſcape. Secondly, 'twill be your ſhame: you account it a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and are aſhamed to be ſeen on this day in borrowed gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96098:11"/>
but 'twill be greater cauſe of ſhame at the laſt day, to be found cloath'd with no better perfections, then the borrowed parts, and acquired arts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: to have no knowledge of Chriſt but what is traditionall: taken in from creatures like your ſelves. What a great ſhame and unſpeakable bluſhing will it cauſe in you then; when you ſhall bee ſtrip't of all your bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed garments, and ſhall ſeeme as you are there; who would not be as you ſeem'd here? Thirdly, 'twill bee your Judgement: you <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 24. 31.</note> ſhall be judg'd for not uſing your owne gifts, and that in a right manner. Wee have a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>every man ſhall anſwer for his owne ſinnes,</hi> and 'tis as true, that every man ſhall anſwer for not uſing his owne graces: <hi>Every one ſhall give account of himſelfe to God</hi> *, ſaith the Scriptures: of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 12.</note> himſelfe and his owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the Kingdome of grace.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96098:12"/>
Fourthly, 'twill be your loſſe, you have no more then you uſe, and ſo: uſe 'tis even ſo with us all: we enjoy no more then wee doe experimentally imploy. What good wilt be to me to diſcourſe plauſibly of a rich mans treaſure, when the meaneſſe of my being, &amp; courſe of living, plainly ſpeaks 'tis none of my owne? and what good will all thy parts and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doe thee, when thou ſhalt die of this diſeaſe, non-experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall acquaintance with Chriſt? who will know you then as little as you know him. The loſſe will be of theſe things. Firſt, loſſe of time: time might be better ſpent relating to a mans owne benefit, and reſpecting that. Secondly, loſſe of labour: the Apoſtle was what hee was <hi>by the grace of God which was in him,</hi> and tells you that <hi>grace was not given</hi> him <hi>in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>vaine</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>'T was not made voyd.</hi>
                  </note>, 'twas not loſt labour. May we not truly ſay of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſight of Chriſt, as <hi>Job</hi> did
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96098:12"/>
to his friends of ſpeaking out the truth. <hi>O! how forcible are right</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 6. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>words?</hi> and we ſay too, O! how forcible is a right ſight of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to ſee Chriſt, is to ſee Chriſt as a man is ſeen of Chriſt, and for the ſame reaſon, to the ſame end: 'tis to <hi>know as you are knowne, and to apprehend that, for which alſo</hi> you are <hi>apprehended of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Or rather</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>If I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that, for which I am comprehended.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt ſees all the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and windings, and ſecrets of his peoples hearts: all the firſt riſes, motions, and conceptions of things within their ſecret parts. There's nothing in his, hid from him, ſo ſhall Chriſtians ſee and know Chriſt one day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that for ever: ſee all he is and ha's: what thoughts hee ha's had of them from the beginning<hi>:</hi> what a world of love ha's been, and is ſtor'd up in his bleſſed breſt for them<hi>:</hi> they ſhall ſee the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all his mercies and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions towards them: and in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96098:13"/>
Sonne you ſhall ſee the Father, and how little cauſe you have had in this world, to ſay <hi>will God be mercifull no more: ha's he forgotten to be gracious;</hi> ha's he ſhut up his loving <hi>kindneſſe in diſpleaſure?</hi> how little reaſon can bee render'd for ſuch deſpaire: there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in God and Chriſt, that's communicable to the creature which ſhall bee hid from thee; thou precious child of a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Father<hi>!</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>know as thou art knowne:</hi> this is to ſee Chriſt cleerely: this is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous viſion; but 'tis not had till you have entered the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt lookes on a poore Soule that he may fall in love with it. Chriſtians<hi>!</hi> how doe you ſerve Chriſt? doe you ſet your eyes, hearts, and hands on Jeſus Chriſt that you may ſhew your love to him, lay faſt hold on him, and with <hi>Jacob</hi> not let him ſtirre from you, till hee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96098:13"/>
ha's bleſſed you with right-hand favours?</p>
               <p>How ſtands your hearts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt? Are you well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards him? do's look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breed liking, and liking long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your breſts, and ſpirits af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much of him? Let me tell you, if your ſight be right which you have of him, 'twill ſerve you ſo; the more you ſee <hi>him,</hi> the better you like, and long for his ſocietie.</p>
               <p>And now, diſtreſſed ſoules! whom ſinne and the Serpent ha's ſtung, behold a Jeſus, looke up to the author of grace and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: what! will you die in your ſinnes, and be damned for ever, rather then that the Lord Chriſt ſhould worke his will upon you, pluck your ſins from you, which are as your right hands and eyes unto you? are you good at bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? have mercie on your ſelves and precious ſoules, and mind theſe things <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>For</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96098:14"/>
Firſt, all heires of everlaſting life longed to ſee Chriſt before their deaths, and had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. What made old <hi>Simeon</hi> deſire to depart this world in peace but this? He had ſeen Chriſt as well by faith as ſenſe. What put <hi>Paul</hi> into his two great ſtraights, a loathneſſe to die, and a loathneſſe to live<hi>:</hi> a deſire to die, and a deſire not to die<hi>:</hi> but this? Hee had ſeen much of Chriſt. Me thinkes I ſhould heare you ſay of Chriſt, as <hi>Jacob</hi> of his <hi>Joſeph, 'tis enough my ſonne's yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gon.</hi> 45. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I'le goe and ſee him before I die.</hi> Seekers of Chriſt<hi>!</hi> what thoughts have you? what words fall from you concerning this thing? your Saviour's alive, will live for ever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and doe not you long to ſee him before you die? If not, your graves will be Sepulchres both to you and your comforts, and you'l lie downe in ſorrow. And, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſoules! Let me tell you from the Lord, 'tis a miſerable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96098:14"/>
thing to ſee death before you have ſeen Jeſus Chriſt. To die Chriſtleſſe is to die a Godleſſe, graceleſſe, and heaven leſſe wretch: to make a worſe end than bruits. Unſanctified ſoules! where is the ſounding of your owne bowells for your owne welfare? do's not thy heart quake, and all thy parts ſhake to thinke of the ſlighting of a Jeſus, and of <hi>tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling under foot his moſt precious bloud?</hi> It had been better for thee thou hadſt ne'r had being then not to have a well being in the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Will you heare the language of a Chriſtleſſe man at the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-day? 'tis this<hi>: Mountaines and rocks fall upon me, and hide me from the face of him that ſits upon the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.</hi> All ſuch mens Joyes have a <hi>mar-mirth</hi> with them: when ſuch an one dies, all dies with him: his ſinne being excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which ſhall ever live in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96098:15"/>
memorie of the Lord of Hoſts, and give life to the parties owne miſerie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, your neceſſitie call's for it <note n="k" place="margin">Ingens te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. <hi>Liv.</hi> O quantum cogit egeſtas!</note>: you muſt mind him, for you want him: neceſſitie is made a cauſe of minding ſomethings: Chriſt tells of ſome that would not ſup with him, would not come at him; and what thinke yee was the cauſe? one had <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed ground, and he muſt ſee to it; Another had bought cattell and hee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lu.</hi> 14, 18, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt prove them: A third had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a wife, and hee could not come,</hi> would be excuſed: for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie made them all doe it. Alas poore ſoules! is it a fault to own a Chriſt, accept of a Jeſus, a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Is it an offence in your eſteeme ſo to doe, that ye would be excuſed for it? Or is it a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that you beg to bee excuſed from it? the Lord lay no other burthen on my owne ſoule, then Jeſus Chriſt his yoake, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with my ſpirit. But who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96098:15"/>
can read, without remorſe of heart, and moiſtned eyes, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne that Chriſt made to thoſe unworthie perſons, and their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie ſayings? <hi>Not one of them</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall taſte of my Supper.</hi> Tender hearts! do'ſt not trouble you to ſee faithleſſe men ſo much their owne foes, as not to taſte of Chriſt's Supper? And, incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible ſinners! Doe you know and feele the weight of this cenſure, ſentence? 'tis not to eat of the tree of life, which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God<hi>:</hi> 'tis not to have the leaſt mouthfull of hidden <hi>Manna:</hi> not to have any thing to doe with the bread of God, and food of ſoules; 'tis to have all wants and no ſupplies to be wretched, poore, blind, and naked; and yet not in the way to receive one mercie. See you not what 'tis then to ſupply the wants of an outward man, by increaſing the wants of an inward?</p>
               <p>Does neceſſitie cauſe an aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96098:16"/>
man to have a worldly mind? ô! what neceſſities, like thoſe of the ſoule? what wants are more piercing, diſtreſſing, and vexing, then inward wants? I tell thee no mortall wants ought ſo much as immortallitie: you have need of him for <hi>Wiſdome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Sanctification, and Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that in all your ſervices hee may pray in you, pray and plead for you to your heavenly Father; worke in you, and worke for you his owne bleſſed will and worke, and to preſent you, and what's yours, blameleſſe before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſence in life, death, and at the Judgement day. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<hi>!</hi> Doe not ſtormes drive men into a harbour? and doe not Warres conſtraine men into ſtrong Caſtles and holds? oh then! Let wants drive thee unto a Chriſt, and let him drowne thy ſelfe in himſelfe, who's the ocean of ſupplies.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a right ſight of Chriſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96098:16"/>
gives a right ſight of ſelfe, and ſelfes eſtate; men ne'r ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo well, as when they moſt ſee Jeſus Chriſt. Chriſtians! You may ſee in Chriſt what you have been, are, and ſhall be. What you have been.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what excellent creatures yee were, when yee ſtood in your firſt Parents: how exquiſite that righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe was, in which you were firſt made, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lords owne likeneſſe: but you have loſt it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo the ſight on't, ſuch as it then was; but you may, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſt againe, find it in him: as a ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hee ha's done, do's, and ever will keepe his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, ſtation, and perfection, without any the leaſt alteration: you may ſee in him what glorious ones you were, before yee were caſt out of an earthly Paradiſe. This is the myſterie, yee ſhall know by him, what you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you were, what a bleſſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96098:17"/>
eſtate ſtanding man was in, what an excellent nature he had before it was loſt, how well hee might have lived, and all his poſteritie, had hee not ſinn'd with outward ſenſes, and ſtain'd his inward ſoule: hee ſinn'd with his ſenſes by hearing with his eares, the praiſes of the fruit, beholding it with his eyes, touching with his hand, and taſting with his palate. Thus ſinne, entring by his ſenſes, got into the world, and death by ſinne; himſelfe being made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, with all his poſteritie by that act.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what you are,</p>
               <p>Firſt, by degeneration: how much unlike what you once were. When you ſee his holineſſe, doe not you ſee your owne unholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? when you ſee his puritie and paſſing Sanctitie, doe not you by meanes of that ſee your owne impuritie and ſurpaſſing depravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Will you heare what a God-beholding man ſaid once,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96098:17"/>
'twas this: <hi>Woe is mee, for I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, becauſe I am a man of uncle an lips, and I dwell in the mids of a people of uncleane lips, for mine eyes have ſeen the King, the Lord of hoſts.</hi> 'Twas his trouble (and hee gives the reaſon;) that his <hi>lips</hi> were not <hi>cleaner,</hi> like the Lords, and that his ſocietie was ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, that it did unfit him for communion with the higheſt God and King: it pierced his honeſt heart that he had no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a part of the Lords holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in him. Chriſtians<hi>!</hi> When you ſee the Lords lowlineſſe, doe not you ſee your owne loftineſſe? When you ſee Chriſts humility, doe not you ſee your owne pride? When you ſee his clemencie, cannot you then ſee your owne naturall crueltie to your ſelves and others? ſo alſo by the light of his patience, you may ſee your owne paſſion: by his kindneſſe to you, your own unkindneſſe to him, by all his faithfullnes, your
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96098:18"/>
own unfaithfulnes, &amp; by his fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in good, your own barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s?</p>
               <p>Secondly, by reſtauration: what a vaſt difference is betwixt grace and the beſt refined nature? Moreover, there's now a more firme union betwixt thy ſoule and God, then was betwixt God and man at that time: for had the union then been as ſtrong as now, <hi>Adam</hi> had ne'r loſt himſelfe, and his by ſinne: the oneneſſe that's betwixt God and his people is ſuch, that they can never any more be parted and taken aſunder<hi>:</hi> beſides all this; <hi>Adam</hi> was left to himſelfe, and to his own will<hi>: to chooſe whether he would ſtand or fall:</hi> But now Chriſtians are not left to themſelves, and cannot have their will; God will never leave them, nor forſake them, and they ſhall ne'r fall more ſo to indanger themſelves and ſoules, as he then did: for God is both able and willing to make them ſtand. Is not this to ſee your
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96098:18"/>
ſelves truely, and fully, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe're you are, uprightly, and what you are not in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; ſurely no viſion is like this, no ſight like this.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what you ſhall bee. It do's not here appeare what you ſhall be; but in Chriſt, and where Chriſt is, you may plainelie, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and throughly be reſolved of that<hi>:</hi> for when you <hi>ſee him even as he is,</hi> ſo ſhall you your ſelves be: Chriſt breathes out ſweetlie this ſelfe ſame thing: <hi>Father! I will that thoſe whom thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>me be with me where I am, that they may behold my glorie.</hi> Chriſt's glorie is transforming: he'l have you with him, that you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him: and what's the iſſue? 'tis this<hi>:</hi> you'l be changed into the ſame glorie, you cannot eſcape it, there you, <hi>with open face, as in a glaſſe beholding the glorie of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from glorie to glorie, and that of the Lord the Spirit</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. Can a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96098:19"/>
repreſentation of his glorie, by a <hi>medium,</hi> transforme ſo ſweetlie? Ha's glorie ſuch a power? Oh then! what will it doe, when wee ſhall behold it without meanes, more clearelie then a glaſſe can repreſent it?</p>
               <p>Fourthlie, all right ſight of Chriſt ha's in it a ſuſtaining na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a heart-releeving vertue, a ſoule-reviving abilitie: things of Heaven are all ſupporting, much more Chriſt himſelfe, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is the Heaven above, as he's God equall to the Father: doe you want an experiment of this alſo? the Apoſtle gives you one, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17, 18.</note> when he tells you that, Chriſt and all his <hi>obedience</hi> is &amp; was for your ſakes; adding that for this cauſe <hi>wee faint not in the periſhing eſtate of the outward man,</hi> whil'ſt <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is renewed day by day,</hi> whileſt <hi>light affections</hi> worke us unto, fit <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> us for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, maſſie glorie; and all this, <hi>when wee looke not at things which are ſeen; but at things</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96098:19"/>
                  <hi>which are not ſeen.</hi> When the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſoule's loſt in her unſeen Saviour, ſhee's ſafe and <hi>takes her reſt; for the Lord makes her dwell in ſafety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt's ſouldiers<hi>!</hi> pray tell me, what ſeen power and might ſuſtained you in all your ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all warefare that you have had? I can tell you none at all; for when you were in the field againſt ſinne, Satan, the world, and ſelfe, had you not all the Lords owne armour on? <hi>The helmet of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, breſt plate of righteouſneſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 13. to 18.</note> 
                  <hi>the girdle of truth, with the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God, and above all the ſheild of Faith, whereby you were able to quench all fierie darts</hi> ſhot and darted at you, your ſoules and peace<hi>:</hi> and, when you were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, did not Chriſt ſtand by you, with you, and in you? Did not he <hi>teach</hi> your <hi>hands to warre, and ſingers to ſight,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes? had not he your hand in his, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96098:20"/>
cauſed you to give ſome mortall wounds, kill that which would have kill'd you your ſelves, ſoules and all: which being gone, all was gone with you. Who ſtood by <hi>Joſhua</hi> when he <hi>called on God, and Satan ſtood at his right hand to reſiſt him?</hi> was't not <hi>the Angel of the Covenant,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.</note> who, when the Tempter accuſed him for <hi>ſtanding before the Lord in filthy garments,</hi> did excuſe him, remove his <hi>rags,</hi> and give him <hi>robes?</hi> and does not Chriſt ſtand everie Chriſtian in the like ſtead? Sure I am, if ever you did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and were not foiled in the Lords fights and fields, 'twas thus with you. O how precious, and how cordiall are the thoughts of theſe things! the number where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no end yee know. Who then that's wiſe deſires not to ſee Chriſt, and himſelfe in Chriſt, before hee behold his laſt, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and approaching change and diſſolution? 'Tis a bleſſed thing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96098:20"/>
to be able to graſpe Chriſt and death in the armes at once, at one and the ſame time, and is't not an everlaſting curſe to die Chriſtleſſe? <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> and you'l find it ſo.</p>
               <p>Finally, let the Lord perſwade <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> you to bee endeared to Jeſus Chriſt; ever ſet him in your ſight, looke up to him, who looks downe towards you; for he's the Author and finiſher of your graces<hi>:</hi> would you know the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, of ſuch right apprenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, then conſider theſe things ſincerelie.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'twill increaſe inward Joy. Have you a mind to be merrie? be much in this, and 'twill make you right glad: other mirth may end in mourning; but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, this makes the <hi>ſpirit rejoyce in God its Saviour,</hi> (as ſhe ſaid) there are many Joy-makers, as friends, eſtates, the treaſures and pleaſures of this life; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tell you of <hi>a joy of harveſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:96098:21"/>
                  <hi>and a Joy of heart; a Joy of harveſt</hi> is verie great, but this brings <hi>joy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 3. 65. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of heart,</hi> both great and good, a cordiall Joy. Precious ſoules! <hi>ſow precious ſeed weeping;</hi> but a precious Chriſt being the fruit, they reap their crop ſinging<hi>:</hi> ſome <hi>ſow in teares,</hi> weeping, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſighing, roaring, &amp; wailing after this deareſt Lord, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; but when they find him, themſelves are found <hi>to reape in joy:</hi> Righteous ones! what though as the Spouſe you have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.</note> ſeeking him, <hi>whom your ſoules love,</hi> even earlie and late, <hi>by night,</hi> as well as day, and have long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd ſocietie with him, yet have not <hi>found him,</hi> and your ſelves in him? Conſider, he ſeekes as well as you, ha's loſt as well as you: beſides, when hee finds you, and you him, <hi>you'l hold him faſt;</hi> and ſo good is he, you'l not <hi>let him goe;</hi> Chriſt told the <hi>Jewes</hi> that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham rejoyced to ſee his day, did ſee it, and was glad.</hi> And ſenſuall world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 56.</note>!
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96098:21"/>
what e're you deeme of ſuch a favour, it skills not, ſure I am, that a right ſight of Chriſt, will make a right-ſighted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian glad at heart; nothing do's him ſo much good as this: ſmall things cauſe laughter in the face, when the heart's a ſtranger to the Joy; but this, as 'tis the nature of great things, will make the heart glad, even then when the face of a man, and face of times is verie ſad: the comforts ariſing hence are <hi>meat</hi> for Saints <hi>to eat, which the world knowes not of:</hi> and now a word to you that would glorie in ſomething, what can be your <hi>glorie?</hi> which ſhall not bee <hi>your ſhame,</hi> beſides the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>God ha's ſaid. <hi>The wiſe man may not glorie in his wiſdome; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 23, 24. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>the mighty man in his might, nor yet the rich man in his riches.</hi> Why? who ſhall glorie then? and in what ſhall men glorie? if not in ſuch deſireable things; well <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96098:22"/>
hath ſaid, <hi>Let him that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, glorie in this, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, and knoweth mee, that I am the Lord, which exerciſe loving-kindneſſe, Judgement, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe on the Earth: for in theſe things I delight.</hi> God ha's ſhew'd you what to glorie in, gracious ſpirits<hi>!</hi> 'tis in your acquaintance with him: when you know, and underſtand him aright; ſee him as he is; <hi>viz.</hi> full of loving-kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Judgement, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, one that acts as he is: 'tis his delight to doe ſuch things? Beleevers<hi>!</hi> are you like him, by looking upon him? are you chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this reſpect? Marke well, what it is you glorie, delight, and take pleaſure in.</p>
               <p>Secondly, 'twill ſtrengthen pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience under the croſſe and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizement for Chriſt: doe you ſuffer from the hands of <hi>unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men?</hi> and would you be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of them, as of your enemies? looking up to Chriſt you'l find<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96098:22"/>
he's not yet aveng'd of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: do's God ſuffer, &amp; ſhall not man? does the head <hi>endure the contradiction of ſinners againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi> and can the members think to be free? Is't not all reaſon in the world, that head and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſhould bee fellow-ſharers, in the ſufferings of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die myſticall? who dare denie it? 'twas a ſweet ſaying of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witneſſe to the truth of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who ſeem'd to faint, under his great triall; and being offer'd a cup of ſpirits, to ſuſtaine him, replied thus; My Lord, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had gall, and vinegar given him: as if he had been aſtonied, to ſee himſelfe fare better then Chriſt: and indeed, experienc'd Chriſtians! when you thinke in ſufferings you are ſerved ill, you ſhould conſider, ſweet Chriſt was not ſerved ſo well: that will ſtill your murmurings; for can you ſuffer as much as hee ha's done? I tell you nay: yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96098:23"/>
do's the event or end of things, bring cares upon you? why! <hi>James</hi> commands you by the Spirit, to behold, and <hi>ſee the end</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 5. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lord.</hi> You may thinke your troubles will end ill, have an evill end; but God can put a good end to ill beginnings: as ſome things may be ſweet to the taſte, yet bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the bellie; ſo other things may be unſavorie, in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, which may be better in, and by the ſecond; though in things naturall, or corporall it is not ſo, as Phyſitians have ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of right Regeneration.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FAlne man's riſing is graduall, firſt, by Grace, and next by Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: by man came the maladie, and by man alſo comes the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie: a fruit leſſe firſt birth may be repair'd by a ſecond: by</hi> Adam <hi>ſinne entered, and reigned unto</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96098:23"/>
                     <hi>death, and by</hi> Adam <hi>grace ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, reigning unto life, ('tis the ſecond</hi> Adam <hi>that now I meane) Grace can make up, what nature ha's loſt; amend what nature hath done amiſſe: Firſt, birth's privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is nothing: Second, birth's priviledge is all things, all in all, referring to felicitie:</hi> Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>antecedes</hi> Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>He that's borne but once dies twice; but he that's borne twiſe ſhall not taſte of the ſecond death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt-births are an Embleme of the ſecond; ther's a certaine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe betwixt them both: we'l give you a hint of the whole thus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt, naturall births bring ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, both on the bearer, and on that which is born: the mother ha's her pangs and thro's, and the child's in ſtraites too, till it's brought from the womb, into the world: ſpirituall births bring ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings alſo, the Spirit that brings forth is a ſufferer too, as well as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96098:24"/>
doer, it being <hi>quenched.</hi> Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chriſtians! you can tell, that you have often <hi>quenched the holy Spirit,</hi> even in all its motions, ſtrivings, and conteſtations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you. Have not you when the Spirit ha's diſwaded from evili, and perſwaded to good, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted its ſweeteſt motions? how ſeldome have you moved with the Spirit, againſt the fleſh, and for the Lord? aske your hearts this queſtion, obedient ſonnes of God: where, almoſt, is that man, or woman, that's kind to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? gives it good entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Ah Lord! thy Spirit meets with hardeſt meaſure, from our fleſh: and is't not <hi>grieved, vexed,</hi> and <hi>reſiſted</hi> alſo? if men goe one ſtep further, which is to <hi>deſpight</hi> it; they have done their worſt againſt it, and their owne ſoules alſo. Theſe are the ſteps which reach to Hell. Take heed you tread not the firſt of them, <hi>quench not the Spirit.</hi> 'Tis a verie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96098:24"/>
ſad thing, to ſinne ſo fowly, that if a man ſinne's but one ſinne more, he fall's finallie: next to <hi>reſiſting,</hi> comes <hi>deſpighting,</hi> and then how can you <hi>bee renewed by Repentauce?</hi> Is not this to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the loſſe of a precious ſoule deſperatelie? and to be unkind to the Spirit immenſlie? than which what is more diſmall? the Spirit ſuffers, being <hi>quenched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then the fleſh, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers being croſſed, in all its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: In the ſecond birth, right Regeneration, all who are Chriſt's, have their <hi>fleſh crucified;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>with the affections,</hi> paſſions, <hi>and luſts,</hi> proud fleſh is beaten downe, and Chriſt's humble Spirit ſet on high<hi>:</hi> in ſuch a ſoule, love to ſinne, is the life of ſinnne; if you loath it 'twill die: hatred unto it is a wounding of it, who knowes not this, that knowes Jeſus Chriſt? and hates ſinne, as 'tis hatefull, and makes hatefull? ſinne is, or ſhould be to Saints
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96098:25"/>
more hatefull then all things, and to creatures moſt hurtfull. When nothing elſe is hatefull, or can make ſo in the ſight of God<hi>:</hi> Will you mind what one borne of God ha's ſaid? 'twas this, <hi>I hate the evill I doe.</hi> Love of ſinne muſt die, when love of Chriſt will live, and be lively: luſtings after ſinne are leſſened too; if not whollie mortified: one of the Lords births, though he ſinne, yet he hungers not after it, doe's not thirſt to commit it, ha's but liſtleſſe deſires towards it, and troubl'd he is, that he doth at all deſire ſuch an undeſirable thing; hee would faine be, and doe, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then hee is, and does, though his fleſh be croſſed, and himſelfe, made to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in naturall birth's, the bearers bowells yerne towards the babe i'th birth, leaſt it ſhould prove abortive; right glad's the parent, to ſee the child live, and doe well: her ſaying's like his,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96098:25"/>
                  <hi>is my ſonne ſafe? deale gently with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.32. &amp; 5.</note> 
                  <hi>him for my ſake.</hi> In ſpiritual births, the bearers bowells yerne too<hi>:</hi> the Lords bowells worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards babes in Chriſt, leaſt they ſhould miſcarrie; and loath is hee that poore ſoules ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, die in ſinne and be damned. Hence thoſe ſayings, <hi>how ſhall I give thee up? how ſhall I doe this?</hi> or that <hi>againſt thee?</hi> God would rather bring up, then give up, or caſt out any ſoule: will you marke his ſaying in ſacred writ? 'tis this, <hi>I deſire not the death of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: I had rather they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and live, turne you, turne you,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>why will you die? Is Ephraim my deare ſonne? is he a pleaſant child? for ſince I ſpake unto him, I doe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie remember him ſtill; therefore my bowells are troubled, &amp; doe</hi> ſound for him, <hi>I will ſurely have mercie upon him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! how glad is God when men doe prove good, live the life of Chriſt, and prove godlie Chriſtians:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:96098:26"/>
Thirdly, before the naturall birth, the babe in the wombe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not nouriſhment in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie way, but in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie manner, not by the mouth, but at the navell, is cheriſht invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly<hi>:</hi> yet cheriſh'd it is, and doe's well: In ſpirituall births, babes in Chriſt are fed too, but 'tis my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſlie, not in an ordinarie way, the ordinarie way is pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reading, hearing, pondering, and conferring of the good things of God: but before this babe ſpirituall can tell how to uſe his mouth, how to improve this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie meanes of life ſo, as to take in nouriſhment by it; God by ſome extraordinarie way, breakes inviſiblie and ſweetlie upon the ſoule, and gives it a taſte of his ſoule-raviſhing Joyes, inwardly, ſecretlie. And yet, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ha's it, hee cannot tell you how he came by it, how hee tooke it in; ſo ſtrangely was hee raviſh'd: he feels much, but can
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96098:26"/>
ſpeake out little of the Lords goodneſſe to his owne ſoule; for is't not the nature of ſuch things to cauſe joy in the heart more than in the countenance, when other things are wont to make onely outwardly cheerfull? <hi>The wind bloweth where it liſt's, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it comes, nor whether it goes: ſo is everie one that's borne of the Spirit. Is not the way of the Lord with a ſoule, like the way of an Eagle in the aire, the way of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent on the rock, neither of which you are able to track? the way of a ſhip in the midſt of the Sea, which you cannot find out? ſo hidden and myſterious are his workings.</hi> Saints live the life of their Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſiblie, <hi>not by bread onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, before naturall birth's, babes in the wombe void not excrements<hi>:</hi> tis the ſame in this caſe: before that a man's <hi>borne againe,</hi> comes out of the wombe of ſinne, death, and Hell.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96098:27"/>
Though he have the moſt refined nature, yet voids hee not excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſinnes, filthie, defiled, and defiling garments: he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres rags before robes, that's his follie; Experience! ſpeake thou, is't not true? Let the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencers of the Lords ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries crie out, and crie on, ne'r ſo oft, if you live in your ſinnes, you ſhall die, die the death of Devills themſelves, yet you'l ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver part with your excrimentall ſinnes, till you are come through the ſtraights, and felt the pangs of the new birth. <hi>O! that men were wiſe and would conſider this thing,</hi> wiſely, and well: who would not long to be borne againe, to have a new nature, and name; and be made like to Chriſt?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, in naturall birth's, <note place="margin">Homo epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me mundi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> babes are borne crying, as the Philoſopher notes. In ſpirituall birth's, babes of Chriſt are borne crying too: Grace in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an will doe like grace, lead him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96098:27"/>
to the Throne of grace, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with the God of Grace, through Jeſus Chriſt: while he's living he's crying, and praying to the living God, and well-ſpring of everie good. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! when you were firſt chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, had your eyes firſt opened, did you not, as well as now you doe, hunger after Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion? was it not verie ſweet unto you, when in all your wants you were carried out unto the God of ſupplies? and was't not a great eaſe to your ſpirits, when you could, and did poure out your ſoules before him? Babes of Chriſt! when borne, doe ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho to their Father, crie for crie. When Chriſt cries out <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> the anſwer is, <hi>who art thou ô Lord? and what wouldeſt thou have me to doe?</hi> then <hi>Saul of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9.</note> muſt be ſent to; <hi>for behold hee prayes,</hi> ſaith Jeſus<hi>: he prayes.</hi> God ſaith to his child, <hi>ſeeke my face,</hi> and the child's heart anſwers, <hi>thy</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:96098:28"/>
                  <hi>face Lord will I ſeeke,</hi> ther's like for like. Saints love to retaliate with their God: would you heare the heartie crie of a heartie Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? 'tis this. <hi>As the hart panteth after the water brookes, ſo panteth my ſoule after thee oh God! my ſoule thirſteth for God, for the living God;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 42. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>when ſhall I come, and appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God?</hi> the ſweeteſt preſence of ſweeteſt Majeſtie is refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that, babes of Chriſt doe know full well.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, a babe of the naturall birth, in the day of its nativitie, is a poore, polluted, helpleſſe, and ſhiftleſſe creature, ha's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what's given it, nor ha's it a power to deſerve any thing. 'Tis an object of loathing to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: but is not an object of love almoſt to any, and 'tis ſhiftleſſe, it may lie and ſit ſtill, as in the open field, to the loathing of its perſon; but cannot ſtirre head, hand, or foot, to help it ſelfe, to releeve it ſelfe. So in the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96098:28"/>
do's not God, when hee comes in, to change men, find them in their bloud, polluted, with a navell uncut, unwaſhed, not ſalted, unſwadled, not pitied, and much loathed? and who can ſhew mercie to ſuch, if God did not? did not God caſt his skirt over ſuch, how naked would they be and appeare? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.4, 5, 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>7. A child of the naturall birth, being brought forth, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of nature lives lingring after the mothers breſts<hi>:</hi> ſo in the ſpirituall, the new-borne child lives hungring after the breſt's of Chriſt's conſolations, and that by an inſtinct of grace; were there no meanes to ſtirre up, no reward to accrue, yet babes of Chriſt could doe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but long after <hi>the ſincere milke</hi> of Gods word, <hi>as new borne babes,</hi> that they may grow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. The pureſt word and freeſt <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.</note> from mixture is that, they moſt covet. Chriſtians! what are your
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96098:29"/>
deſires? and how ſtrong are they this way? you ſee what ſome by an inſtinct of grace can doe: be you wiſe in heart then, prove your ſelves, and tell me: is this your worke?</p>
               <p>Eightly, a new-borne babe, ſucking, is ſatisfied with ſincere milke, and that alone, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can pleaſe it, ſatisfie, or appeaſe it's crying-out loud<hi>:</hi> ſo in the ſpirituall, when a poore ſoule ha's rang'd the world through for delights and fulneſſe, ha's tryed all wayes and meanes to quiet it ſelfe; at laſt it ſits downe, finding no reſt in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and reſolves, <hi>the Lord ſhall be its reſting place,</hi> and when it wants the comforts of this life, yea, ſometimes even bread for his hungrie ſtomack, it can goe to his Fathers houſe and home, and there find bread enough, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the bread of God: can bee content with the breſts of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when, if you give it all the world,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96098:29"/>
you cannot ſtill it, fill it; for its wanting ſtill: but at the breſt it can ſuck, and bee delighted with the abundance of that glorie, as the Prophet ſpeakes. <hi>Oh ſweet</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>God! how good art thou? and how much good do'ſt thou to the ſoules of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now let all ſeeke after this <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> as after hidden treaſures. <hi>viz.</hi> to be borne againe. God do's you a greater favour, when hee makes you live the life of Chriſt, than <note place="margin">The life of grace is farre beyond the life of nature.</note> when he cauſes you to live the life of man. 'Tis a more bleſſed thing by innumerable degrees to be borne twice than once; for the one can but give you ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into an earthlie <hi>Canaan</hi> at the beſt, which do's not alwayes doe ſo well, the other gives you enterance into an heavenly one, which birth never do's amiſſe to any. Who, that's wiſe, will then boaſt of his naturall birth, when hee ha's ne'r come under the power of the ſpirituall, ne'r felt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96098:30"/>
it's pangs, nor been partaker of it's priviledges? Careleſſe ſoules! doe you want a ſpurre to this purpoſe? conſider! as there is a paritie betwixt them, ſo there is a diſparitie in reſpect of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the one above the other.</p>
               <p>For firſt the natural is by carnall copulation, and is a fleſhlie Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; <hi>the firſt man is of the earth, earthie: and how can hee bee cleane,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>that's borne of a woman?</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ha's ſaid. But the ſpirituall is by a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 25. 4.</note> union and communion of God and Chriſt with the ſoule of man, and is a ſpirituall Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: he that will <hi>enter the Kingdome of God</hi> muſt <hi>be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of the Spirit:</hi> ſaid Chriſt: and that which is ſo <hi>borne is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as <hi>that which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh. The ſecond man is the Lord from Heaven.</hi> Doe not you ſee then, the laſt is more noble then the firſt, and that the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall excells? who, conſidering
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96098:30"/>
this, deſires not to bee borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? 2. The ſeed of the naturall is corruptible, mortall, may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and die; but that of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall is incorruptible, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, remaines for ever. <hi>Yee are borne againe,</hi> (ſaith the Scripture) <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>not of corruptible ſeed; but of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, by the word of God,</hi> which lives and abides for ever. <hi>He that is borne of God ſinneth not,</hi> that is, not unto death, and why? marke that; <hi>for the ſeed of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in him:</hi> the ſeed that's in <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 9.</note> him is of an immortall nature.</p>
               <p>3. In the naturall the conception is ſinfull: <hi>David</hi> tells his God that hee <hi>was ſhapen in iniquitie, and in ſinne did</hi> his <hi>mother conceive</hi> him: and may wee not all trulie ſay to each other, as the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to the blind man, <hi>thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together borne in ſinne.</hi> I am alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether borne in ſinne, ſhapen in ſinne; ô vaine man! why boaſts thou ſo much of thy noble birth, who know eſt nothing of thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation?
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96098:31"/>
But the ſpirituall is a holy conception of the grace and goodneſſe of a good and gracious God: a gracious ſpirit can tell you he is what hee is <hi>by the grace of God that is in</hi> him. Are not <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 10.</note> all the conceptions of Gods Spirit in the ſoule like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; verie holy, verie ſpirituall, verie heavenly? what concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons like them, or to be compared with them? Surely none. In the naturall, birth men are borne bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh<hi>: vaine man would be wiſe; but he is borne like a wild aſſes colt.</hi> Men by nature are cruell, croſſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 11, 12.</note> perverſe, unteachable, hard to be intreated: but by grace, holy, heavenlie, harmeleſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the naturall, babes are born to griefe, ſorrow, and trouble. <hi>Although afflictions come not forth of the duſt, neither doth trouble ſpring out of the ground, yet man is borne to trouble, as the ſparkles flie upward.</hi> 'Tis naturall for a man to know ſorrow. But in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96098:31"/>
he's borne to peace, Joy, and quietneſſe. When a man's begotten againe, he's <hi>begotten to a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>lively hope, to an inheritance uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, and undefil'd, that fades not away, reſerv'd in Heaven for</hi> him. And are not <hi>the fruits,</hi> or births <hi>of the Spirit, Love, Joy, Peace, Goodneſſe, Faith,</hi> and the like? By the naturall birth you are brought forth into a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, irkeſome world; but by the ſpirituall out of troubles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace. <hi>In the world</hi> babes of Chriſt <hi>ſhall have trouble; but in him they ſhal have peace which paſſeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>underſtanding.</hi> Now tell me, you wiſe virgins<hi>!</hi> whether <hi>Martha,</hi> or <hi>Mary ha's choſen the better part?</hi> Whether Heavens quietneſſe bee not better then earth's cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances? whether intereſt in Chriſt, and by that, a right title to the creatures bee not better, then a portion in the creatures by uſurpation without Jeſus Chriſt? By the ſpirituall birth privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96098:32"/>
you inherit all things: by the naturall nothing<hi>:</hi> although you poſſeſſe ſomething. You have ſeen what the ſpirituall birth is by its likeneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likeneſſe to the naturall: wee'l now ſhew you how God brings in, and brings up returning ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, He principles them.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, acts them.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, builds them.</item>
                  <item>And fourthly, confirmes them.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, God is ſaid to principle man, when, by uniting himſelfe to the ſoule by his Spirit, he do's inviſiblie ſow the ſeeds of all grace in the heart at once; grace is called the ſeed of God. Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſpoſeth for communion, communion corroborates uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a paſſive reception of Chriſt that now I meane; that, whereby a principle is begotten in the will. Chriſt joynes the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96098:32"/>
meanes and end together: ſo ſhould the godly doe Election, vocation, Juſtification, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Humiliation, then comes the end which is glorification.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt acts them, drawes out thoſe principles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt, his firſt act is illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſhines out from Heaven with a cleare light upon the hearts of men, and upon their wayes. Light was the firſt thing that appeared in the old Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and 'tis the firſt that appears in the new Creation alſo<hi>:</hi> Light <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1.</note> was the firſt ornament of the world, wherewith the Lord <hi>decked it as with a garment</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Anſw.</note>, and this light is Chriſt. For, <hi>yee were once dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe; but are now Light in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord:</hi> Light diſcovers darkneſſe: Regeneration is a tranſlation from darkneſſe into light. True Converts! how like you that; his light diſcovers ſinne, all the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt ſecrets of cloſeſt hearts, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96098:33"/>
Juſtice incenſed againſt the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? Light diſcovers the uneve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a mans way, and what it is in the account <hi>of Juſtice it ſelfe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>This light's immediate.</hi> (Chriſt in you the hope of glorie) it ha's no meanes of conveyance, but acts like it ſelfe, ſcrutinouſly: the light of this Sunne, like the wiſe mens ſtarre, never leaves a ſoule till 'tas lead it to a Saviour, a meanes of eſcape from all ſinnes evill; Divine light informs men on whom <hi>the Lord hath laid help,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>even on one that's mighty,</hi> and able to ſave: that's the next act of il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination, <hi>viz:</hi> a diſcovery of the ſufficiencies, as well as the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, of a Jeſus; that he's able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come unto God by him; and that he can in no wiſe caſt out them that come unto him: it brings glad tidings to ſad ſoules: ſinne may bee mightie; but Chriſt is mightier, will ſubdue it<hi>:</hi> ſins may be many; but Chriſt's mercies
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96098:33"/>
are more: ſinnes may be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie incenſing; but Chriſt is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pleaſing unto an offended Majeſtie, and ſinners in the Sonne cannot bee diſpleaſing unto the Father: he loves light, for hee dwells in it: this divine light re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 16.</note> all. Returning ſinner! why droopeſt thou? Can thy ſinne undoe thee, when 'tis laid on Chriſt? ſad ſoule<hi>!</hi> why weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou <hi>as one without hope?</hi> canſt thou bee worſe then whom God ha's pardoned, and Chriſt ha's purchaſed, cleanſed, and ſav'd? Thinke not ſo, leaſt thou ſinne againſt the remedie it ſelfe. Light from Heaven will reveale Chriſt to thee, and thee to thy ſelfe, thou ſinking ſoule! thy wants and Chriſt's ſupplies ſhall meet together; then doe not diſtruſt of that.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chri'ſts ſecond act in man, by which hee drawes out his owne principles, is humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, begetting in the ſubject
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96098:34"/>
low thoughts of ſelfe, and all ſelfes worth: ſhall I tell you what they ſay ſincerelie, whom God and Chriſt, by the Spirit ha's humbled? 'tis this, <hi>I am a worme and no man. I am not worthie to be call'd a ſonne, make me as a hired ſervant. I am the leaſt of all the Saints: yea the leaſt of all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Oh! that I were but a doore keeper in thy houſe.</hi> Chriſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles whom hee will exalt<hi>:</hi> Gods method is firſt to lay low, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſet aloft: yet note you, 'tis truth in the inward parts he chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aimes at<hi>:</hi> ſome are ſo gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in putting upon much, that they prove irregular in diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging little; though truth of grace; ſelfe-loathing alſo, for ſelfe-defilements, joynes hands with this grace<hi>:</hi> would you know how Chriſt humbles, breakes the heart kindlie? 'tis thus<hi>:</hi> by ſetting himſelfe with his wounds open before their eies; as peirced by their ſinnes. <hi>I will powre upon</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:96098:34"/>
                  <hi>my people a ſpirit of grace and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication:</hi> marke that: <hi>and then they ſhall looke on him whom they have pierced, and mourne for him as one mournes for the loſſe of a firſt borne.</hi> Can you looke on a pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 10.</note> Chriſt, you flintie hearts! and not be broken, pierced your ſelves? if you doe, 'tis becauſe the Spirit of grace is not poured out upon you. When <hi>Peter</hi> ſet forth a crucified Chriſt, were not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2 36.37.</note> 
                  <hi>his hearers pricked at the heart,</hi> when they beleeved, through grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that they were the verie men the preacher meant? Could his lookes fetch teares from <hi>Peters</hi> eyes, and will not his wounds doe the like to others? what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? This is Chriſt's way, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe men kindlie; and who more kindled in love to Chriſt than ſuch who are ſo laid low? you ſee his acts, and his wayes to effect his bleſſed will on man. Chriſt ha's his ends too in humbling ſuch as he'l ſave<hi>:</hi> we'l ſhew what
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96098:35"/>
his ends be as briefly as may be.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt humbles that hee may inhabit, <hi>he dwells in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Heavens, with him alſo, that is, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a contrite, humble, and low ſpirit, to revive him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as it is uncomfortable not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 15.</note> to dwell in God, ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, 'tis diſconſolate not to have a God dwelling in us: are not Cities and Kingdomes without Inhabitants verie ſolitarie? even ſo is a ſoule without God, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie diſmall, verie uncheerefull. Chriſt's preſence is reviving, this Chriſt knowes, and thus hee humbles that hee may inhabit, make the heart his mantion, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place. <hi>God dwells in higheſt heavens, and loweſt ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſtians are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to make them lovely in the ſight of the Lord: An humble ſoule is a comelie one, meekneſſe is a great inward <hi>ornament; is in the ſight of God of great price:</hi> a <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4.</note> proud heart is void of Chriſt's
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96098:35"/>
comelineſſe weares not his robe of graces. Conſider! Do's God prize, greatly prize the meeke in heart, the quiet in ſpirit? then you! that ſtudie to bee eſteem'd of him, covet to bee humbled by him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt humbles that he may exalt<hi>: When thou wa'ſt lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in thine owne eyes, wa'ſt thou not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>made head of the Tribes of Iſrael, and the King over them?</hi> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> to <hi>Saul.</hi> When <hi>Saul</hi> thought himſelfe one of the ſmalleſt of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and his familie the leaſt of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin;</hi> then God made him greateſt. But when he waxed proud, and reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Lord, and his words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to him by his Prophets, God rejected him; and <hi>his latter end was worſe then his beginning:</hi> doe not you now obſerve a vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the fruits of God's humbling man, and mans exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe? marke the end of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96098:36"/>
each operation, and then tell mee, i'ſt not ſweet to be laid and kept low by Chriſt; that this grace may have its perfect work in you, as well as other graces: let all true converts ſpeake: Is not Chriſt moſt advanced by man, when man's moſt abaſed by Chriſt? who can denie it?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt makes hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that he may bee familiar with the humble ſpirit: God and Chriſt is a ſtranger to the loftie in heart, will not be familiar with them as a man with his friend: will you heare the Lord himſelfe ſpeake, who beſt knowes his owne mind in this principle? 'tis this. <hi>Though the Lord be high, yet hath hee reſpect to the lowlie; but the proud he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth afarre off:</hi> hee knowes them; but 'tis at a diſtance, not as friends nearely alied to his bleſſed ſelfe: he knowes them as enemies and uſeth them ſo; hee reſiſts, the proud, but gives grace to the humble. Many incomes from the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:96098:36"/>
higheſt Heavens have the loweſt ſoules: Chriſt do's not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when a man's downe, adde afflictions to his bonds, deject; or reject a ſoule that's dejected alreadie; but when he's downe, helps him up, when he ha's much trouble, gives him much peace, for much ſorrow, much Joy, <hi>garments of joy for the ſpirit of heavineſſe</hi> to humble hearts: he's called a <hi>God that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts thoſe that are caſt downe;</hi> but <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 6.</note> he's to the proud a ſtranger, ô ſweet Lord! there's none like to thee, nor are there any workes like thine.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Chriſt humbles to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, thoſe he'l ſave to himſelf, as wel in grace, as glory: Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was humble, and faine would he have his to be, and doe, like him: <hi>Learne of mee</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>for I am meek and lowly of heart.</hi> How ſweet a deſigne is this? what<hi>!</hi> doe all Chriſt's acts prove transforming, is all he doe's done to change us into the ſimilitude
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96098:37"/>
of himſelfe? ô great myſterie<hi>!</hi> bleſſed is hee that underſtands it, and improves it. To bee like Chriſt is to enter glorie in this terme of life, to be in part what we ſhall be for ever compleatly: for what's the glorie of the juſt and children of God in Heaven, but their likeneſſe unto Jeſus Chriſt? When <hi>John</hi> ſpake of great things to come in glorie not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, he ſummes up all in this one ſaying; <hi>we ſhall be like</hi> Chriſt. Humilitie makes man the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 2.</note> of Chriſt<hi>:</hi> for he was hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but pride makes man the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of Satan, the Father of Pride; <hi>as proud as Luciſer,</hi> that's the world's proverb concerning ſome: but how glorious would it be, were it poſſible to find men as humble as Chriſt? Humilitie is Gods Creature, pride is the Devills<hi>:</hi> you ſee then how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a grace it is as well as faith and love with other graces: then ſuffer your ſelves to be made like
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:96098:37"/>
Chriſt in this, and admire his goodneſſe in this excellent end he propounds in his workings in you, and actings of you, for good, becauſe <hi>the pride of a man ſhall bring him low, but honour ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the humble in Spirit.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt's third act in, and on man is his bringing up the ſoule, and infixing of it to the object ſo apprehended by it. Men are mightily prone to ſeeke out ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny comforters: but Chriſt will have his to have but one, and in him all true contentments. Chriſt firſt removes all props that a ſoule might reſt on, and take comfort in, on this ſide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Is it proſperitie that ſome leane on? when they are ſetled on their lees, and have their cares of Chriſt, &amp; ſoule choaked, he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that into adverſitie, and then in their afflictions they'l <hi>ſeeke him early:</hi> when Chriſt withdrawes himſelfe, returnes to his place, they'l acknowledge their offence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96098:38"/>
and ſeeke his face whoſe preſence was not prized before: when men ſmart by outward and inward wants, then ſupplies from Chriſt are deſireable, verie ſeaſonable. Chriſt will teach mercies worth by its want, to thoſe hee loves: health is beſt prized in ſickneſſe, riches moſt prized in povertie, libertie's moſt priz'd in infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>So Chriſtians learne to prize the ſweetneſſe of their Saviours preſence, by the bitterneſſe of his abſence: doe we doate on friends? Chriſt will take them hence; to let us know there's no friend like Chriſt: thus he cleares it out to the ſoule, that all props beſide himſelfe, are <hi>broken reeds,</hi> that will deceive when moſt weight is laid on them, or <hi>broken ciſternes</hi> which hold no water when wee thinke there's moſt in them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt removes all obſtructions that hinder conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:96098:38"/>
with him. Do's unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe diſcourage? Chriſt aſſures them he's worthie, and hee is ſo in himſelfe for their ſakes, and that living waters are powred out to thirſtie ſoules freely<hi>:</hi> that ſuch have moſt of Chriſt, and receive moſt from Chriſt, who carrie leaſt unto Chriſt: that a man's owne Righteouſneſſe effects not, nor can his owne unrighteouſneſſe hinder, his Juſtification, becauſe men are juſtified freely by his grace, and that there is one who juſtifies the ungodly; if they bee returning backſliders: that it's more pride then humilitie to keepe from Chriſt meerely for a mans unworthineſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt workes in the heart a true perſwaſion, on Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ground, that himſelfe and all his benefits are made over to ſuch a perſon in particular, that hee may <hi>know that</hi> his <hi>Redeemer lives, that he ſhall ſee him for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 19. 25.</note>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:96098:39"/>
that he is his God, his Lord, his Saviour, his Mediatour, his Interceſſour, his Advocate at the Throne of grace.</p>
               <p>Chriſt's third act is a building of them: when Chriſt ha's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 6.</note> materialls, then he falls to building.</p>
               <p>Chriſt builds Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by keeping them and all their graces in continuall action: there are ſometimes <hi>fightings without, feares within,</hi> to exerciſe <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 5.</note> grace, to quicken faith, patience, and watchfulneſſe: God ſuffers ſometimes one corruption to get ſtrength, ſometimes another, to keep them doing, as well as beleeving, fighting as well as fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: ſometimes unruly paſſion ſtrives to reigne, then the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſtrives <hi>that patience may have its perfect worke,</hi> at another time worldly ſorrow fills the whole man, then the ſtrife is, that all ſorrow may be turned into ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſinne: now cares of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:96098:39"/>
carcaſe eat a man and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts up, then meanes is uſed that the ſoule be car'd for too, that all cutting cares be caſt on God, for hee cares for his owne, while Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan tempts to deſpaire: another while he tempts men to preſume, this makes worke for grace, do's not weaken, but ſtrengthen grace, for vertue gets ſtrength by wounds. Adde to this, pride, vaine <note place="margin">Vireſcit vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, virtus.</note> glorie, hearts hypocriſie, forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, ſenſualitie, incredulitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, deadneſſe of heart, dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in divine ſervices, froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, untowardneſſe, unwatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, coldneſſe in affections, weakneſſe in deſires after Chriſt, badneſſe of memorie, miſpending mercies, time, talents, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, abuſes of Chriſt's love, breach of bonds and Covenants, relapſes, recidivations, and the like.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by infuſing ſtrength ſutable to oppoſitions: ſome, like <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> task-maſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:96098:40"/>
much worke, but give no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities thereunto; but Chriſt is no ſuch Maſter, if hee laies bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens on a ſoule, he gives a heart and parts able to ſuſtaine it. Which of his ſervants did e're come into great ſtraights, who had not great helpes? Some have ſlept on the cold ground and were healthfull, when in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick employments for Chriſt? whereas being wearied in their owne perſonall employments, though they have repoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on beds of downe, been well fedd, and warmely clad; yet could they not have health and lifes vigour in them. Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minding Chriſtians have ſaid it<hi>:</hi> and ha's not he promiſed to <hi>lay no more on you then you are able to beare?</hi> is not this a <hi>ſpecimen,</hi> that he's a mercifull Maſter? if affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions bee many which ſurprize the Saints, ſtrength ſhall bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven either of bodie or mind to uphold them. When the Lord
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96098:40"/>
foreſaw that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and much oppoſed in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah,</hi> be accuſed before <hi>Gallio;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 14.</note> how thinke yee hee was enabled for the encounter? 'twas thus: the Lord Chriſt <hi>appear'd to him in a viſion,</hi> ſaying<hi>: Bee not afraid, but ſpeake, and hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot thy peace,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>for I am with thee, and no man ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee:</hi> hee had great tryalls; but hee had great ſtrength: the ſtrength of God was with him, the arme of God wrought deliverance for him. In all afflictions God obſerves a meane, is never in the extreame, hee ha's ſaid he'l <hi>correct in meaſure,</hi> yet will not leave men altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 11.</note> unpuniſh'd: he has <hi>a rodde,</hi> and hee ha's <hi>a ſtaffe</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes: yet ſo pitifull is he, that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.</note> he'l not cudgell a weakely child; for that were to breake his bones, becauſe he is tender, and a ſwitch, or rod may ſuffice. O ſoule! con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, thy Saviour can tell how much thou ſmart'ſt under everie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:96098:41"/>
twigge he layes upon thee, and how much thy heart breakes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der everie blow receiv'd from him: then conſider; would'ſt thou in patience poſſeſſe thy ſoule, and ſelfe, under all thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings? thy abilities and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are with thee in meaſure, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee by meaſure. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, what though ſinne bee a grace-weakning vice, yet if grace be afforded in proportion, ſinne ſhall periſh, when grace will flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; ſo well workes God in the ſoules of his ſervants, and upon their ſpirits. Is not this to bee <hi>built up,</hi> and that <hi>upon the rock Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> who's a ne'r failing, firme foundation? tis to grow accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>to the meaſure of the ſtature of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a cauſing of his to live onely upon himſelfe, and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Father: to live above all things; even thoſe things which would be above them, and keep them under. Shall I tell you, yee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:96098:41"/>
diſconſolate ſoules! what Chriſt, firſt or laſt, will cauſe you to live above? They're ſuch things as theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt helps his to live above corruptions<hi>:</hi> would you know how? 'tis thus, by giving ſoules a ſight of pardoning pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as well as a ſenſe of incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſins, and imperfect ſervices. Some pore too little, others ſo much, upon their ſinnes, that they have ſcarce a <hi>heart</hi> to ponder their Saviour, or any of his ſweeteſt ſayings; are liſtleſſe lovers of the Lord Jeſus. Sad Soules! let me tell you, your ſinnes doe keep you under. Diſcouragements with feares and diſtruſt, have ſurpriz'd you, got above you; and will not this thing, if allowed of, make you goe drooping, ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mourning to your graves? what's of more force to kindle diſcomfort within your breſts? God would have men bee ſenſible of ſinne, ſtand, and goe under it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:96098:42"/>
as under a <hi>heavie burthen:</hi> but ſhall ſenſe of ſinne bee ſuch, as that it ſhould hinder from the ſight of the Lamb, who is the meanes of eſcape from its evill, ſtaine, filth, guilt, and power? <hi>God forbid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt cauſe's his to live above temptation: and that's thus: When they in the time of greateſt temptation, being aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are made to reaſſault Satan, and ſtand, or elſe if they doe fall, makes them fight even falling, with their weapons in their hands: when though they are ſlaughtered, foiled and doe fall, yet they cannot be overcome. As hee ſaid of perſecuted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note n="*" place="margin">Occidi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terant, vinci non poterant, <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Deo duce non poteſt eſſe dubius belli eventus, <hi>Eraz. Mar.</hi>
                  </note>. And can the event of that fight be doubfull, where the Lord is the Leader? I trow not. Chriſt makes Chriſtians doe like himſelfe in ſuch à caſe; retort back the Serpents owne ſubtill arguments to him againe. When Satan alleadged Scripture to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:96098:42"/>
Chriſt to ſinne, hee alleadges Scipture to prove he ſhould <hi>not tempt the Lord God;</hi> but ſerve him: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> ſo, when Satan cenſures a ſoule to his face, &amp; which is more, even to &amp; before the face of God, ſhould he doe. Do's the Tempter ſuggeſt unto thee. Thou art a caſt-away, art wicked, and therefore thy ſelfe, and ſervices are an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord, that many better than thy ſelfe are in Hell, that thou art an hypocrite, doeſt but diſſemble, wilt fall away, come to nothing, haſt ſinn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, and that thy day of grace is paſt? 'tis ſweet to replie as he, <hi>who art thou that condemneſt?</hi> 'tis a <hi>Chriſt that died, yea rather, that's riſen againe, who is ever at the right hand of God, who alſo makes interceſsion for us.</hi> Therefore <hi>Satan get thee hence; for thou ſavoureſt not the things which be of God,</hi> and thou ſhould'ſt not thus tempt the ſervants of Chriſt, who are one with him,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:96098:43"/>
as 'twere <hi>bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh,</hi> and much more. Thus not to give place to temptation, is to overcome it, and live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it; 'tis to bee firmely built upon the rock of ages, Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt in building helps ſome to live above graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evidences: and that after this manner: working the ſoule to a cloſe with, and dependance upon an abſolute promiſe, when the glorie of an evidence, from the conditionall promiſe, is eclips'd.</p>
               <p>Ther's a time when ſome of Gods deare children ſtagger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the promiſes and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall performances. Gracious ſpirits! you can tell, that this is your very caſe. Alas for ſome! how hardly doe they live, and how uncheerefull doe they ſpend their dayes on earth: becauſe the Comforter, who ſhould releeve their ſoules, is farre from them? as the Church once ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:96098:43"/>
Others alſo would be glad at the heart, could they graſpe Chriſt in the precious Promiſe, by a precious Faith; and what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders this? even this is the thing, corruption and carnall reaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervenes, comes between the ſoule and home. Hence objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are rais'd againſt God, Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, Chriſt, Promiſe, ſelfe, and all; becauſe the evidence is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, do's not at all exiſt. To ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſuch, build up ſuch, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Father of mercies, as well as Spirits, to convince and perſwade the ſoule, that he'l ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie what's wanting, will heale back-ſlidings freely, worke both will and deed fullie, and thus hee ſuſtaines the ſoule in life, raiſes it up as it were from the grave of deſpaire, and diſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt help's ſome to live above <hi>glorious</hi> manifeſtations of his Fathers love. 'Tis after this ſort, <hi>viz:</hi> when in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:96098:44"/>
of thoſe manifeſtations, juſt ones are made to live, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the inviſible eſſence of <hi>God; viz.</hi> when they live &amp; rejoyce in the Lord, when they ſee him not, and that <hi>with Joy unſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of glorie:</hi> when a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can live waiting on him, who ha's <hi>hid his face</hi> from him, as the Prophet ſaid hee would doe: 'tis an eaſie thing to ſwimme when the head's held up; but 'tis a ſingular thing to be kept from drowning, when the whole man's kept under water. Chriſtians! through Chriſt you may and can doe ſingular things: this is one<hi>:</hi> when the <hi>Sunne is no more thy light by day, neither for brightneſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>doth the Moone give light unto thee, yet the unſeen Lord's to thee an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting light, and thy God's thy glorie.</hi> When, as the Church ſaid, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Micah</hi> 7, 8.</note> thou ſitteſt <hi>in darkneſſe,</hi> yet haſt <hi>determin'd the Lord ſhall bee a light unto thee.</hi> When, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, thou ſeeſt <hi>no light of Sunne, Moone,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:96098:44"/>
                  <hi>or Starres appeare</hi> for many dayes, and yet canſt live like a child of light in thickeſt darkneſſe: tell me, tell me, thou ſpirituall ſoule<hi>!</hi> is not this to live above even glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manifeſtations of deareſt love? if not: what is't then? verilie, verilie I ſay unto thee, thou that ſo liveſt, liveſt by Chriſt, like Chriſt, with him, in him, whilſt he thus acts in thee, for thee, and by thee.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt builds his: and that hee do's by cheriſhing and nouriſhing them with heart-ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing comforts and ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Chriſt's comming into a ſoule is verie reſtorative, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſolicitous with her is verie inſtructive: when hee comes to her, much good comes along with him; for he ne'r comes into an emptie heart with an emptie hand. <hi>He filleth the hungrie with good things.</hi> Satan's all for emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiing the ſoule of good things; but Chriſt is all for filling:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:96098:45"/>
Chriſt makes his abound towards Heaven and heavenly minds. Did you ever ſee ſuch a gueſt, you keepers of his Temple<hi>! which is within you, which you have of him?</hi> do's not his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome make you rich to keepe open houſe for ever? Alas my friends and worthies of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world! when hee firſt uſed your hearts, his houſe, you were worth nothing, had nothing but ſinne, that's nothing, 'tis but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, emptineſſe<hi>:</hi> what inſides had you? and how uncleane were they? and were your outſides ought but bodies of unſanctified parts? what were all your <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> leſſe than <hi>weapons of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> raiſed up both againſt your ſelves and Saviour alſo? was not your whole man a ſlave of Satan, his captive priſoner? now when he repaires you, puts a glorie upon you, diſpoſſeſſes Satan in you, fills your hearts with himſelfe, do's hee not then
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:96098:45"/>
build you up as a ſpirituall houſe for himſelfe? True Converts! anſwer to the queſtion, is not this one thing that Chriſt hath done for you, in your converſion from ſinne to himſelfe? is not this courſe the meanes of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and breeding up your ſoules; for the heavenly Academie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove? is not this to make you fit to be <hi>partakers of that inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in light?</hi> Do's <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 12.</note> not this kindneſſe deſerve a gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thanks to the Father, who ha's made you ſo?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt confirmes his; even thoſe he will ſave.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by giving them ſome ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledneſſe of Spirit, concerning their finall condition; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what a man ſhall bee in the end, and for ever, is the great Queſtion; and moſt ſtated by ſome: and when the Spirit ſpeaks, that it ſhall bee everlaſtingly well, then the ſoul's ſafe. What breeds doubts, fear's and diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:96098:46"/>
ſo much as this? whence are thoſe cries? I am a wretch, ſhall be damned, and goe to Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> am a caſt-away, have deceived ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and am deceiv'd my ſelfe, whileſt I ſeem'd what I was not, and ſo beguiled my owne ſoule. There's no mercie for me, I have ſo ſinn'd againſt it: Chriſt dyed not for mee, ſuch a one as I, there's much in God; but nothing for mee, my heart's hardned againſt the uſe of meanes. Is't not hence? their unacquaintance with the certaintie of what their condition ſhall be? for then, the Serpent ſubtilly winds himſelfe in; and makes the condition of ſuch to be worſe than 'tis. Now, when Chriſt, the Sunne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, doth ariſe, ſhining in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and upon that ſoule, all thoſe miſts of ignorance and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour are ſoone diſper'd, and then at the laſt the unſetled ſoule is made ſteadie, you cannot move it: though feares ariſe, and doubts
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:96098:46"/>
be many, and trialls more, yet this is the reſult of all in ſuch a ſoule; well, let God doe what hee will with mee, I'le hang on him: <hi>though he kill mee, yet will I truſt in him.</hi> I have many rubs in my heavenly race; but I ſhall get through all at laſt: I am often brought to call in queſtion what my finall eſtate is: but yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay but God ha's done ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in me, ſure I am, I would not allow of ſinne for all the world, and, if my heart deceives me not, I would be better then I am, would faine love God, ſerve him and feare him, that's my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and I doe not ſinne; but I am troubled at it, troubled in the actings, and it brings me on my knees to the God of pardons. Thus it pleaſeth <hi>Jehovah</hi> to work ſecretlie the ſoules ſettlement in a fit ſeaſon, which may fitly bee called Chriſt's way of bringing up his children.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by aſſuring them of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:96098:47"/>
his abilitie, and activitie to keep them from a totall Apoſtaſie, and fatall deſtinie. Will you know how, confirm'd Chriſtians ſpeake? 'Tis thus. When <hi>I fall I ſhall ariſe.</hi> God, firſt, or laſt, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 8.</note> that truth upon the ſoule, which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeakes of<hi>: Viz:</hi> that, <hi>though a good man fall he ſhall not be utterly caſt downe:</hi> and what's the reaſon? <hi>for the Lord upholds him with his hand.</hi> Feares, of falling from Chriſt in tribulations that attend Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or towards the cloſe of time, keep ſome under, makes them ſad, till Chriſt confirmes them, and makes them glad. Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring grace! thou art a Jewell, and happie is that ſoule that ha's thee, and holds out to the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:96098:47"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>HEB. 11. 13, 14, 15 16.</bibl>
                  <q>And they confeſſed that they were ſtrangers and pilgrims on the earth.</q>
                  <q>For they that ſay ſuch things declare plainly, that they ſeek a Countrie: And truely, if they had been mindfull of that Countrey, from whence they came out, they might have had opportunity to have returned: But now they deſire a better Countrie, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Saints perigrination in this evill world.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEavenly minds, whileſt rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through an earthlie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are farre from their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly home: this world's a ſtrange Countrie to the worthies of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Dayes on earth, are but dayes of pilgrimage to heires of Heaven, and few, and evill, are all of them: the wiſe in heart, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet to eſcape the fooliſh ſnare, of placing ſoules reſt, and happineſſe in earthly contentments: loath are they, that full Barnes, faire ſtructures, goods, heap'd up for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:96098:48"/>
                     <hi>yeares, ſhould keep them out of their owne Countrie; the</hi> Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>above: for this were to dwell in a ſtrange land for ever, or elſe in ſome worſeplace: Citizens of Heaven are ſtrangers here.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We'lſhew you firſt, what it is to bee a ſtranger. Secondly, whence it is. Thirdly, the uſe you are to make of it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt, 'tis to bee there, where a man's out of his proper place, as a fiſh on the drie Land; and this is the caſe of all Saints un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne: when a man ha's holineſſe, Heaven's his home: he may ſeeke the things of this world, yea great things; but not for himſelfe, for God ha's ſaid, ſeeke them not: he's to bee, for Chriſt, as well as to doe for him, and to ſeeke things which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, where Chriſt ſits, at the right hand of God: hee may <hi>uſe this world;</hi> but it muſt bee ſo, <hi>as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>though he us'd it not:</hi> holy hearts!
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:96098:48"/>
you may love things below, in meaſure, putting bounds to your love; but you may not ſet your affections, fix them upon theſe things, lodge them in, and on theſe things here.</p>
               <p>When you'r about to ſet them, (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſet them on things which are above:</hi> and why? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3.</note> for <hi>your life is hid with Chriſt, in God;</hi> ſpeake out, you Denizens of Heaven! Doe not you ſurvive in Chriſt? dwell in him? Is this world your owne, and onely home? will you heare, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrangers have ſaid, that did precede you? 'twas this, <hi>our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is in Heaven.</hi> You <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20.</note> Saints, and ſervants of the moſt High! when you dwell much in, and upon the world; you doe not like your ſelfes, refin'd, but like your ſelves, depraved: not like ſtrangers in the earth, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journers in the world; but like great houſholders, laſting, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie inhabitants.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:96098:49"/>
Secondly, He's a ſtranger who lives, under the dominion, of a ſtrange King<hi>: the children of this world</hi> live under the reigne of <hi>the God of this world;</hi> who ha's <hi>blinded their eyes,</hi> and hardned their hearts, ſo as that they are waxen fat, and full; as though they lack'd nothing, if not, what meanes their ſubjection, laying downe of their necks, to the yoak of the Lawes, cuſtomes, fancies, and faſhions of this world? what's the reaſon, they <hi>follow</hi> the <hi>multitude to ſinne; and drinke in iniquitie; as the fiſh do's water?</hi> Is't not hence? they're under the rule, and Regiment, of the <hi>Prince that rules in the aire; and workes in the children of diſobedience:</hi> Prophane ſoules! do's not this ſpeake you, <hi>ſtrangers in Heaven? and unto the life of holineſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world?</hi> What can you ſay for your ſelves? and what reaſon can you give, why that ſentence of the Judge, ſhould
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:96098:49"/>
not paſſe upon you? which is, if you amend not, you <hi>ſhall not enter into</hi> his <hi>reſt:</hi> and making excuſes, to keep your ſelves from Chriſt, <hi>ſhall not taſte of</hi> his <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> eat of his dainties; are your actions a captivation of your ſelves, and affections, to Chriſt: or Satan, ſinne, and the fleſh, who are Antichriſts? Conſider it ſadlie; for your caſe is put ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie, as to the buſineſſe in hand: Now the worthies of the world to come, are ſtrangers in this land; for this verie reaſon, they have another King; are the ſubjects of another Kingdome; and are guided, rul'd, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd, by the Lawes, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of that Countrie, which is above; whence they come, and to which place, at the end of their travailes, and the travailes of their ſoules, they ſhall returne.</p>
               <p>Beleevers! you are, or ſhould be govern'd, by the Law of the Spirit of life: a Law of love, an
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:96098:50"/>
inwritten <hi>Principle</hi> receiv'd, from Father, Sonne, and Spirit; ſo that were it poſſible, you ſhould not know the Law Morall, yet would you not be as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14.</note> of ſome juſtly; <hi>a Law unto</hi> your <hi>ſelves?</hi> would not grace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, and the divine nature, conſtraine you, into a dutifull frame? doe not dutifull chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren love to doe duties to their Parents? Not to bee, and doe, like ſonnes, is to force an abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Father<hi>:</hi> what! could Heathens, <hi>having no Law, doe the things contain'd in the Law; and that by nature?</hi> and ſhall Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doe leſſe with grace, which do's ſo much excell, the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined nature? The Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, they had an <hi>inwritten principle;</hi> viz. <hi>the worke of the Law, written in their hearts:</hi> ſo, Chriſt's familiars! make report, doe not your ſoules long to bee ſubject unto Chriſt? are not you under his Dominion, if ſo,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:96098:50"/>
that proves you, bleſſed pilgrims, and ſtrangers here.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he's ſtranger-like, <note place="margin">Ad placitum Principis.</note> who, lives in a land, or leaves it, onely at the pleaſure of the Prince; ſuch ſtrangers are Saints here; when God the King of Saints pleaſeth, their beings muſt receive their periods: God hath put bounds to earthlie beings; and 'tis from the good pleaſure of his will, to Chriſt's co-heires.</p>
               <p>Strangers to Heaven as well as ſtrangers on earth, have boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> beings too?</p>
               <p>But 'tis not pleaſure, 'tis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> from God to them, ſuch forbearance, is an effect of wrath, not of love<hi>:</hi> 'tis but his willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſhew his wrath, and make his power knowne, that <hi>hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures, with much long ſuffering, the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>veſſells of wrath, fitted, to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle.) <hi>What though all things come alike to all</hi> (as the wiſe man ſpeakes) and that <hi>there is one event to the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:96098:51"/>
                  <hi>and to the wicked;</hi> yet ther's <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 2.</note> Gods good will appearing to the one, whileſt his ill will breakes forth in the events of the other: the good man ha's peace in his end, whileſt <hi>ther's no peace to the wicked ſaith my God;</hi> but <hi>they are like to the raging ſeas which caſt up mire and dirt.</hi> Saints are here at the good pleaſure of their Prince, and therefore ſtranger-like on earth, ſo alſo is their ſubſtance with them at the good pleaſure of his will: get what they can, God will have the diſpoſing of it in love. You ſee then, heavenly Inhabitants! you are not this worlds children, that, <hi>the houſe you muſt put on, is a houſe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, immortalitie, everlaſting life:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2.</note> and this is that home the Lord would have you groane earneſtly for, that you <hi>may be cloath'd</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he's a ſtranger, who ha's double duties and burthens laid upon him, becauſe he's not
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:96098:51"/>
a peculiar native of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie where hee dwells: ſuch are Saints while in the bodie, and dwelling here; for they have burthens of their owne to beare, and they alſo beare the burthens of other men.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of their owne? they have that, made burthenſome to them, which is not made ſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to earthlie men: ſinne is their burthen, both the ſinnes of themſelves and others: though God ha's laid the iniquitie of Saints on his Sonne, that they ſhall never be their burthen here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and that themſelves ſhall never feele their weight for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet ha's hee made their weight heavie to them, whileſt in the bodie. <hi>My iniquities are gone over my head, and are a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then too heavie for me.</hi> The good man could not ſtand under the burthen, when the crie of his crime was aſcended on high, and tells you he ha's <hi>no reſt in his bones,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:96098:52"/>
                  <hi>nor ſoundneſſe in his fleſh, by reaſon of his ſinne.</hi> That he's <hi>troubled with it, and bowed downe greatly:</hi> that it makes him <hi>goe mourning all the day long.</hi> What though 'tis better to feele their preſſures here, than lie under them in Hell? yet, in that they are a burthen to Saints here, and not to ſinners, it demonſtrates them ſtrangers in this world. For men of this world find not ſinne ponderous in them, they can ſwallow it downe without any the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, checke, or curbe given to it. But ſinners<hi>!</hi> what though you're incenſible now? you ſhall find your ſenſe of feeling hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I can gueſſe at your diſeaſes: ſuffering grieves you more than ſinning? ſinne is your Heaven, ſuch as 'tis: if not; what means your complaining and crying out of the one, but not of the other?</p>
               <p>Secondly, burthens of others: the ſinne that others feele not, becauſe 'tis in them as its proper
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:96098:52"/>
place, even that (I ſay) makes the Saints know ſorrow. A righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoule's vexed, fretted, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from day to day, whileſt hee <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note> heares, ſees, and obſerves the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull deeds of men: and 'twas ſuch a trouble to the Prophet, that <hi>rivers of waters ran downe his eyes, for the breach of the Law: viz.</hi> abundance of teares ſhedd he for other mens ſinnes: whereas, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! in this age, men are ſeldome ſeen to weep for their owne ſins. Oh <hi>England!</hi> thy people grow in knowledge, but not in practiſe; they're all for ſpeculation. Many of thy people know ſin; but few there are who have a heart to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſinne. Ile tell thee thy diſeaſe; thou art Judgement ſad, but not ſinne ſad<hi>:</hi> Joy ha's ſo much tranſported ſome (whether headie or heartie, let experience ſpeake) that there's little growth of other graces found. Faith, Love, Patience, Meekneſſe, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, Mercifulneſſe, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlie
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:96098:53"/>
kindneſſe are rarities in theſe tottering times. <hi>Ah Lord! what will the end of theſe things be?</hi> Engliſh Atheiſts<hi>!</hi> muſt Saints beare your burthen here? what then? why? you ſhall bear't your ſelves hereafter<hi>:</hi> ungratefull hearts<hi>!</hi> you have melting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, whoſe <hi>ſoules weepe in ſecret places for your pride,</hi> whoſe eyes weepe ſore, and runne down with teares on your behalfe; ſuch ſtrangers have burden enough, and more then they can beare, did not <hi>God lay help on one that's migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> they have burdens of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too. Both their owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: the Saints have many reall feares, ſorrowes, ſufferings, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſmitings, within; which the children of this world feele not, many ſower morſells, and many a bitter cup which others taſte not of; is not this to be us'd like a ſtranger? what feares of falling? cares of ſtanding? de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of beleeving, living, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:96098:53"/>
the Lord Jeſus, are there found in them, that are not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? and are there any ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes like to theirs? Children of this world are ſafe in the hands of Satan, who acts them, and workes in them; hence they are not diſturb'd, not moleſted, and tormented by him, as Gods children be; who can have no reſt in the world by reaſon of him, and ſinne which is his creature: when any reſt they take, 'tis in him whoſe <hi>dwelling is farre above</hi> this unworthie ſtation. Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers can hardly live in a ſtrange Land, ſuch is the oppoſition they have from ſundrie cauſes. Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt endure hardſhip, whileſt in the Church Militant: adde to this, the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of others, <hi>who is weake,</hi> and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29.</note> they are not? <hi>offended, and</hi> they <hi>burne not?</hi> afflicted, and their bowells yerne not, ſtirre not? certainely there's a ſweet near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bleſſed dearneſſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:96098:54"/>
betwixt united members of Chriſt's bodie myſticall: for their affections doe all runne in one, and the ſame veine; a veine of <note place="margin">3 <hi>Ep. Ioh</hi> 1. 7.</note> truth, as thoſe who <hi>love in truth, knowing truth,</hi> and for the truths ſake. When God brought evill on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>to</hi> 25.</note> the Church, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> cries out, <hi>I am the man that have ſeen affliction by the rod of his wrath. I am brought into darknes, he ha's turn'd his hand againſt me, he ha's broken my bones, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd me with gall &amp; travel, made my chaine heavie, ha's ſhut out my prayer, &amp; as for the wormwood, &amp; the gal, my ſoule ha's them ſtill in remembrance:</hi> with many expreſſions of like importance. And <hi>Paul</hi> was but one Member of the Church; yet there came upon him <hi>dayly,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>the care of all the Churches,</hi> he <hi>bare their burthen,</hi> as well as his owne; and ſo fulfill'd the Law of Chriſt. The like to <hi>Paul</hi> is the caſe of ſome now: Some one Chriſtian takes care for all the Churches: ſurely then theſe acts, ſo ſtrange
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:96098:54"/>
to the world, muſt needs prove Saints to be ſtrangers here. But whence is it, and why do's God ſerve his ſonnes and daughters thus? put them into a ſtrange Land? Let them live for a time ſo farre from home? whence is it he puts them into the hands of this world, which is ſo unkind a nurſe, to them, and whatſoever elſe is his? we'l ſhew you whence 'tis that ſo kind a father puts his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into ſuch an unkind world.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that they may ſee the vaſt difference, which is betwixt earth and Heaven: unſanctified ones ſee no difference betwixt the one and the other, all's alike to them: could they live below, and know no wants, not meet with changes, have <hi>their hearts</hi> deſire, they would ſeeke no other Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, bee content to live below, and not above the world: for Chriſt's unſavourie and verie ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to ſuch full hearts: ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient ones, who barre out the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:96098:55"/>
ſufficiences of Chriſt, keepe at a diſtance from him<hi>:</hi> ſenſuall ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content with ſeen things, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is beleeving with ſuch an one: Beſides this, <hi>Reſt is ſweet to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer,</hi> as the Proverb is; ſo Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven's then exceeding good to the godly, after their wearied ſtepps, and long and irkeſome travailes on earth: mercies are beſt, when moſt miſſed: Heaven is to Saints as the Inne to the traveller, a great refreſhment: Heaven is by ſo much the more glorious, by how much Earth's ignoble.</p>
               <p>And was't not the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, that <hi>a Reſt ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for the children of God, when the time of refreſhment ſhould come from his preſence?</hi> Is not this to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt reſt and trouble? what do's it more? Saints are bid to <hi>run ne the race that's ſet before them.</hi> Now you know there's a great diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwixt the beginning, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and end of a race: theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:96098:55"/>
foot-men have great weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, trouble, and rubbs; yea, ſometimes falls and bruiſes in their heavenly race; but the end is in Heaven, and there's reſt, with reward in fulneſſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to glimpſe out glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to a faithleſſe people, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons under their owne forme: that his <hi>light may ſhine</hi> in them, and from them <hi>in the midſt of a perverſe generation:</hi> there's much of the glory of God in his Image on the godly: hee could take them hence, and ſtate them in Heaven, as ſoone as they open the wombe; but that evill men may ſee there's ſome that love him, and live like him, as well as others that ſlight him, and live like the <hi>Prince of darkneſſe:</hi> Doe not theſe children of bleſſed light let the world ſee, by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, what a life their Father leads and lives? note this well: earthlie men are much led by examples of men, and God ſends
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:96098:56"/>
good men to give examples to the bad; yea, he ha's ſent a good <hi>Chriſt, who ha's left an example, that all ſhould tread his ſtepps.</hi> This takes off the cloake of excuſe from the back of ſinne, now men have ſeen, ther's no cloake for their ſinne; becauſe there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing imitable and obſervable, in any perſon, or thing, which may not bee found in Chriſtians, or Chriſt; in one, or other the ſons of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, beſides this; God ſends ſome into the world, even their ſtrange Land, and place of captivitie, to ſave others from fatall ruine, for a time: the Saints being in this world ſupports ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and keeps them alive: God would ſoone put an end to ſuch <hi>cumberers of the ground,</hi> did not his ſonnes ſtand in the gap: then unkind world! how canſt thou abuſe ſuch props of thy peace as theſe be? when <hi>Lot's</hi> out of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> the whole is ſet on fire: ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:96098:56"/>
when all the Lords righteous <hi>Noahs</hi> are got into the arke Chriſt, and Heaven; the whole world's deſtroyed with fire; for the Spirit ha's ſaid it, <hi>who cannot lie: that vengeance ſhall bee taken</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>by ſire, when troubled Saints ſhall have reſt, and when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be reveal'd from Heaven with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not his Goſpel: who ſhall bee puniſhed with everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting deſtruction, from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glorie of his power, when he ſhall come to be gloriſied in his Saints, and admir'd by all them that beleeve, and then ſhall</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> themſelves be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> too, with all their ſligh ſecret trickes and ſhifts, <hi>whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſſe of his comming:</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle affirmes. Then conſider theſe things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 8.</note> ſoules! eſteeme theſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:96098:57"/>
ſtrangers more, leaſt that you incurre the diſpleaſure of God, and your beings here be of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, no long duration.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, God ſends his hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſpoſe of them for high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er things: ſome are ſent to leſſer ſchooles, to fit them for exerciſe in greater places: this world's the ſchoole of the Croſſe to the Saints, and when they have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how to <hi>beare a Croſſe,</hi> they ſhall <hi>weare a Crowne:</hi> when they have learned to be <hi>ſuſtained under a loſſe,</hi> they ſhall <hi>inherit all Chriſt, and whatſoever is gaine:</hi> Saints muſt enter heaven; but 'tis, as the Scripture ſpeakes, <hi>through many tribulations. Gold is</hi> not <hi>pure,</hi> if not <hi>tried, water's</hi> not <hi>ſweet</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>current: Veſſells</hi> are not <hi>bright,</hi> if not <hi>ſcowred;</hi> nor are Saints fit to enter Heaven, if not prepar'd: Hence, that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Give thankes to the Father, who ha's made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance, of the Saints in</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:96098:57"/>
                  <hi>Light: made us,</hi> we are not found meet, but the Lord <hi>makes us meet,</hi> while wee are ſurvivers in this world: holineſſe, and heavenly mindedneſſe in Saints, is their fitneſſe for Heaven and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and ſuffering fits for reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>our light afflictions,</hi> if wee be <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17.</note> ſonnes of God, <hi>worke for us,</hi> or worke us unto, as the word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, <hi>a more exceeding weight of glorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Light afflictions</hi> to exceeding maſſie glorie, and momentarie ſufferings fit us for, worke us to, eternall reigning. God <hi>prepar'd</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>for his</hi> children <hi>a Kingdome before the foundation of the world,</hi> and the ſame God prepares them to bee fit Subjects for ſuch a Kingdome, yea, and which is more, to be fit Princes and Kings in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome<hi>: hee ha's waſhed away their ſinnes in his owne bloud, and ha's made them Kings, and Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and his Father:</hi> ſaith the Spirit to the ſeven Churches of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:96098:58"/>
Fifthly, that grace might have a being, as well as Glorie: grace ha's a being onely in the gracious here, and had not God brought them into this ſtrange Land, where ſhould eſpeciall grace have exiſted, ſave in the breſt of its O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall? true it is, there had been <hi>glory to God on high:</hi> as the <hi>Angels ſang,</hi> when they <hi>appear'd to the Shepheards;</hi> but where would have been <hi>peace on earth, and good will towards men,</hi> if God had not brought forth his choſen veſſells, to make peace with them, make knowne his good will towards them? what brought the babe Jeſus into the wombe and world, bred him up in the ſhape of a man, made him doe and ſuffer like a God; but the power and good pleaſure of his Father, for his childrens good, whom hee knew would be ſtrangers in this world? and is not the Kingdome of grace on earth, in the hearts of theſe ſtrangers? where is't elſe?
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:96098:58"/>
how are all the manifeſtations of grace, and favour from God made apparent; but to his choſen? being here, they are here to <hi>be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſanctified, juſtified,</hi> and <hi>ſav'd</hi> from hence. Oh great myſteries &amp; rarely obſerv'd of any<hi>!</hi> Now to applie<hi>:</hi> would you know your ſtate, and relation in which you ſtand, as to the buſineſſe in hand? then note theſe things and marke them well.</p>
               <p>1. What price doe you put on <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> the worlds glorie? how high is that in your eſteeme? what thoughts have you of it? I muſt tell you that a holy one, and hee who's a ſtranger on earth, do's more eſteeme the repairing of the Lords Image in his ſoule, his reſtitution to his ancient, or a better diſcent, his re-eſtating in the poſſeſſion of God, and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of Angels; than all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, pleaſures, and treaſures of this glittering, delighting, and advancing world: hence hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:96098:59"/>
to rid himſelfe from ſuch feculent matters here, and out of the greatneſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Spirit, with the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of his divine diſpoſition, is altogether ambitious of the <hi>preſence of the Lamb,</hi> and immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good things. Strangers on earth can tell you the truth of this Relation: and you, Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of Heaven! tell me, ha's not God wrought your heart to this frame? if he ha's not, he will doe it firſt, or laſt: for the Citizens of Heaven ſet not much by the beſt things on earth, when they are themſelves, and act like their Saviour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a ſtranger on earth is knowne by his Language: <hi>thou art a Galilean, for thy ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 73. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.70.</note> 
                  <hi>thee:</hi> Or as another Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, <hi>thy ſpeech agrees thereunto:</hi> ſo one who's a Citizen of Heaven is knowne by his ſpeech; hee ſpeakes a language different from the worlds natives: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:96098:59"/>
tell you of a <hi>ſound ſpeech which cannot be condemned:</hi> that's the language of Heaven, and all its Natives: whereas the children of this world have a putid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, rotten language; ſuch as the holy Lord cannot owne, but will call to <hi>account for everie idle</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>word</hi> that's ſpoken by them: hence the Apoſtle moves the Church of the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> to <hi>ſpeake,</hi> like Chriſt, words <hi>with grace, ſeaſon'd, as with ſalt;</hi> that have the ſavour of God in them: and in the new Covenant, the Lord bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to give to his children <hi>a pure language, that they might call on the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zep.</hi> 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>name of the Lord with one conſent.</hi> What's all this, but to ſhew, that he would have them differ from other people, be knowne by their ſpeech? a Chriſtian ſhould bee knowne by his diſcourſe, in all ſocieties: what though ſinners can ſpeake the language of Saints; yet Saints ſhould not ſpeake the language of ſinners: will you
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:96098:60"/>
heare how theſe ſpake, who are now in Heaven? 'twas thus; as they <hi>were allowed of God, not as they who pleaſe men, but God which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the heart:</hi> and can the heart be good when the ſpeech is bad? the Scripture ſaith nay, and in this the worlds Proverb may convince it, <hi>viz.</hi> As is the man ſuch is his ſpeech: uncleane ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers! a word to you, your ſpeech bewraies you too: ſhewes you are earthlie men, have earthly minds; <hi>for out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth ſpeakes. What will you doe in the day of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition for ſinne, the great and terrible day of the Lord?</hi> Dare you uſe uncleane ſpeech then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſpotleſſe <hi>Lambe of God, and Judge of quick and dead?</hi> if ſo, uſe it now: if not, ſhun it, that Chriſt may give you a diſcharge from that, and all other your ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a ſtrangers mind and motion's homeward: he may be
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:96098:60"/>
where hee lacks nothing, is well accommodated, ha's many friends and more pleaſures; yet ſtill his heart's at home, his mind's carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither, and all his motion's that way: (for home's homely, as we ſay) 'tis even ſo with men of the high Countrey, whileſt in this low Region: <hi>Paul</hi> tells you, <hi>hee preſſed forward after the marke:</hi> he was in the world, and injoyed enough for a ſtranger too; but yet his mind was with Chriſt, and in Heaven, his owne Countrie; his motion was that way alſo: and was't not his good opinion of his heavenly home, that cauſed thoſe words to fall from him; <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> And why? <hi>for 'tis beſt of all, I have Chriſt while I live;</hi> but when I die, <hi>I ſhall have gaine:</hi> what motive more ſtrong, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke to longings after heavenly manſions? Children of God<hi>!</hi> hie you home, for the night drawes on, and the poſting Sunne
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:96098:61"/>
of worldly Joyes, treaſures, and pleaſures, is almoſt ſet, let <hi>the Lord</hi> then <hi>trie</hi> your <hi>hearts and ſearch your reines</hi> in this reſpect; for if you bee ſtrangers, 'twill thus be knowne: aske your hearts this queſtion, whither, and to what place, or end doe all my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and motions tend? when you draw nigh to God querie thus<hi>:</hi> what doe I approach his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence for? is't to put on my houſe from Heaven? is't, that my love may be leſſened to my earthly Tabernacle? ſay to thy ſoule <hi>in the night ſeaſon:</hi> where have I been? what have I done, this by paſt day, and to what end did my being and doing tend? ſome mens paines, cares, and feares tend to intomb them in the world, burie them in the earth: theſe are not ſtrangers here, are not in a ſtrange land. Earthlie ſoules and ſenſuall! Looke about you, and conſider your eſtate: for heavenlie ones
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:96098:61"/>
are <hi>loſt in God,</hi> drown'd in Chriſt, <hi>Heaven's their home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſtrangers in a ſtrange land content themſelves onely with things needfull, as they paſſe through the land of their pilgrimage: aſpire not after any great matters; If they mind their home ſincerely: is't not as true of ſuch, who are Citizens of Heaven? a little contents them, when they are themſelves. <hi>Paul</hi> had <hi>learned what ever his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, therewith to be contented:</hi> and why? 'twas becauſe he was <hi>a ſtranger,</hi> and his <hi>hope of the things of this world was very little.</hi> So, honeſt hearted <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſir'd but food &amp; rayment, and then promiſed the Lord ſhould bee his God: ſo <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was content to <hi>dwell in Tents,</hi> who might have had ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9. 10.</note> ſtructures, to ſhew hee was <hi>in a ſtrange Countrie, and looked for a Citie which ha's foundations, whoſe maker and builder is God:</hi> and me thinkes, I ſhould heare
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:96098:62"/>
all ſayings of Saints about out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, to hold harmonie with that of <hi>Agur: Lord give</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>me neither povertie nor riches, but ſeed mee with food convenient;</hi> and on the ſame ground, he had<hi>: left</hi> you <hi>be full and denie</hi> him: which, 'tis a thouſand to one, you'l doe, <hi>and then ſay, who's the Lord? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poore, ſteale, and ſo take the name</hi> of your <hi>God in vaine:</hi> adde to theſe, two things more, to cauſe content in ſtrangers.</p>
               <p>Firſt, fulneſſe is onely at your owne home: if you looke for't here, you doe but beat the aire; for <hi>it ha's pleaſed the Father that all fulneſſe ſhould dwell in Chriſt:</hi> now when you are at your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and have Chriſt in your armes, you may ſay you're full<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have bread enough; but ne'r till then: do's not the wiſe man tell you that <hi>all's vanitie under the Sunne: viz:</hi> vacuitie, empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lightneſſe: it ha's left the creature, (as wee ſaid before)
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:96098:62"/>
you muſt bee above the naturall Sunne, before you can eſpie, or take in a ſpirituall fulneſſe: and, is't not better to have it there, where you may hold it? Lay theſe things among your cutting cares, and carefull thoughts, and then you ſhall find thoſe thoughts will be eaten up of theſe; the leſſer things will bee loſt among the greater. When <hi>David</hi> doated much on the world, what was the iſſue? 'twas this, he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a foole for ſo doing; tells the Lord he was <hi>ignorant, and as a beaſt, a bruit before him.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And at laſt, he ſweetly ſings, <hi>whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there's none on earth that I deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee:</hi> then he had enough; &amp; beloved ſtrangers<hi>!</hi> let me tell you, you either have, or ſhall have enough too<hi>:</hi> as the Proverb is: for <hi>when</hi> you <hi>awake</hi> you <hi>ſhall be ſatisfied with the Lords Image:</hi> at the Reſurrection, God will make you amends (I am ſure)
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:96098:63"/>
for all your hard meaſure that you receive in this ſtrange land.</p>
               <p>Secondly, unneceſſarie things: things you need not, are not in ſtraights for, are but as lumber, and luggidge, which will hinder you, and preſſe you downe as you're running your heavenly race. Do's not experience teach, that ſome have more of the worlds wealth, than they can tell how to uſe? do's not that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in heavenly ingagements? I know nothing more obſtructive. Oh! how good is God to his, then, when he rids them of need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe luggidge, ſtrips them of ſeen things, that hee may cloath them with unſeen things, an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, incorruptible, immortall ſubſtance? do's not one ſtaffe ſupport the Traveller when a bundle of ſtaves brings him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Oh then! that all, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for Heaven, would ſeek no more proviſion for the journey, then will help them thither. Oh
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:96098:63"/>
ſoule! will it not grieve thee to conſider, that when thou haſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely thought thou art as high as Heaven, thou ſhalt by an evill world be laid as low as Hell? be then in earneſt a ſtranger to it, and in it? for to be a ſtranger to the other world, will hinder from entering <hi>into</hi> thy <hi>Maſters Joyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, ſtrangers ingage not themſelves, too much, in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Natives of ſtrange lands: ſtrangers muſt not bee medlers, as the Proverb is. Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of Heaven! would you ſhew your ſelves to be ſtrangers here? plunge not your ſelves too deep then in the <hi>negotiation</hi> of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of this world; who make it their buſines, to be mightie, weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, honourable, pleaſed and pleaſur'd here: but doe not you doe ſo; meddle not with that their buſineſſe; haſten home, and why? for their's moſt might, wealth, pleaſure, and treaſure, in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:96098:64"/>
heavenly places. What can you thinke of, which is in this world, and is not in your <hi>Fathers houſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, you ſtrangers! you <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> may be glad 'tis with you as 'tis; that you are no better acquainted here. Oh<hi>!</hi> be not loath then, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare to leave this ſtrange land: would you haſten to your journeyes end? is your heart at home? let theſe things then give life to your indeavours that way.</p>
               <p>Firſt, till you leave it, you're farre from your beſt friends, and chiefeſt favours. When the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall child was from his Fathers houſe, 'tis ſaid hee was in <hi>a farre Countrie:</hi> and is not your caſe the ſame; who dwell in God? What<hi>!</hi> are huskes, hardly got, ſo good? what<hi>!</hi> ſhall they bee more in eſteeme than bread? if you will not come from among the ſwine, your Father will fetch you: 'tis better then, to goe and meet him, while his armes are open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:96098:64"/>
you, his head bowed to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute you, and his heart drawn out to feaſt you, feed you, cloath and adorne you with Jewells. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, your father is of another Countrie, he, that <hi>begot you again,</hi> lives in Heaven, a great way hence: and what are you here for, but to diſpatch your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers buſineſſe?</hi> as Jeſus told his Mother. Are not you the Lords factours? and muſt factours ſtay alwayes abroad? what! ſhall they forget their native Countrie, and not haſten to it? who, that's wiſe, do's not ſtrive lawfully to be at his heavenly home? What! know you not that your Father's your beſt benefactour? Beſides, your ſpirituall brethren and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, with all your holy acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taince, are within thoſe heavenly places: a godly child may have his thoughts running out on his godlie parents deceaſed; a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band his thoughts on his wife, and on the contrarie, the wife on
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:96098:65"/>
her husband<hi>:</hi> but alas! they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee their faces till God hath taken them out of this ſtrange land<hi>:</hi> who then would bee wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this world, and not rather wean'd from it, and married to the Lord? Yet further, your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dowrie is above, alſo: <hi>your reward's with the Lord in the land of the living:</hi> how then can you like to dwell in a land, where there's ſuch dying of perſons and portions? ſome <hi>live by bread on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in a ſence; but children from on hie cannot<hi>:</hi> the mind or ſoule is the man, as wee ſay, and that cannot, may not ſurvive in ſuch a manner, by ſuch meanes.</p>
               <p>This ſtrange land can onely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the bodie, ha's not one ſavourie morſell for the ſoule; do's rather contaminate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile the ſoule, than refreſh it. O divine, Celeſtiall ſoule<hi>!</hi> 'tis the ſafeſt way for thee then, to flie from this ſtrange land in all thy motions, as from the face of a Serpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:96098:65"/>
Secondly, you ſhould not bee loath to leave it, when providence will have it ſo; for till then you'l be foiled, vexed, and ſoiled with filthie ſinnes<hi>:</hi> they'l beare you downe, keepe you under, bring you low, when you would be on high with God in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: whileſt the ſoule is in the bodie, ſinne lodgeth with her, will have roome as well as ſhee. Oh<hi>!</hi> how unrulie a gueſt is ſinne? Beſides, here, in this ſtrange land, you cannot ſing your Hebrew ſongs ſo ſweetlie, with ſuch ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Joy, as in your owne Countrie<hi>:</hi> if this world, which ſometimes inthrals you, ſhould <hi>require of</hi> you <hi>ſongs,</hi> bid you bee merrie. Alas! this is no place for ſuch Joy, as is a Joy of heart: heartie Joy is in Heaven, and me thinkes I ſhould heare ſuch a voice from Chriſtians, as was heard in the Temple before the fall of the <hi>Jewes, Migremus hinc, let us goe hence, let us goe hence.</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:96098:66"/>
Thus, as children learne to ſpeake, and delight in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of their Parents; ſo ſhould you, in imitation of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Finally, <hi>I beſeech you,</hi> if you be ſtrangers, <hi>that you would, as Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims and ſtrangers, abſtaine from fleſhlie luſts, which warre againſt the Spirit:</hi> ſo ſaith the Lord of Reſts: for certainly ſinne cannot enter Heaven. Oh<hi>!</hi> what a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed good would it prove to you? if you would bee and doe now, what you are willing to bee and doe then, when pureſt glorie muſt make the ſcrutinie for, and into impureſt ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:96098:66"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>1 CORINTHIANS 15. 51, 52.</bibl>
                  <q>Behold, I ſhew you a myſterie, wee ſhall not all ſleep, but we ſhall all be changed, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Saints laſt and beſt change.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MUtable man ha's made his times variable,</hi> Adam <hi>chang'd his mind, and God chang'd his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Paradiſe could not hold him, who held not God in his thoughts; let goe an unparaleld good. When man alter'd his doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God alter'd his being. All changes are our owne, the Lord ha's ſaid he change's not. Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by ſinne was the maladie, but mutation by grace and glorie is the remedie: man ha's chang'd for the worſe, yet man is chang'd for the better, that's the myſterie.</hi>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:96098:67"/>
                     <hi>Man ha's made himſelfe mutable, yet the immutable God will tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate him into an immutable eſtate of good: though the changes of life bee many, yet a change by death deprives them of beings. He's beſt that lives at reſt, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver alter more: Now there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines ſuch a reſt for the people of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saints have their appointed</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>time of change. We'l therefore ſhew you what a change is: next the ſeverall ſorts of changes, and then the uſe of them; even after this manner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt to be changed, is to have a different manner of being; 'tis the ceſſation of a perſon or thing, from being what it once was. We'l now ſhew you what the changes of this world be, &amp; then the ſundrie kinds of them<hi>:</hi> thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Either ſuch as reſpect the bodie.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſoule or Spirit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:96098:67"/>
And thirdly, ſuch as concern them both joyntly.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, externall changes. Saints whileſt in the bodie are children of change, nor can their injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of life bee found immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Certainlie the ſorrowes of life, exceed the pleaſures of the living: ſtrange are the turnings of things, as well as times. The tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of riches into povertie, Plentie into ſcarcitie, Health, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſickneſſe, Joy into heavineſſe ſhew, that all ſeen good is ſhort liv'd. The Lord's arrowes ſtick faſt in ſome, and feſter fouly. Children of change<hi>!</hi> tell me (if you can) how ſoone is a friend-like amitie turn'd into a foe-like enmitie, even in theſe our dayes? How doe friends ſtart aſide like a broken bow, from fidelitie, to Treacherie? as <hi>Ephraim</hi> once did? Conſociation, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, is now turn'd into Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and confuſion; ſhall I give you the reaſon? 'tis the want
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:96098:68"/>
of immutable, unchangeable love. Husbands, and wives, Parents, and children, Maſters, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, are rent in ſunder; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome different opinions. Do's not this ſpeake out ſtrange alterations? What do's it more? and what do's all this, but imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the comforts of a former communion? Ther's nothing in this world found long-laſting, God ha's added brevitie, as well as vacuitie, unto all outward things. Secondly, there's a change of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits too, God ha's given ſome, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirits then what they once had.</p>
               <p>The Scripture tells you of a newneſſe of Spirit, there's not an annihilation, but a mutation in this reſpect. This is to have the hearts frame, turn'd into Chriſt's frame, a corrupt mind, converted into the mind of Chriſt; Paſſion, turn'd into Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Pride into Meekneſſe, hardneſſe, into ſoftneſſe, Lofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:96098:68"/>
into lowlineſſe. Hence the underſtanding makes right diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of Chriſt, and ſelfe, the will inclines unto, and cloſeth with, better objects than it was wont to doe. Then affections of love to ſinne, are turn'd into ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſinne<hi>:</hi> and nothing is ſo much belov'd of him, as that Chriſt who ſuffer'd for ſinne. If any evill be diſcover'd, he ſhunnes it, if any good, he embraces that, is right glad of that, oh how good is ſuch a change! 'Tis a comfort to ſee groſſe mettall pure, darke aire cleare, a dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> live, and be lively<hi>:</hi> But the comfort ariſing thence, is not worthie the name of comfort, if compared to that comfort ariſing hence.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſuch a change as do's referre to them both joyntly, and that's a change of life; a life of nature, into a life of grace, a life of grace into a life of glorie: the firſt is ſweet, and good, <hi>viz.</hi> the life of nature, but the ſecond is
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:96098:69"/>
ſweeter and better, <hi>viz.</hi> that of grace: the third, the beſt and ſweeteſt life of all. <hi>Viz:</hi> that of glorie. And 'tis alwayes God's method with thoſe he'l ſave, thus to turne nature into Grace; and Grace into Glorie: and that by one and the ſame Spirit, who workes out nature, workes in grace, and workes up the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto Glorie. Such a change is exceeding good, makes excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glad<hi>:</hi> But alas<hi>!</hi> who can number the ſorrowes of ſuch, as ſhall be tranſlated from under mercies, into everlaſting miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? from a pleaſing earth, into a tormenting Hell? Lord! what a ſad, and bad change is this? and what mortall can abide thy comming? oh that naturall men then would become graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that in <hi>fine</hi> they may become glorious! and let me tell thee who ever thou art, ſuch a change as this, will ſweeten all other thy changes in this world.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:96098:69"/>
In a word, to bee gloriouſly chang'd, is to have a <hi>vile body made like unto the glorious bodie of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But firſt, the livelie bodie, muſt be turn'd into lifeleſſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereof it is compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 'Tis a change of the bodies materialls, and elementarie qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and this laſt, even this is that bliſſefull thing our Apoſtle ſpeakes of: this is that glorious Myſterie which merits obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Behold, I ſhew you a Myſterie, we ſhall not all ſleep, but wee ſhall all be chang'd.</hi> Oh renewed ſoule<hi>!</hi> Remember thou in all thy thoughts, and wayes, the worth, and comfort of this thy laſt, and beſt change: thus thy Autumne is turn'd into a ſpring, thy heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, into the Joy of the morning, even the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reſurrection. Now, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> that <hi>that day come</hi> not on you <hi>as a thiefe in the night,</hi> mind much theſe rules following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Expect it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:96098:70"/>
2. Rejoyce in it.</item>
                  <item>3. Suffer God to diſpoſe you for it, expect it, and that on theſe grounds.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Life's brevitie.</item>
                  <item>2. Death's certaintie.</item>
                  <item>3. Your owne Neceſſitie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Life's brevitie. What is life? 'tis ſaid in the Scripture's that 'tis but <hi>a ſhew,</hi> and alas! what's <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 6.</note> that? 'tis but of a ſhort aſpect, though made verie glorious by the skill of the Artificer; and then 'tis ſhut up though the eye be not ſatisfied with ſeeing. And elſewhere 'tis call'd <hi>a ſhadow,</hi> which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh</hi> 8, 9.</note> if you doe graſpe, what have you gain'd? open your hands, and you'l find 'tis nothing: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>James</hi> 4. 14.</note> Beſides, when the Sunne is ſet, or the <hi>Medium</hi> of its Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, it's briefly forgotten, as a thing whoſe <hi>Idea</hi> was never in mind. 'Tis but <hi>a vapour</hi> which the wind will ſoone diſſipate, ſcatter, and diſperſe. A <hi>Poſt that haſtens</hi> name what you can
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:96098:70"/>
that's of the ſwifteſt wing, yet you'l find lifes ſpeed is greater; by which it haſten's out of the living, the poſting Sunne of worldlie wealth and greatneſſe is ſet in an inſtant, in a moment. Wee every day ſtand with our lives <hi>in our hand,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his dayes on earth. Life ha's many out-lets, but few in-lets. There's many wayes to goe out of the world, but onely one way into the world: and that paſſage is verie dangerous too; ſome have beings in the wombe, and at laſt it's made their tombe, they ne'r ſee the world. Others bring <hi>to the birth,</hi> but <hi>want ſtrength to bring forth. Job</hi> may well call't <hi>a flower;</hi> for though 'tis ſweet; yet 'tis of an earthlie breed: It ha's a glorie too; but the beſt glorie of a flower muſt be preſerv'd by a ſhower, and when all's done it withers, and is loſt at laſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Deaths certaintie: it will not faile you, 'twill find
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:96098:71"/>
you wherever you goe<hi>:</hi> therefore when thy <hi>bones are full of marrow,</hi> and <hi>riches comes in as a floud:</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue thus, yet I muſt die. Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expecting Chriſtians can tell you, that a wife, a child, a friend, nor any of them, can be injoyed for ever: That their eſtates, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and lives, are going, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, will deſert them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe long for, and deſire a change, after which they can change no more.</p>
               <p>'Tis further cleare thus. Firſt, from Gods decree. <hi>It is appointed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>for all men once to die.</hi> Secondly, from the conſtitution of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Mans nature is a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1.</note> of waſting ingredients, he's made up of dying materialls; The Apoſtle calls the bodie <hi>a houſe of earth;</hi> and know you not that earth may be and is corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, do's breed that which will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and infeſt it, with a noiſome ſtench? Beſides, a houſe of earth is weake<hi>:</hi> and what is there,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:96098:71"/>
which hath not power on that which is weakneſſe it ſelfe? Adde to this, that a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> is not made to laſt long, 'tis made on purpoſe for a ſhort time of exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the defilements of our nature, they put us to the ſword, murther us in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; have given being to this laſt change as well as others. Trees and plants breed the wormes which at laſt make them lifeleſſe, and ſo doe we ſerve our ſelves, and ſoules. If <hi>Adam</hi> give <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 12.</note> leave to <hi>ſinne, ſinne</hi> will give way to <hi>death. There's no man living, who ſhall not</hi> have his fit of dying; though the death of Saints bee precious in the ſight of the Lord, yet die they muſt; for his <hi>onely begotten ſonne</hi> did not eſcape it. What then though a man ſtrive, repine, order his diet, intreat, and ſhun occaſions; yet as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>none ſhall deliver his ſoule from</hi> the hand of <hi>the grave:</hi>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:96098:72"/>
Live hee as long as <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> yet muſt hee die at laſt. Gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed ſinners<hi>!</hi> what meane you to ſtand it out with God ſo long, to breake with God for a trifle? what's your life, that ſhould bee ſpent, laid out for him, and that he requires from you? 'Tis not worth the honour to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of force, to draw your ſoules from God. Oh then! make no more waſte of <hi>time, redeeme</hi> it; for if Chriſt ha's redeem'd you, you cannot ſquander away the whole thereof, and give him none. Remember, 'tis a difficult thing to die well.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, mans neceſſitie, and that firſt in reſpect of the bodie. A corruptible bodie, cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the incorruptible Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens? it muſt die and be chang'd: It muſt leave its filth in the grave, before it can be meet to dwell in the heavenlie places above. The bodie is now the ſubſtance and matter of all diſeaſes, putrifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:96098:72"/>
infirmities, and deformities, although you take in the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Creature your eyes have ſeen within the bounds of this obſervation<hi>:</hi> For is't not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the likeneſſe of fleſh, heat of luſt, and ſtaine of ſinne? the ſenſible Prophet ſincerely confeſſed it. Beſides, who knowes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51. 5.</note> not that knowes Chriſt, that 'tis the livelie inſtrument of ſinne? The verie excrements of whoſe noſtrills, ear's, pores, and other paſſages duelie and trulie conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, will ſeeme more loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome then the uncleaneſt ſinke or vault. Oh! what vile bodies have wee<hi>!</hi> and how great need have wee that they ſhould be chang'd, buried in the duſt and refined? Trees and plants bring forth leaves, flowers, fruits, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſmells; But mans bodie brings forth naturallie nothing but vermine, wormes, rottenneſſe, and a filthie ſtench. <hi>Lord! what is man that thou art mindfull of</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:96098:73"/>
                  <hi>him?</hi> and what ha's hee to bee proud of, who's made of ſuch materialls?</p>
               <p>Firſt, in reſpect of the ſoule; that ſhe may be freed from that diſcord which is in the bodie, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the change comes; for whileſt the bodie lives a naturall life, there's no buſineſſe can bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched which concernes the ſoules welfare, without a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in the heart: the fleſh is a home-bred enemie, a boſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, that's daily againſt the Spirit, becauſe they <hi>are contraries.</hi> The fleſh, alas! foreſtalls all Divine motions, actions, and indeavours, of the ſoule, and Spirit; and it begets, and breeds, an indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe towards them all; though all <hi>the wayes of God be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſe,</hi> and all his <hi>paths peace;</hi> yet this bodie of fleſh will make them ſeeme irkeſome, burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and full of trouble. Is't not high time then, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhould be changed? made a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:96098:73"/>
better ſervant to the ſoule? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it's ſinne-ſick diſtempers are infanable, whileſt it is here, for ha's it not brought on man a certaine neceſſitie of ſinning? ſo that we cannot but diſpleaſe the higheſt Lord.</p>
               <p>Doe you doubt of this? why the Scriptures tell you, that thoſe who are in <hi>the fleſh cannot pleaſe God;</hi> that wretched <hi>Law of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>members</hi> wars <hi>againſt the Law of the mind,</hi> and <hi>Spirit of life:</hi> which brings the whole man into an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable bondage. This is mans miſerie in his upriſings, and downe-lyings, a depraved nature <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23.</note> is his aſſociate, and as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>innumerable evills</hi> doe <hi>encompaſſe him about; and have taken hold of him:</hi> that he's <hi>not able to looke up to Heaven.</hi> This bring's <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 12.</note> to mind a worthie ſaying of like concernment. O fleſh, fleſh<hi>!</hi> I can neither live with thee, nor without thee. Now at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breathing in, or the re-uniting of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:96098:74"/>
the ſoule, to its owne proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; the bodie ſhall be found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible: and that, even that; will be found the laſt and beſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, rejoyce, in, and at the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> thoughts of ſuch a change, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, firſt, 'twill rid you of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſocietie with ſin and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh<hi>:</hi> whileſt we are here we converſe and commerce with greateſt ſinners; and with innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſinnes: we, alas! walke among the Tombes, with men that lie under the powers and pledges of the everlaſting death, perſons who die living, and will at laſt live dying, and yet ne'r bee dead. In this life, Gracious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians! you heare the greateſt Majeſties name prophaned; his wayes blaſphem'd, truths de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam'd, and doe ſee his friends are foil'd and ſpo'ld<hi>:</hi> But after death you ſhall never heare ſuch evill tidings any more. Who then, that's wiſe, will love, and long to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:96098:74"/>
live with the dead; more then the living? or in the ſocietie of condemned perſons, in a noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome goale, rather than to have fellowſhip with the glorious Princes of God, in the Heaven of matchleſſe and endleſſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? In this <hi>Babylon</hi> faithfull <hi>Jewes</hi> are forc'd to hang <hi>their Harpes upon the willowes;</hi> are much diſabled from ſinging ſweetlie to the Lambe their <hi>Hebrew ſongs:</hi> certainly then all whoſe manſions are with God; are, or ſhould be, wearie of this world: wean'd from this ſcituation; peinched with the coldneſſe of this cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; for this world alas! is a great cooler to the heat of a gracious heart.</p>
               <p>And were they as ſubject to it, as its children are, were they as much intangled with it: Though now they may have a little heat, yet then they would have none at all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, 'twill free, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:96098:75"/>
you from all carnall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; then there ſhall bee no more Gold, nor greatneſſe, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure you from God: no ſinne, nor ſinnes pleaſure to intice and bewitch you, lie proſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you: no ſelfe, nor Satan, to tempt and intrap you: Good Lord! what a good caſe will thine then bee in? who? or what can expreſſe thoſe joyous rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and tranſcendent verities, of ſuch glorious beings? Oh! how unſearchable are the riches of ſuch grace, and favour? Narrow hearts! open your ſelves, and the gates of your ſoules, and let <hi>the King of glorie come in:</hi> why ſhould he be unto you <hi>as a wayfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man, that ſtaies but for a night and is gone?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, 'twill alter the nature of all your ſpirituall diſtreſſes: there ſhall bee then, no more doubts unreſolved; no more ſins, the 'ile be deſtroi'd; no more graces unrevived: no more feares
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:96098:75"/>
of finall falling; no more que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries about the truth of your high calling, no more want of God, Chriſt, and the good deſired; no more diſlike of, and from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Chriſtians; no ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of carriage among knowne members of Chriſt's bodie my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall. In a word, there ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this change, never bee any more hearts hardneſſe; minds blindneſſe, wills perverſeneſſe, loves coldneſſe, zeales raſhneſſe, liſtleſſe deſires, heartleſſe prayers, tireſome ſpirit, or rebellious fleſh; But, holy hearts! you ſhall be God-like, Chriſt-like in all things.</p>
               <p>3. Suffer God to diſpoſe you for it, ſith 'twill come and you muſt be changed. Men ſquare wood before they build, diſcipline their Troopes, e're they joyne in battell; rigg, trimme, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their ſhips, ere they launch, put forth to Sea: ſo God is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome, every day of life; for
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:96098:76"/>
the day of death. Would you know the way, by which the Lord effects this bleſſed fitneſſe; for ſo glorious a change? ſo great a worke, as is the worke of dying? obſerve then rightly, theſe ſerious things in the <hi>ſequell:</hi> God fits his children for ſuch a deceaſe, thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by making the bodie of ſinne irkeſome to them. There are ſome, who with <hi>David,</hi> have their <hi>ſinnes ever before</hi> them; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forget them<hi>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> are greevouſly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 3.</note> burden'd with them, and their crie is ſuch as this. <hi>Oh! who ſhall deliver me from the bodie of this death?</hi> This, even this ha's made ſome wearie of the world, yea, and wearie of themſelues too: all the while longing to be there, where they might never ſee, or ſeele it more. Such had rather die a thouſand deaths, then live diſhonouring him; in whoſe <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſtands</hi> their <hi>life:</hi> and whoſe <hi>loving-kindneſſe is better than life;</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes. Hence alſo
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:96098:76"/>
everie ſanctified ſorrow, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, of this earthlie life; puts him upon minding his laſt and long'd for home: every decay of ſtrength, dimnes of ſight, dulnes of hearing, and diſabilitie of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and doing, with all ſicknes, weaknes, aches, and pains<hi>:</hi> theſe I ſay doe forewarne him of his approaching deceaſe. And thus with <hi>Job</hi> he <hi>waites all the dayes of his life, untill his appointed change comes.</hi> Holy hearts! you're well acquainted with the ſtate of this diſtreſſe; and therefore, you muſt ſigne, and ſeale to the truth of this experiment: yet <hi>let not your hearts be troubled,</hi> for ſinnes burthen ſhall bee remov'd, and you your ſelues certainely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd, and ſav'd.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by making death to them deſirable: this is a death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweetning way<hi>:</hi> and he acts in the buſineſſe after this manner. Firſt ſuggeſting into their thoughts, that when death ſurprizeth them
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:96098:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it ſhall be ſtingleſſe; and what's <hi>the ſting of death?</hi> why the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tell you <hi>'tis ſinne:</hi> ſinne is deaths Arrow, which when 'tis ſhot into the bowells of the ſoule, at the appointed time of change, oh! how do's it wound with horrour, cut with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and pierce with dread, of a great, juſt, and glorious Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie? And then, how do's the poore ſoule feſter with deſpaire, whil'ſt ſhe cannot beleeve, or hope to bee well, and doe well, after death: who ha's been, and done, ſo ill, in time of life. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, if in life, there's no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge from ſinne; in death, the ſoule will greatlie feare, if not throughly feel its diſcharge from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But to you that are in Jeſus Chriſt, be this word ſpoken. <hi>The Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made you free; from the law of ſinne and death: The ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of</hi>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:96098:77"/>
                  <hi>ſinne is the Law. viz.</hi> ſinnes Law; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 15.</note> for this place ſeemes to explaine the other.</p>
               <p>Thus you are freed from both the power of ſinne and death al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. I may adde, and the victorie of the grave, which cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, or infringe your bodies long; ſo long, as to retaine you for ever. Give thankes then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, who ha's given you <hi>the victorie, through</hi> your Lord and <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſing with <hi>Paul, ô death where is thy ſting? ô grave where is thy victorie?</hi> For when a poore ſoule conſiders within her ſelfe thus: well, I am now neere my time of change; I muſt leave the world<hi>:</hi> But Chriſt ha's promis'd that he'l bee with me to the end of my courſe; and ha's alſo aſſur'd me, that my ſinnes are forgiven, and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; I have a diſcharge from them, through the mercie of God. Is ſhe not then readie to crie out? <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:96098:78"/>
                  <hi>quicklie.</hi> Death doe thy dutie freely: and thus the poore, droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, doubting Chriſtian, lives dying; yet ne'r taſtes of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death. God acquits the ſoule in Juſtification from ſinnes guilt; and cleanſeth the ſoule through Sanctification from ſinnes filth; hee that's waſhed from his old polutions, hath the heavenly ornaments of Chriſt's Spirit<hi>:</hi> He's fit to ſolemnize a marriage with the Lambe. God alſo perſwades the ſoule, that he ha's found a righteouſneſſe; as well as a ranſome for her. Now beleevers may conclude then, as the Scripture ſpeakes: that <hi>Righteouſneſſe delivers from death:</hi> And that <hi>the righteous hath hope in his end.</hi> He fits his to be changed by <hi>mortification</hi> alſo, for when <hi>God,</hi> by his Spirit, has crucified ſinne; that would have ſlaine the ſoule Death cannot hurt much, in ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the carcaſe. Hence is that of Chriſt. <hi>Feare not them who kill</hi>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:96098:78"/>
                  <hi>the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the Lord makes the change deſirable to ſome by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25.</note> their eyes, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their hearts, unto a fight and ſenſe of all the al-ſufficiencies of Chriſt; to ſuſtaine the ſoule un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtraights of ſuch a death: what though ſinne upbraids thee, Satan affrights thee, and thine owne heart trembles within thee, &amp; that thou art at a ſtand, knoweſt not what to doe, nor how to die? Yet beleeve, for Chriſt will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thee through. Chriſt did not give himſelf for thee in vain, that he ſhould <hi>give thee up in thy laſt, &amp;</hi> greateſt triall; give thee into the hands of Satan. Why then, leane on him, who's a ſtay of ſtrength and you'l not miſcarrie: He that hath, and is had, of a good Chriſt ſhall bee ſure of a good death with ſtrength and peace.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by giving his a through taſte of that heavenly joy, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:96098:79"/>
holineſſe, and reall happineſſe; that themſelves ſhall poſſeſſe in the fruition of Chriſt, when once they are changed. This the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls firſt fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of glory. And is't not this, that makes the <hi>Saints</hi> themſelves, <hi>groane within</hi> themſelves; <hi>wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Redemption of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 23.</note> The Lord ha's ſaid it, Oh<hi>!</hi> how do's the taſte of Heavens joy, and of the powers of the world to come; ſtrengthen a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Chriſtian, leaning on Chriſt, to lie under the ſtroake of death? yea, even to long that ſo great a worke were over? and thus God ſweetens death to the good; gives it a good ſavour, when they come to taſte it, it being the ſame cup, which Chriſt himſelfe did firſt drinke of.</p>
               <p>Now you have heard how it fares with the good, at their laſt change; and how good ſuch a change is to them: But alas! for the bad, the Chriſt-leſſe man,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:96098:79"/>
'tis bitter unto him. Theſe things imbitter death to the grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
               <p>1. The biting and tumifying ſting of death, that indiſpoſeth to dying well<hi>:</hi> 'Tis biting: oh! how will the wofull thoughts of a miſpent life, of by paſt ſinnes, of ſlighting Jeſus, and his holy waies, like fiery darts, and ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scorpions, peirce through the ſoule and Spirit? Then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſinners, as <hi>James</hi> ſpeakes of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>James</hi> 5. 3.</note> the <hi>ruſt</hi> of ill gotten, and ill kept <hi>gold;</hi> the guilt of your ſins <hi>ſhall eat your fleſh as it were fire:</hi> Then even then all ſcruing deceivers, ſhall be forced to ſay of their own unlawfully acquir'd goods, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Idolls, get you hence: But alas! theſe are thy workes, and they will follow thee, flow faſter into thy mind, then thou canſt get them out, and make thy ſoule wearie even to the death.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Death's ſting tumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies alſo, <hi>Judas</hi> ſinn'd, betraid his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:96098:80"/>
Maſter, improved the reward: But what was his end? hee fell head-long, burſt aſunder in the midſt, and all his bowells guſhed out: Death had ſtung him, and the ſting made him ſwell ſo, that, his tumour being great, the world could not hold him; and for haſt that hee might the ſooner bee at his owne place, he betrayed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the hands of Satan, was his owne executioner. There's a time when ſtouteſt ſinners ſhall burſt aſunder, under the hand of auſteereſt Juſtice. If the Lord's love makes not breaches on mans Spirit, drawes him not up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven; his wrath will breake it, beat it even to powder, and caſt it downe into the loweſt Hell. O ſinners! Learne then while a Saviour teaches, what an evill ſinne is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſudainneſſe of an <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 27.</note> approaching Judgement. <hi>After death comes Judgement,</hi> and what's the Judgement? Chriſt-leſſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:96098:80"/>
man or woman! I have ſad newes for thee: thou thy ſelfe and all thou art, muſt bee preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Holy, moſt Juſt, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: And with thee ſhalt thou bring all thy <hi>vaine thoughts,</hi> will thou, nill thou, <hi>idle words,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and ſinfull workes, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent time and Talents; In a word all the ſecrets of thy heart ſhall then bee torne in pieces, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd, and unfolded: yea, thoſe ſecrets, which no eye hath ſeen, but his, which is ten thouſand times brighter then the Sunne; yea, even thoſe ſecret ſinnes which have been cover'd here by reſtraint from God, or men, ſhall be uncover'd there: ſo that thou wilt bee fill'd with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſee that which thine eies never did, nor ever would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. There the hearts cloſeſt corners, &amp; darkeſt depths, ſhall then bee laid open, made viſible, before the face of God, Chriſt, Angels, and men. A meere diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:96098:81"/>
                  <hi>of Righteouſneſſe, and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come,</hi> God being in it, and <hi>Foelix</hi> hearning of it, what effects did it worke in him thinke you? why the Text tells you it made him to <hi>tremble,</hi> and to bid <hi>Paul</hi> be gone, hee could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare on't. So <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 5, 6.</note> ſaw but the writing of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the wall, which did but import a temporall ſcourge: And his countenance was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, his thoughts troubl'd him, ſo that the joynts of his Ioines were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt another. And what's any carnall man more, then ſenſuall <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> or carnall <hi>Foelix,</hi> that he ſhould thinke himſelfe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from Judgement? You then that put this evill day farre from you, beare in mind this thing: A ſonne of Love could not indure that; hee prayed, <hi>Enter not into Judgement with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ô Lord:</hi> How then can a child of wrath abide it, who is by
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:96098:81"/>
nature nothing elſe? It's called in Scripture the day of the Lord, his great day, his terrible day. 'Tis the day of Chriſts's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2. 11.</note> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</hi> And who ſhall ſtand when <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 2.</note> he appeareth? for he is like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers fire, and fullers ſope. Thus you have ſeen things that imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the change to ſome, even all that know not Chriſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not his Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the certaine ſtanding before an impartiall <hi>Judge of quick and dead,</hi> who cannot, will not connive at ſinne, and ſinners; <hi>When all fleſh ſhall appeare before the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt: that every one may receive the things</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>done in his bodie, according to that he hath done, whether it bee good, or evill.</hi> knowing <hi>therefore the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Lord, We perſwade men</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Oh! how terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, intollerable are the thoughts of this! ſurely words cannot ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: then he, who ſaid, <hi>Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:96098:82"/>
                  <hi>from me, Ile have none of thy wayes,</hi> ſhall find that God ha's ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to his prayers. Adde to this, that though he ſtand to be judged, yet hee ſhall fall in the Judgement. For <hi>the ungodly ſhall not ſtand in the Judgement,</hi> as the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> notes. You then! whoſe deſtruction is of your ſelves, if your precious ſoules miſcarrie: Conſider ſenſibly in whom your helpe lies, make out towards a Jeſus betime; for there's no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhewed on the other ſide the grave; one drop of water which is but a verie ſmall thing: if mis'd and deſir'd, cannot be obtain'd: Then, if ever you'le owne free grace and fellowſhip with Chriſt. Doe it now, even <hi>while 'tis called</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to day; heare his voice and harden not your hearts:</hi> for this day let ſlip, you may ne'r have another. Reſiſting ſinners! I wiſh you well, my bowells are troubled for you; oh pitie your ſelves! and let not ſinlive to kill your ſoules:
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:96098:82"/>
as it hath ſerv'd others who are gone to their owne place. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and forget not <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> fall and follie: leaſt ſweet Chriſt hide the day of peace from your eyes, as once hee ſerv'd her.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the ſtinging thoughts of being Chriſt-les, and friendles, at that Tribunall bar of heavenly Majeſtie<hi>:</hi> The thoughts of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Advocate with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſpeake one good word for the ſoule to the Irefull Judge; none to ſtand betwixt God and the ſoule, none to keep off the ſtroakes and blowes. When Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall ſuggeſt, and cauſe a man to crie out in bitterneſſe of his ſpirit; Ah wretch that I am, I have lived ſo ill, I cannot die well, nor willingly<hi>:</hi> yet die I muſt, but cannot tell what will become of my poore ſoule and ſelfe! I am now giving up the Ghoſt, but alas! I know not who ſhall have it; I have been Satans
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:96098:83"/>
ſervant, and ſinnes ſervant, all my daies, have ſlighted glorious meanes of acquaintance with God, have been wearie of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, wearie of ſpirituall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and ſpirituall ſocietie: Thus have I made the Judge my foe, and the Advocate my adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie; And woe is mee I know neither of them both. And then though ſuch crie out; <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and hills fall upon us, and hide us from the preſence of him, that ſits on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb:</hi> Mountaines will not doe it for them. Then men ſhall ſhreeke and crie out with trembling, <hi>Lord, Lord. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna thou ſonne of David have mercie on us:</hi> yet ſhall have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Anſwer but this, <hi>I tell you, I know not whence you are, depart from me;</hi> you ſhall goe thither, <hi>where there ſhall bee weeping, wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> When <hi>you ſhall ſee Abraham, Iſaac, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacob, and all the Prophets in the</hi>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:96098:83"/>
                  <hi>Kingdome, and you your ſelves thruſt out.</hi> Or that of Chriſt; <hi>I profeſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>unto you, I never knew you,</hi> then, even then, thoſe who have been <hi>aſham'd of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and of</hi> his <hi>words; in a ſinfull, and adulterous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> ſhall find Chriſt <hi>will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of them, as he comes to Judge in the glorie of his Father, with the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. <hi>laſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>holy Angels.</hi> Ah Lord! can no healing be found for theſe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſoules? <hi>Is there no balme in Gilead</hi> for them? open their hearts, inlighten their minds, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their wants, and ſupplie them all; lay hold on their ſinnes, and ſubdue them fullie<hi>:</hi> and, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, ſenſuall ſoules! I ſay to you, as they to <hi>Jonah, Ariſe you ſleepers, call on your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, the reſignation of the ſoule into the hands of Satan, a devilliſh tormenting Tyrant, a cruell enemie to all mankind: one that, <hi>odio inteſtino proſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> followes and purſues man <hi>with a deadly hatred.</hi> Satan ha's an
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:96098:84"/>
Intereſt in ſome now, but then he'l have the principle<hi>:</hi> ſome <hi>are of him</hi> as Chriſt ſpeakes, and thoſe muſt unto him at the cloſe of time. Then Satan puts in a bill of inditement, as large as that booke of <hi>Zacharie;</hi> wherein is alledged all evill deeds that e're were committed: yea <hi>Conſcience,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zcah.</hi> 5.</note> neither good nor quiet, will <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and memorie give bitter evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the whileſt the Devills are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2. 10.</note> readie to fetch away the ſoule. In a word, the whole man, and everie part thereof will bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, thoſe verie eyes which were quick and active to behold <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 20.</note> vanitie, ſhall looſe their light and ſee nothing but bloud-guiltineſſe of ſinne: and the other ſenſes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their order ſhall faile, and fall, the mind, reaſon, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, as heavenly powers of the ſoule, ſhall be ſhaken with fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtormes of deſpaire, and flaſhings of Hell fire. Then the earthlie houſe ſhall ſhake and
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:96098:84"/>
tremble, yea, the humours like an overflowing Sea, ſhall roare and rattle; <hi>Then the Sunne ſhall bee turn'd into darkeneſſe, and the Moone into bloud, and the ſtarres ſhall fall from Heaven.</hi> The aire ſhall be full of ſtormes, and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Meteors, <hi>the earth it ſelfe alſo ſhall tremble, the Sea roare, and mens hearts ſhall faile for feare, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the end of ſuch ſorrowfull beginnings,</hi> which ſhall receive no periods. Then he, or ſhe that ha's ſpent ſo many dayes or nights in vaine, and idle paſtimes, would give a world, could it bee done, for one houres delay: that they might repent, be reconciled to God, and live. Repent now, deſperate ſinner<hi>!</hi> Compare things together, ſay to thy ſelfe, in earneſt thus. There is a ſinne that I am addicted to, as Pride, Paſſion, Covetouſneſſe, Luxurie, Prophaneneſſe, of this and the other ſort; which if I live in, and goe on, I die for ever; I looſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:96098:85"/>
God, Chriſt, Heaven, and my owne ſoule too, and then <hi>what gaine</hi> I? Nothing but <hi>the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin,</hi> which are levitie, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and then the preſſures of Hell which are perplexitie. The Proverb is, if a man doe venture, and run a hazzard, let him doe it for ſomething: ſo let us doe as well as ſay. What! ſhall I gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie Satan for tempting, the fleſh for ſuggeſting, the world for alluring to ſinne, with the loſſe of my precious ſoule? when I am gone, all's gone with me. And Chriſtians! be you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in this particular, doe not you like theſe; what though Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan roares Lyon-like, The fleſh drawes one way, the world ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? yet <hi>ſtand</hi> you <hi>faſt, quit your ſelves like men, bee ſtrong in the Lord your ſtrength: perſevere, hold out to the end, let no man take your Crowne for if you are redeem'd from thrall: by precious bloud:</hi> then come not into ſuch bondage
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:96098:85"/>
againe, worke not in ſuch <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Gallies any more, that your laſt change be not bitter, and if you are right for Chriſt, be aſſured you cannot.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, the ſtinging thoughts of an excluſion, and ejection from Gods bleſſed preſence, and all familiarity with him and his in thoſe heavenly places; this loſſe, even this (as the Learned have proved) is a greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then ought elſe can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to damned ſoules <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Poena da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni, ſeu divinae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, omnium omninò ſuppliciorum ſummum eſt, quo Deus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem punire poteſt: Nam uti videre Deum, ipſiſſima beatitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do eſt<hi>:</hi> Ita, Deum videre non poſſe, maxima damnatorum poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na eſt, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Inter ſupplicia omnia hoc futurum eſt ſummum, maximum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> à conditoris aſpectu vel brevi morula detineri.</p>
                     <p>Intollerabilis eſt Gehenna &amp; illa poena: tamen licet quis innumeras ponat gehennas, tale nil dicet, quale illa faelici exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere gloria, à Chriſto odio haberi: audire, Neſcio vos <hi>Chryſoft.</hi> ad Po. <hi>Antioch.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Omnia verò gehennae ſupplicia ſuperabit, Deum non videre, &amp; bonis carere, quae in poteſtate habuiſti obtinere. <hi>Bern.</hi> de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter domo. cap. 38.</p>
                     <p>Intollerabilis quidèm res eſt etiam gehenna: quis neſcit, &amp; ſupplicium illud horribile? tamen ſi mille aliquis ponat gehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, nihil tale dicturus eſt, quale eſt à beatae illius gloriae ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore repelli, exoſumque Chriſto, &amp; audire ab illo: non novi. vos. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in <hi>Mat. Hom.</hi> 24.</p>
                  </note>. And 'tis
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:96098:86"/>
fitly called a paine of loſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> an unhappie and everlaſting ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, from the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and the beatificall viſion of the moſt glorious ſoveraigne, and chiefeſt good. 'Tis not to have the leaſt influence of heat and life, from the leaſt Ray of that Sun-like, reſplendent bodie of Chriſt: not to have one glance of its glorie, not to have one taſte of thoſe overflowing rivers of pleaſures, not to have one glimpſe of that inacceſſable light, and <hi>Jehovah's</hi> glorie. What ſhall I ſay the loſſe is? And how ſhall I eſteem it? Surely none, but one, who ha's been in Heaven, heard and ſeen what's there; can tell you what it is to bee ſhut out thence. <hi>Paul</hi> could and did doe ſomething this way, having had in a rapture a little glimpſe of that infinite glory; And having drunke a ſmall drop, of thoſe ever ſpringing fountaines of matchleſſe Joy and Peace: Hence
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:96098:86"/>
was he brought to call <hi>the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things of this life, and the knowledge of them but droſſe and dung,</hi> yea, even <hi>dogs meat,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thoſe things above: Oh how ſweet<hi>!</hi> how comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<hi>!</hi> how refreſhing are the ſurpaſſing rarities of Heaven! Honeſt ſoules! doe not your hearts burn within you, when you thinke on them, diſcourſe on them, and read of them, even burne with love to them? Sure I am whate're you thinke of theſe things, and whatſoever the worke is that they make upon your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; that the loſſe of them will be bitter<hi>:</hi> And I ſeriouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge through Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I count nothing gaine in reſpect of them, when I am my ſelfe, and compare the beſt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things with them. Oh paine of loſſe<hi>!</hi> thou peirceſt the verie heart, ſoule, and inward parts, doſt wound deeply: The paine of ſence is but as a ſcar in the fleſh,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:96098:87"/>
to this; for, this cuts the verie heart in peeces, breakes it to ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: Doe you not ſee this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by common experience? oh how do's it fret, vex and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet men to looſe good bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines on earth? when a man do's but let ſlip an opportunitie of taking a good peniworth of commodities, when it ha's been offer'd: How do's hee upbraid himſelfe with his negligence fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and folly? There are ſome cannot get ſuch a fault out of their minds along time, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the gaine that would have come that way, was ſuch, as that it would have made them rich men, as long as they liv'd after. Aye! but what's that bargain, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or prize to this? that may be loſt in a moment, &amp; at the beſt it laſts not long; for life it ſelfe is but ſhort with all the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations of it<hi>:</hi> but I muſt needs tell all intelligent hearts, ther's enough in God to make you rich
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:96098:87"/>
for ever; and if he makes a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with you, gives himſelf for your ſelves, he'l warrant his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to laſt for ever, and to ſerve for everie turne<hi>:</hi> Heaven is meat, drinke, and cloathing, health, libertie, and harbouring, unto all that are ſeated there. You ſee then by this, what it is that imbitters death, and the change to ſome: this laſt ha's moſt gall and wormewood in't, namely, the pain of loſſe, which Chriſts ſenſible ſervants ne're ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine. Finally, unto you, <hi>who are the redeemed of the Lords Chriſt,</hi> be theſe things ſpoken. Feare not but deſire to ſee this day, your laſt, and beſt, even the laſt and beſt of all your changes. Conſider.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the day of your change is the Lords pay-day, everie <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in the Lords vineyard,</hi> ſhall then <hi>receive his peny;</hi> everie prayer ſhall then have its anſwer; Everie hungring, and thirſting
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:96098:88"/>
ſoule ſhall then bee filled, ſhall ne'r hunger nor thirſt more<hi>:</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſigh, groane, and the teares that have fallen from the eyes of Saints in ſecret, or elſe where, ſhall have their fruit, even <hi>the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et fruits of righteouſneſſe;</hi> which were ſowne in peace many yeares before: And then <hi>all teares ſhall be wiped off from all faces of Saints,</hi> yea, even everie grace ſhall then be glorious. <hi>Moſes</hi> did and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd much when he did but eye the reward, what then ſhall wee be, ſuffer, and doe, when wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it? Then 'twill goe well with the righteous, no mans latter end will be like theirs.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſoule will bee in its prime then, for whileſt it is in a corruptible bodie, it is ſo ruled by ſenſes, and is ſo fiercely car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by ſenſuall appetites, that it's compelled to give way to the bodie; and cannot follow the light either of nature, or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Hence <hi>the truth</hi> is withheld
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:96098:88"/>
                  <hi>in unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and the ſoule cannot act like her ſelfe; like a Spirit, whoſe nature is to ſore aloft, towards the place whence ſhe came. Now till then, the ſoul is made a ſervant, and cannot looke out at the eyes, but 'twill bee infected, nor heare by the eares, but 'twill bee diſtracted, nor ſmell at the noſtrills, and not be tainted, taſte by the tongue and not be allured, or touch by the hand, and not bee defiled: And everie ſenſe on everie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; temptation is ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the ſoule, untill the bodie is changed and made glorious. Who then that's wiſe will not long for his approaching deceaſe, that he may enter the Celeſtiall Paradiſe? to exchange his braſſe for gold, his vanitie for felicitie, vileneſſe for honour, bondage for freedome, a leaſe of life tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, for an inheritance of life immortall<hi>:</hi> Sith that to live here is to die? for how much wee live,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:96098:89"/>
ſo much wee die; everie ſtep of life is a ſtep towards death: and he that ha's liv'd the halfe of his dayes, is dead the halfe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Death gets firſt our Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, then our youth, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and certainly as long as we have lived, ſo long we have died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But 'tis very grievous, and irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>to mee, to thinke of the taking aſunder of ſoule and bodie: Might they goe together as</hi> Enoch's <hi>did, the change would bee more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are put aſunder but for a time, after which the'l bee united <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> for ever: Beſides the union of the ſoule with Chriſt remaines in full force ſtill, as the <hi>Hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> did, when his bodie lay in the grave. The Lords preſence is with the bodie in the duſt, as much as the ſoule is in Heaven with God, and in his preſence. God told <hi>Jacob</hi> hee would goe downe with him into <hi>Egipt,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>on.</hi> 46. 4.</note> alſo ſurely bring him up againe;
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:96098:89"/>
But <hi>Jacob</hi> was dead ere hee was brought up againe. Therefore he carried up his carcaſe out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> not his ſoule, and ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled his bleſſed Promiſe. Saints! why care you ſo much for the carcaſe? why feare you to let it lie in the duſt, and to bee turned into its owne materialls? ther's not a bone, nerve, or ſinew of the whole ſhall be loſt; he <hi>keeps all the bones of the Righteous,</hi> ſaith the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34. 20.</note> Prophet. And ha's not Chriſt told you that the haires of your heads are numbred? He has told them one by one, and certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Reſurrection, though you may have more in order to perfection: yet you ſhall not have leſſe. Is not this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Do's it not warme you at the heart, and refreſh you to ſee how you are car'd for? then, as you are not like children of wrath in your living, ſo loath to be like them in your lothneſſe of dying. Adde to this, that the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:96098:90"/>
grave is but the Lords Treaſurie, wherein hee layes all the bodies of his Saints<hi>:</hi> or may fitly bee called a ſecond wombe. Now conſider well. God might have made the firſt wombe thy tombe, and then how couldeſt thou have beheld his greateſt glorie; Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grudg not at Gods procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in ſuch a kind as this<hi>:</hi> For God meaneth your good in ſuch an alteration. The bodie falls but like an eare of corne into the ground, that it may ſprout and ſpring up more gloriouſly: who then minding Heaven, lets his mind run ſo much on his earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle? is ſo loth to lay it downe? Surely <hi>Abraham's</hi> change was ſtill before him, and he bought him <hi>burying places.</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> waited for it all the daies of his life. In a word, the ſoule ſhall have no need of the bodie, untill the Reſurrection; ſhe's happie of her ſelfe till then: Nor can a glorified ſoule returne into
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:96098:90"/>
a ſinfull bodie againe: Hence 'tis evident, as ſome conceive, that <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſoule was not in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, was not a glorified ſoule, for if ſo 'twould not have return'd into a ſinfull bodie: But the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt ſoule and bodie was loſed at that time, and the ſoule was ſtill in the bodie<hi>: tanquam in ſede, non tanquam in organo.</hi> 'Twas in the bodie, but did not animate the bodie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that you bee not loth to ſtoope to Chriſt in this great worke of dying, and that you may have comfort in it. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider further.</p>
               <p>That it is no more but a meere mutation, 'tis not an annihilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being turn'd into nothing; but a being turn'd into ſomething better then you were<hi>:</hi> and who, that has underſtanding will not let fall a handfull of dirt to take up a handfull of Gold? 'tis but like <hi>Joſephs</hi> act of changing his garments, when hee went in to
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:96098:91"/>
                  <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> You ſhall but for a few houres, it may be, but for a few minutes, be putting off and on that which the Scripture calls cloathing. Put off, and lay aſide the ragges of mortalitie, and ſinne, and then put on the robes of immortalitie, eternitie, and glorie. A Chriſtian at the moſt do's but taſte <hi>aliquid mortis,</hi> his death is but as a ſleep.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this change will put a period to all other thy changes, at death they all ſhall looſe their beings; Here you find changes of Joy, and ſorrow, comforts, and croſſes, ſickneſſe, and health, abundance, and wealth: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this you ſhall ne'r bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled any more, with a ſick body, ſad eſtate, and common loſſes; And for inward changes they ſhall ceaſe alſo, whereas here you're ſometimes free, anon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, ſometimes you have a ſweet taſte of Heaven, at other times diſtracted with feares of
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:96098:91"/>
Hell, ſometimes ſtroaked with Chriſt, and the comforts of the Spirit, anon ſtricken with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, one while magnifying God for grace, another while crying out of ſinnes violent workings in your minds and members; But at this day of change you'l be releaſed for ever, from ſinne and Satan, and you ſhall bee as free, as heart can wiſh, or deſire. In a word, 'tis your yeare of <hi>Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee:</hi> in the yeare of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> every one that-had loſt or ſold his lands, upon the ſounding of the Trumpet return'd, and received them againe; ſo you Saints of the moſt high God ſhall have what you have loſt, even the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that Image which you loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> of all knowledge, wiſedome, Righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe, which then he had, and loſt, and you ſhall enjoy a better eſtate than ever hee loſt, or ſold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:96098:92"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>IOHN 17. 22, 23, 24.</bibl>
                  <q>And the glory which thou gaveſt mee, I have given them, that they may be one even as we are one, &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>Father I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given mee be with mee where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the unfolding of Glory, or the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of Saints when chang'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHriſts gifts are largely exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, he gives all hee ha's to his, what would they more? Chriſt's ſayings are all truth: neither Grace nor Glory, nor any good thing doth he with-hold from his.</hi> The Glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them. <hi>The end of Chriſt's amity is unity: all Chriſt's drift is to encreaſe union betwixt himſelfe and his: if diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content ſurprize his, they ſhall have all he is and hath, ere he'le</hi>
                     <pb n="181" facs="tcp:96098:92"/>
                     <hi>be at odds with them: Oh what a Jeſus is this! Chriſts friends fare as himſelfe doe's; If he have Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they can't want it,</hi> that they may be one. <hi>The union of Chriſt with Chriſtians, is like that of Chriſt with God, ſome things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted:</hi> even as we are one, &amp;c. <hi>All Chriſts acts have his whole will in them:</hi> Father I will, &amp;c. <hi>Chriſt loves that his ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwellers in Glory, dwell with him: ſuch Inmates offend not him:</hi> I will that they may be with me where I am. <hi>Chriſt loves to haue his Glory look'd on, give him what hee loves: for will not looking breed liking? and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king longing after ſuch a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing?</hi> that they may behold my glory, &amp;c. <hi>Wee'l ſhew what the Glory is that's given, and that as ſuccinctly as may be.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:96098:93"/>
GLory in the generall, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but apparant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and even ſo the word is uſed in Scripture, for even that which was made glorious, had no Glory in this reſpect <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by reaſon of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which excelleth. <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 10. Nonunquam <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pud philoſophoseſt ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeu <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Item fama rumor, <hi>&amp;</hi> in bonam &amp; in malam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſaepius ad bonae famae exiſtimatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſtringitur; unde vertitut gloria, honor. <hi>Eraſ.</hi> opinio &amp; per ſyncchdochen generis gloria, quia gloria eſt opiniopraeclara de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licujus ſapientia &amp; virtute. <hi>Piſc.</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 2. Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 29. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 2. ſplendor, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 31. <hi>Acts</hi> 22. 11. brightneſſe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 3. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 7. And in this place heavenly felicity or eternall glory. Hinc <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> quod ſignificat, ornare gloria, glorificare, uſurpatur vel de collatione boni praeclari &amp; ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vel de manifeſtatione, &amp; predicatione gloriae. Tarnovius.</note> 'Tis excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, for 'tis the Lords Glory-Chriſt enjoynes his followers to to ſay to his Father, <hi>Thine is the Glory:</hi> and in Scripture phraſe whenſoever God is added to things, it denotes them emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; as <hi>the citie of God, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of God, the increaſes of God,</hi> It is apparant too. <hi>My ſoule thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, and my fleſh longeth for thee, to ſee thy glory, ſo as I have ſeene it in the Sanctuary.</hi> Hence it is that
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:96098:93"/>
where a Believer is, where Chriſt is; hee ſhall clearely ſee, and fully know the excellencies of God, and Chriſt: yea, what his owne excellency is, by vertue of his union and communion with them both; for then that Glory will be apparant above, which is not ſo apparant here below.</p>
               <p>Three things there are that make everlaſting Glory.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Lords revealing of himſelfe to the ſoule clearly and immediatly.</item>
                  <item>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. His communicating of himſelfe unto her fully, and at once.</item>
                  <item>3. The convolution or turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole ſoule on God, according unto what hee reveales of himſelfe in ſuch a manner.</item>
               </list>
               <p>1. A clear revelation of God, <note place="margin">Tunc et enim juſti cuncta ſcient quae Deus fecit ſcienda tam ea quae praeterita, quam ea quae poſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſunt futura. <hi>Anſelm de</hi> ſimilitud. <hi>Cap.</hi> 54. Neque ſola vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio Dei ſanctis hominibus in coelo promittitur ſed etiam omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um rerum, quas fecit Deus, &amp;c. <hi>Greg.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e aetern. felicit, l. 3. c. 2.</note> and in him many other ſecrets.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:96098:94"/>
                  <q>Then ſhal be made evident thoſe ſacred ſecrets, and glorious my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the holy Trinity; of the unity of Chriſt's Humanity with the Divine nature, and of Chriſtians with Chriſt: then all the cauſes of God's eternall Councell, in Election and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; as alſo the manner of the Creation of the World, with the fall of the Angels, and all the myſteries of the work of Redemption, together with the ſpirituall ſubſtances, offices, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and excellencies of thoſe Angels that ſtand. The nature, immortality, operations, and originall of our owne ſoules, and that after a way unuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Viſions of God, and glory on Earth, are darke; we ſee darkely ſaith the Scripture<hi>:</hi> would we ſee clearly, we muſt waite then til we are in Heaven. <note n="*" place="margin">For whilſt he talked with God, the skin of his face did ſhine, ſo, as that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to come nigh him. Ex. 34. 29, 30.</note> God told <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hee could not ſee his face,</hi> viz. <hi>all his Glory, &amp; live:</hi> (a part he did
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:96098:94"/>
ſee:) But no living man is found capatious enough to take in ſuch a degree of glory, as is the fulneſſe of Gods face and favour. Is't not the darkneſſe of the viſion, and the obſcurity of the evidences of Gods grace &amp; favour, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times makes a child of light ſit in darkneſſe, and can ſee no light? what (ſave this very thing) made the Church cry out, <hi>Lord thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.44.</note> 
                  <hi>haſt covered thy ſelfe with a cloud, ſo that our Prayers ſhould not paſſe through?</hi> and <hi>Job, Loe he goeth by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Job 9. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>me and I ſee him not; hee paſſeth on alſo, but I perceive him not.</hi> If it be ſaid the Revelation is not dark in it ſelfe: but to ſuch as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes, 'tis the apprehenſion which is darke that ſuch have of it: It's granted<hi>:</hi> but ſtill 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>we ſee darkly here,</hi> and that God and glory are but reveal'd in part, whiles we are here, ſo that imperfect revelations are darke comparatively, referring to what they ſhall be.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:96098:95"/>
How doe ſome precious ſouls grieve, take on, mourn and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, becauſe they cannot ſee God to be theirs, &amp; themſelves to be his, and abiding in him clearly? To ſuch bee it now ſpoken, ere long diſconſolate ſoul! thou ſhalt <note place="margin">Gloria ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat rupibus. <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Where there's an excellency there's a great difficulty.</note> be in his armes, behold his glory, and thine own too, which he ha's <hi>given</hi> thee, even there where this kind of darkneſſe, nor any other of what nature ſoever can ever approach. Revelations of God in heaven are immediate alſo, as well as cleare; there, languiſhing ſoules! you that here mourne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, cry night and day after the Father of Spirits, are ſick of love: there (I ſay) you ſhall not need to be ſtaid <hi>with flaggons, or</hi> comforted <hi>with Apples;</hi> (as the Spouſe once deſit'd) for God ſhal be all unto you then. The <hi>Greek</hi> Poet when he had recited an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Poem, and all his Auditors had left him, except <hi>Plato,</hi> ſpake thus<hi>: Plato</hi> is to me in ſteed of al. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato</hi> eſt mihi pro omnibus.</note>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:96098:95"/>
So a ſoule that's forſaken of all, except God, findes God in ſtead of all to her. And you alſo that now take great paines, and have many weary fits in prayer, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, conference, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; ſhall then reſt from thoſe labours, and enjoy God and Chriſt, without any ſuch meanes.</p>
               <p>Others alſo, whoſe hearts are now full of cares, feares, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes about the maner of doing ſuch ſervices: one while bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing badneſſe of memory, another while coldneſſe of affection, at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time deadneſſe of heart, drowſineſſe and dulneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with all carnall, idle, wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoughts, uncheerfulneſſe, unfitneſſe, and unſuitableneſſe, to and for ſuch holy employments: even thoſe (I ſay) ſhall then bee freed from all ſuch burthens: they ſhall have nothing there to care for, nor ſhall they have any employment to take paines in;
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:96098:96"/>
for it ſhall be, not a paine, but a pleaſure to <hi>follow the Lamb whither ſoever he goes, with whom is fulneſſe of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. His communicating of himſelfe fully and at once. On earth God communicates of his fulneſſe: but the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of all fulneſſe it ſelfe is onely in Heaven. Beſides, the communication of fulneſs which Saints receive here, is onely <hi>of grace for grace:</hi> Believers<hi>!</hi> if you'l receive glory for glory, expect till you be where Chriſt is, in whom ſuch fulneſſe dwels. <hi>Father I will that they may be where I am: to behold my glory.</hi> That, even that will be their renowne, who ſhall dwell in light marvellous</p>
               <p>God do's this; firſt, to keep under ſelfe-advancing ſins<hi>:</hi> wee, Alas! are invincibly prone to lift up our ſelves, and let Chriſt lye low, who ne're deſerv'd ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe at our hands: we riſe in
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:96098:96"/>
our owne conceits immenſly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure; hence wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the Lord to leave <hi>thornes in</hi> our <hi>fleſh,</hi> ſomething or other to beget anguiſh in us; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Satan, a Devil <hi>to buffet us,</hi> &amp; beat us out of our high holds: If in-comes from heaven abound on mens ſpirits, oh how apt are they to waxe fat, and forget the rocke <hi>whence they are hewen?</hi> yea, the very <hi>breſts that gave them ſuck,</hi> ran out freely for their nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? But what a ſad and bad thing is this; that men ſhould be evill becauſe God is good? That God cannot abound in Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but man will abate in humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Paul</hi> ſinn'd once thus, but it brought him on his knees <hi>thrice</hi> to the God of pardons; God will not communicate all his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs on earth, leaſt men ſhould be full of ſpirituall tumours on ſuch a bottome: hee'l firſt have them where they can bee proud no more, and then they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:96098:97"/>
all fulleſt glory. <hi>Oh the height, and the depth of the wiſdome of God! how unſearchable are his Counſells, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> but.</p>
               <p>2. God gives not out all his fulneſſe here, for earthly veſſells, unglorified Chriſtians cannot hold it all whilſt in the body. The Widdowes oyle increaſt whilſt her Veſſell could receive it: but when once the Veſſells were ſtraitned, its encreaſe was ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Chriſtians have had, and ſtill have as much of God here, as ſuch Veſſels will hold<hi>:</hi> ſpeak experience! Are not ſome ſo full of Chriſt at ſome times, as that they can ſcarce containe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a huge world? and hence would faine <hi>be with Chriſt,</hi> that they may bee more inlarg'd like their object, to receive as much of him as can bee given? What mortall can tell how much the affections of Saints are inflamed, and how much their zeal is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:96098:97"/>
when God comes in ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and comfort breakes in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them like a flood? Then, even then, how looſe they ſtick to the Creatures, and how much they long to be above them with the Creator, I want words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. Theſe like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when once they had got a taſte of the grapes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be at quiet untill they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thither. Is not this to keep men longing, who would bee found lothing, had they all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe here? what is't elſe? God ſpeaks good to the heart, but 'tis here a little, and there a little, to keep their ſtomacks open, that he may put in more when he ha's a minde ſo to doe. God commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates all at once in heaven too<hi>:</hi> (though ſome have other thoughts) this puts a difference betwixt fruition of his commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications on earth, &amp; the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them in heaven: for here he gives out himſelfe but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:96098:98"/>
now a little and then a little as we ſaid before. God ſerves his children as you deale with yours: an heire in his minority is kept under, to make him know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and hee receives his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance only by parcels, and ſmall pieces: but when he comes to be of full yeares, then his whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance comes in at once. <note n="a" place="margin">And in this ſence as the Apoſtle ſpeaks the believing heir, while he is a child, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers nothing from a ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though he be Lord of all. But when he's of ripe yeares, &amp; comes into thoſe heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly places, hee is made a Lord, yea a King, &amp; his Father gives him his portion all at once, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1.</note> If diſcoveries of God in glory bee not full, and at once, then theſe abſurdities would follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The viſion of God then would be but graduall, but imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and in part, there as wel as here: and ſtil the glorified would ſtand in doubt, when the reſt ſhould be revealed, which kinde of doubting would argue diſtruſt, which cannot poſſibly have place in heaven. Nor did it ever enter into the thoughts of the moſt High, that the leaſt occaſion ſhould be given to ſuch an evill; And certainely when Saints are where they can ſin no more from
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:96098:98"/>
any cauſe in themſelves, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out themſelves; ſuch as urge the Principle muſt needs be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of charging God: For by the rules and lawes of ſuch kinde of arguing, 'twill eaſily be gather'd that the Lord's ſhutting in of himſelfe though but for a ſeaſon, makes the ſoule queſtion the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of future diſcoveries. Concerning which perſons, I had almoſt ſaid their blaſphemie is of a very high nature: but.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Where then were the Saints ceſſation from labour; would there not then bee a continuall want of the exerciſe of grace? yea even of faith, hope, patience, and long-ſuffering, untill the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of ſuch a full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of God to the ſoule. And who knowes not that thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall ceaſe to exiſt &amp; be, when once the Saints are made glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? For what need will there be of faith to evidence things viſible, and ſuch things as are not at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:96098:99"/>
from the S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>? what need of hope to waite for that which is had already? and what an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Doctrine will this bee found to dying Chriſtians. In a word, grace is ſwallowed up of glory; yet I grant that love ſhall be ever active in thoſe heavenly places.</p>
               <p>The third part of glory is the convolution or turning of the whole ſoul on God, according unto what he reveals of himſelfe in ſuch a maner: here alas! Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot roule themſelves on God immediately &amp; fully. Here the means is cal'd in to help, and wee ſee little is done; but by the meanes. <hi>Faith comes by hearing,</hi> as the Scriptures ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Beſides, who can doe it fully, when as hee that knowes but in part, truſts, and believes but in part; for how can he aſſent unto what he knowes not? Adde to this, that here the thoughts wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from God, cannot be kept in
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:96098:99"/>
in holy employments; and the heart is oft abſent, and afarre off, when the perſon is preſent, as God complains: and this either from ſome defect, in the manner of the adminiſtration of the word (the abſence of the ſpirit and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer concurring) or ſome cauſe ſubordinate thereunto. But in Heaven the preſence of God holds the ſoule cloſe to it ſelfe, ſo that it cannot wander, cannot ſtir from God; and the Majeſtie and glory, with the amiableneſſe of the ſame preſence, drawes out all the abilities of the whole ſoul, to act anſwerable unto the lawes, neareneſſe, and deareneſſe of ſuch a relation as is betwixt God and her ſelfe. Hence 'tis as eaſie for a glorified, ſoule to bee turn'd on God, and to doe for God, as to be, God having freed her from all power of acting otherwiſe, &amp; having alſo implanted in her an in-written conſtitution, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate inſtinct by glory. To be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:96098:100"/>
glorified, is to be freed from all imperfections of ſoule and body, and to enjoy all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in them both joyntly: which by reaſon of <hi>Terminus â quo, viz.</hi> the miſeries and evills that Saints are delivered from, is fitly call'd in ſacred writ, <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and in regard of <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> 'tis as truely and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13, 14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 36. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>&amp; Cap.</hi> 1. 4.</note> ſtiled <hi>beatification, life, eternall Glory, glorification,</hi> and <hi>an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall inheritance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On which two branches there growes that bliſsfull fruit, which the glorified eate in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God. Of theſe 2. in their order it is that we intend to ſpeake.</p>
               <p>Wee begin firſt with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities of the ſoule, which are a part of her glory; The firſt is glorious liberty, ſuch as is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the children of God, <hi>viz.</hi> freedom from all infringements, and ſoule-ſtraitning powers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All power and poſſibility
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:96098:100"/>
of ſinning againſt her ſoveraigne good; conceptions of ſinne ſhall then ceaſe to be, much more then ſhall the births of ſin, which are Death, be annihilated. <hi>There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines no Condemnation</hi> for her, becauſe ſhe's in Chriſt, walkes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit of God, and <hi>followes the Lambe whither ſoever hee goes.</hi> Sin, Death, Divels and Hell, <hi>are ſwallowed up in the victories of</hi> her Husband.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From al ſpots of ſin, all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual impurity, all low thoughts of God, and high thoughts of her ſelfe, all irregularity of will, as it was rebellious to right reaſon with greateſt oppoſition: Though here ſhe could not elect or reject like the Lord, yet in glory ſhee ſhall. Adde to this her freedome from all unſoundneſſe of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and taints of error; which while ſhe was unglorified ſhe was ſubject unto; in all her apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, receptions, and concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the moſt <hi>Holy God,</hi> and his
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:96098:101"/>
moſt <hi>Holy</hi> things, or of her ſelfe and others. Beſides, her freedom from all impuritie, and imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of affection; her love then ſhal be undefiled, like unto Chriſts, and not weak, cold or feeble, as't is whilſt in an <hi>earthly Tabernacle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. From all inſtruments of ſin. Shee'l then be freed from ſuch a body, whoſe <hi>members are all weapons of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious ſervants to her, as ſhee's a ſoule: the <hi>Law,</hi> viz. the power <hi>of the members,</hi> can <hi>rebell</hi> no more <hi>againſt the law of</hi> her <hi>minde,</hi> to <hi>lead</hi> her <hi>captive</hi> to <hi>ſinnes law, viz.</hi> ſins power. The unruly Carkaſſe ſhal never croſſe, vexe, and diſquiet her more; Serenity and Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity ſhall then cover her as a garment. Shee ſhall then have the ſubſtance, dominion, and ſtrength of a Spirit, which is ſuch as is in the Angels of God, one of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> did <hi>in one night ſlay</hi> 185000. <note place="margin">2 Kings 19. 35.</note> Nor ſhall the vile body ever let in ſinne by the ſences, to conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:96098:101"/>
the precious ſoule any more.</p>
               <p>The ſenſes of hearing, ſeeing, ſmelling, taſting and touching ſhall be ſpiritualiz'd, ere that the ſoule will employ them againe. The ſoul ſhal never re-enter into an unglorious body, when once ſhe's rid on't; Nor ſhal ſhee ever have need ſo to doe, for ſhal ſhe not be contain'd in God? and is not that better then to exiſt in a naturall body? The ſoules of S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>, although their ſtrength bee now held in, and buried in their maſſie, ſinful, weake bodies, ſhal then appeare in their native and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Finally, there ſhal be then <hi>mens ſana, in corpore ſano:</hi> a ſound mind in a ſound body.</p>
               <p>The parts of the bodies glory are ſuch as theſe;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Freedome from all wants, weakneſſes, diſtempers, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comelineſſe. Neither blindneſſe, lameneſſe, deafeneſſe, nor croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:96098:102"/>
ſhall enter that place of perfection. The bodies of Saints though they dye imperfect, yet ſhall they riſe made perfect in all their parts. What though their bodies be <hi>without form, comelineſs, &amp; faſhion;</hi> yet they ſhal be made handſome, beautiful, and comely, juſt <hi>like unto</hi> the <hi>glorious bodie</hi> of Chriſt<hi>:</hi> yea, and which is more, <hi>they ſhal,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>be faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the whole body like unto his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die:</hi> bee as handſome bodied as Chriſt is, and have as comely a Perſon, and feature as he himſelf ha's, whom the Father loves dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> ſhall have no lameneſſe in his feet then, he ſhal not halt before God in glory: nor ſhall <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtammer, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with his tongue, or need an Interpreter in that day. For ha's not God promiſed <hi>to turne unto</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>his people a pure language, that they may all call upon the Lord to ſerve him with one conſent;</hi> or as in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, with one ſhoulder.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:96098:102"/>
2. It ſhall have no want of outward ſuſtenance. Beings on earth may conſiſt in <hi>what</hi> men <hi>ſhal eate,</hi> and in that <hi>where with they ſhal be cloathed.</hi> Providence exiſting in ſuch ſupportments: but the Kingdome of Heaven, and Saints beings there, <hi>conſiſts not in meates or drinkes: but in righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe. They ſhall hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>no more, neither ſhall they thirſt any more; for the Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feede them, and leade them to living foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of water,</hi> as the ſpirit ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, adde to this, that the bodies weakeneſſe with want of health ſhall ceaſe then. Here the diſcord of the bodies Elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie qualities, and its corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature concurring begets di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, diſeaſes, putrifactions, and contagions; Although affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s come not forth of the duſt, neither doth trouble ſpring out of the ground: but in glory by the powerfull influence of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:96098:103"/>
Majeſtie upon the whole man, there ſhall be a perfect har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and agreement among all ſuch qualities and diſſonant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. Their bodies whether hot and dry, or cold and moiſt, ſhall have perfect health and ſtrength. Then ulcerous <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall be found as whole as a fiſh; and in that day all inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward contagions, and hurtfull impreſſions ſhall ceaſe to be. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>holy mountaine ſaith God.</hi> There's no beating, bruiſing, wounding, ſtabbing, or killing of bodies in glorie<hi>:</hi> then the moſt high God with a ſtretched-out arme, will free the Carkaſſe from all diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to any inward decays of ſtrength, or vitall ſpirits: which eſtate in Scripture is aptly cal'd a <hi>Condition,</hi> or <hi>Inheritance, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. Potentia non moriendi ex quadam hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſi unio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma originali ter perfecta immortali.</note> 
                  <hi>undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerv'd in heaven for them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Hence the body is inveſted with <hi>Potentia non moriendi,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:96098:103"/>
it can never be a dying body any more, nor ſhall the Saints ever have cauſe to cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, <hi>oh! who ſhall deliver mee from this bodye of death?</hi> and is not this that bleſſed day of the bodies redemption from <hi>ſinne</hi> &amp; <hi>death,</hi> its <hi>wages?</hi> What but this made thoſe followers of Chriſt, who had receiv'd the firſt fruits of this glory wee ſpeak of, to groane within themſelves, waiting to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this reſt?</p>
               <p n="4">4. And what miſſe of ſleep can there be then, when the body ha's ceas'd <hi>from its labours,</hi> which makes it wanting in ſuch a kinde. Beſides, there will be no lacke of fire to heate us, or aire to coole and ſtrengthen the bodies brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for there ſhall be an <hi>aura</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Quae ſupplet defectumaeris corporibus glorificatis.</note> 
                  <hi>caeleſtis</hi> as ſome affirm, which ſhal ſupply the want of aire to glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bodies<hi>:</hi> but I rather judge there ſhall bee no miſſe of ſuch things, becauſe there ſhall be <hi>no ſunne to ſcorch them, neither cold to</hi>
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:96098:104"/>
                  <hi>pinch them: the ſunne ſhall not light upon them, nor any heate</hi> as the holy Ghoſt ha's ſaid.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And can you think that he who <hi>cloaths Lillios</hi> on earth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their owne <hi>paines taking,</hi> will let Saints in heaven goe naked? Ha's not the Lambe of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that his ſhall <hi>walke with him in white?</hi> and that his raiment is ſo fit and large, and covers ſo wel, as that nakedneſſe cannot appear. Who tooke away <hi>Joſhuah's</hi> filthy <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>garments,</hi> when hee <hi>ſtood before the Lord,</hi> caus'd his iniquities to paſs from him, and <hi>cloath'd him with change of raiments?</hi> was't not the <hi>Angell of the Covenant, Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Its univerſal freedom from <note place="margin">Sicut ſpiritus carni ſerviens non incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grué carnalis ita caro ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui ſerviens, recte appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp;c. <hi>Aug.</hi> de civit. Dei, l. 13. c. 20.</note> all power to affront the ſpirit of Chriſt, by diſobedience and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. And as ſubjection to ſinne and Satan ſhews the body is naturall whilſt here: ſo ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:96098:104"/>
to the ſpirit of Chriſt there, will ſhew it is a ſpiritual body, which is another part of its glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A general exemption from <note place="margin">
                     <p>Reſtat ergo ut ſuam recipiat quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, quam vel habuit in juventure, etiamſi ſenex eſt mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: vel fuerat habiturus ſi antê eſt defunctus. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civit. Dei, l. 22. c. 15.</p>
                     <p>Circa triginta annos defini erunt eſſe etiam ſeculi hujus doctiſſimi homines juventutem. Idem. Ibid.</p>
                     <p>Reſurgent omnes tam magni Corpore quam vel erant vel fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi erant in juvenili aetate. Idem. Ibid.</p>
                  </note> all minority, Infancy, youth, old age, &amp; witherdneſſe, by all which the bodie's found in an imperfect ſtate: Infants, youths, and aged perſons, if in Covenant with God, ſhall riſe in the perfection of ſtrength and yeares: which as ſome have prov'd ſhall be ſuch as is found to bee in perſons about the age of 30. or as others affirm, about the age of 33. and then, as others have made good by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the child ſhall riſe in that perfect ſtrength it would have had, had it liv'd untill the time of the fulleſt perfection of growth.</p>
               <p>Now to the ſecond branch of
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:96098:105"/>
the definition, <hi>viz. That to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified is to enjoy all perfection in ſoul and body both joyntly,</hi> and of that thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſoul and body ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally enjoy a moſt exquiſite knowledge of God, the godly, &amp; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 1.</note> of themſelves alſo, when once they're made glorious. An exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite &amp; perfect knowledg of God, they ſhall both ſee him not onely mentally and contemplatively: but alſo with the bodies eyes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally: For the glorious God will let in ſuch a great light, and give ſuch a great ſtrength of ſight unto them both; as that the eyes of them both ſhall be opened, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd, and perfectly apted to concord with himſelfe the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
               <p>Whence was that of <hi>Job. I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 19. 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>know that in my fleſh I ſhall ſee God, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelfe, &amp; mine eyes ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hold him, and not a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> as it is in the Originall, was't not hence? <hi>viz.</hi> that he had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:96098:105"/>
in his own ſoul, being ſeal'd with the ſpirit of promiſe, that ſuch a thing ſhould be? and doe's not God approve this ſaying? when he ſayes he <hi>ſpake right words of</hi> him? And which is more, we ſhall ſee and enjoy him perfectly in our ſelves: wee ſee and know the Lord on this ſide glory but by fits, now and then; even as <hi>a waifaring man, who ſtayes but for a night, and is gone:</hi> or elſe wee ſee him ſpiritually, as the Diſciples ſaw him corporally, when he was comming towards them: <hi>they</hi> ſaid, ſays the Text, <hi>hee is a Ghoſt.</hi> So when God comes in upon our ſpirits with joy and gladneſſe, comfort and refreſhment, wee are prone to thinke 'tis not hee. How many precious Saints are there under Heaven, whoſe ſoules with <hi>David</hi> refuſe to be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſhunne the Lord in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts as if he were a Ghoſt? And though he ſay ne're ſo oft, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples, <hi>be of good cheere,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.27</note>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:96098:106"/>
                  <hi>feare not</hi> to be comforted, <hi>It is I?</hi> Yet how hardly are men brought to believe, being ſlow of heart? yea, and though poſſibly they doe not thinke a Ghoſt is comming towards them<hi>:</hi> yet, doe they not oft conclude that ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are deluſions and illuſions of a falſe ſpirit?</p>
               <p>We doe not only feare vainly thoſe things which cannot hurt us: but alſo dread even perverſly thoſe things which occaſion our <note place="margin">
                     <p>Non ſolum inaniter me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuamus quae nocere non poſſunt, ſed perverſé etiam horreamus ea quae ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem faciunt: <hi>Mucſ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ludit ſuavisſtuié, cum nos putamus omnia eſſe perditisſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In tentationibus fingimus Deum alium: quàm revera eſt putamus Deum tum non eſſe Deum, ſed phantaſma, hoc eſt, horribile ſpectrum quod nos velit devorare. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Quoad in anguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is ſumus, non eſt credendum noſtris Cogitationibus de Deo. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> ſafety.</p>
               <p>For doe not many rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that Satan's transform'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angell of light, then that themſelves are transform'd into Chriſt? who can deny it? and that
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:96098:106"/>
this unbelief argues an imperfect ſight, and knowledge of God, &amp; of his grace and favour? Such ſad ſoules the ſpirit of bondage ha's chain'd up ſtill; yea, ſome have, and doe poſſeſſe God here yet will not ſee and know ſuch a thing: You that raiſe up more objections againſt God and your ſelves, then can meete with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; Is not this your caſe?</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee ſhall ſee him perfectly in the Creatures alſo, when we are in glory: Whilſt we are here, wee ſee not ſo much of God in the creature as there is: wee are too much bent to ſee the Lord rudely, ignorantly, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely, as hee comes unto us in the creatures. Alas! how ſeldom <note place="margin">Longè extra ſepta evehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </note> doe wee obſerve and conſider what of God wee take in by the Creatures? how much we enjoy him in connexion with them? And although fire, could not warme us, food could not ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:96098:107"/>
us, raiment could not ſecure us from ſcorching heate and pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching cold, were't not that God were in them, to give heate to the firſt, put nouriſhment in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, &amp; a conſerving quality in the third; Yet how hardly are we brought to ſee, and wonder at the Lord in ſuch a diſpenſation? Is not this to over-look the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator in the creatures? And is not ſuch a ſight of God too like that which the Heathen had of him? ſome of whom beholding him under the notion of <hi>Cauſa cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> onely, did colour over their creature-worſhip; by affirming, that though they did worſhip the Sunne, Moone, and Stars with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther created things, yet that they did not worſhip the Creature, but God in the Creatures; For ſaid they, God is in every thing, and the truth is, wee all of us doe things of this nature very confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, and prepoſterouſly. If this
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:96098:107"/>
were not ſo, what hinders (could wee ſee the Lord perfectly in the creatures) but that we might take in God, when: we take in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, and ſo have ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die fed together? But glory helps all this; for when Saints are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, <hi>they ſhall ſee God as hee is in himſelfe</hi> &amp; in themſelves, and alſo as he is in the creaturs perfectly. And holy hearts! in the interim ſee as much of God as you can in all your morſells, and mercies, becauſe 'tis very good for you ſo to doe. Remember the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of whom 'tis ſaid, that <hi>while the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 11. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh was betweene their teeth,</hi> ere it was chewed, <hi>the wrath of the Lord was kindled,</hi> and <hi>they dyed,</hi> and <hi>why</hi> for <hi>they</hi> did not obſerve that God was in the mercie, which cauſed murmuring in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A perfect knowledg of the godly there is<hi>:</hi> as ſome have prov'd, <note n="*" place="margin">Ibi á ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis omnes, ibi ab omnibus ſinguli cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcentur, nec quem-quam omni non latebit, quâ patriâ, quâ gentê, quâ ſtirpe, quis editus fuerit, vel quid etiam in vitâ ſuâ fecerit. <hi>Anſelm</hi> de ſimilitud. c. 59.</note> All Saints ſhall bee
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:96098:108"/>
known of every particular Saint and every particular Saint ſhall be known of all: there ſhall be no ſtranger in heaven <note n="a" place="margin">In caelo nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus erit alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. <hi>Aug.</hi> Ep. 6. ad Italicam</note>: in glory S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> ſhall know not onely their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance in this world, but alſo thoſe whom they ne're ſaw here, even as perſons ſeene and known before. Yet in a carnall manner after the fleſh ſhall no man poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly know or be known. Yea that very <hi>Jeſus</hi> that on earth was known after the fleſh, ſhall bee knowne ſo no more. All know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge there ſhall be ſpirituall, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as is the object and Medium thereof. Add to this, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edge of Saints in Heaven ſhal be perſonall, as well as ſpirituall; That this is ſo, many men of God have fully cleared by Scripture and Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By arguments drawn from <hi>Adam</hi> who knew <hi>Evah</hi> as ſoon as he ſaw her, though hee had ne're ſeene her nor known her before <note n="b" place="margin">Si enim A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damas virtuae imaginis divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae concratae Evam de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore ſuo ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam cum è ſomno evigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſet illico agnovit, &amp;c. <hi>Kemnit.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By arguments fetched from
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:96098:108"/>
the Diſciples, knowing <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> in the transfiguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where glory was but weakely ſhadowed forth. Arguing that in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that glorious light, they would know them better <note n="c" place="margin">Petrus in monte in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali corpore Moſem &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam quos nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam viderat revelatione interne cogno vit. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 34. <hi>Buchan.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note n="d" place="margin">Boni bonos in regno, &amp; mali malos in ſupplicio ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcunt. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note> By arguments fetcht from <hi>Dives,</hi> his knowledge of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in Heaven, when the diſtance was great betwixt them: and that therefore the knowledg of Saints in Heaven who are preſent with each other, muſt needs be certain and excellent, with ſome others of like concernment <note n="e" place="margin">Vide <hi>Kemnit</hi> Harm. Evang. C. 87. &amp; Buc. Ioc. 39. <hi>&amp;</hi> Greg Dial. l. 4. c. 33.</note>. Alwhich are impregnable for matter of proofe; And although ſome thinke they have never prov'd a point ſufficiently, till all is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thereunto that may be, with whom I conſent not; yet ſhal I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to give in ſomething more, ſith, I am upon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That knowledg which may moſt augment the comfort of communion, and without which
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:96098:109"/>
lowſhip is not ſweet, ſhall be in glory: but that's a perſonall knowledge of each other, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch a kinde of knowledge ſhall be there. How uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table it is to have fellowſhip with ſtrangers, perſons we know not, let all men judge. Who will lay open his heart to a ſtranger? or mind almoſt the words of a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? yea truſt himſelfe in the company of ſtrangers? 'twas a great heart-ſmart &amp; grief to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that God had <hi>put</hi> his <hi>lovers and friends farre from</hi> him: <hi>yea his acquaintance into darkneſſe:</hi> that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 88. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> hee muſt be yoked to the ſociety of ſtrangers; ſo 'twas matter of great complaint to <hi>Job,</hi> that his <hi>acquaintance were eſtranged from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 19. 13.</note> him, <hi>become ſtrangers to him.</hi> But as 'twas ſaid before, there ſhall be no ſtranger in glory, nor ſhal there be any cauſe of ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints there, for acquaintance cannot bee put farre from us there, for wee ſhall then bee
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:96098:109"/>
link'd to each other, and all of us unto the Lord, ſo as not to ſtirre from him without him<hi>:</hi> But.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That knowledg, which may moſt encreaſe the joy of the Juſt, in their heavenly Manſions, ſhal be in that heavenly place: but a perfect knowledge of Saints will moſt encreaſe the juſt man's joy. <hi>All my delight is in the Saints, and in them that excell.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the righteous ſhall know one another in the Kingdome of their Father. A ſight had of the Saints perſons, &amp; faces on earth, do's much encreaſe the joy of a believing beholder. <hi>They that feare thee, will be glad when they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.74.</note> 
                  <hi>ſee mee: becauſe I have hop'd in thy word,</hi> ſaid the ſenſible Prophet: and me-thinkes 'tis a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to ſee the face, and have the ſociety of a ſanctifyed Saint. I have known ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts that have long'd, and lov'd to look on ſuch, and to be where
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:96098:110"/>
ſuch have come: much more then will a ſight and knowledge of them, being had in Heaven, where knowledge is fully perfect, delight a believing ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That knowledge by which a man ſhall <hi>know as hee's knowne,</hi> ſhall bee in Heaven<hi>:</hi> but that's <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12.</note> perſonall and corporall, God knowes the Saints perſons. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall did I ſay? yea more then perſonall for Saints in Heaven, in Glory, ſhall know each other by their names, God knows them by their names; thou haſt told me ſaith <hi>Moſes, thou knoweſt mee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>by my name.</hi> And ſo ſhall Saints know each other in glory, elſe how can they know as they are knowne? On earth wee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times know many perſons by ſight, but wee know not their names. Now in glory wee ſhall know one another by the ſame names we had on earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee ſhall have in glory a perfect knowledge of our ſelves,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:96098:110"/>
that great leſſon of man-kinde. before the whole man is glorified wee cannot ſee our ſelves, and what wee are. <hi>Who knowes the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>of a man that goes upward?</hi> as the wiſe man ſpeaks. 'Tis above the reach of a mortall wight, to know <hi>what ſpirit</hi> hee's <hi>of</hi> fully, and who can know <hi>the nature</hi> of that <hi>heart</hi> that's <hi>deceitefull above all things, and deſperately wicked?</hi> as the ſpirit ſpake in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets time? Oh what a neaſt of uncleane ſinnes is made there! what depths of darkeſt decets, and cloſeſt ſhifts are harboured there! whoſe inclinations being ſometimes ſcann'd, doe promiſe a ſweete frame for God, when at another time upon an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and advantage of ſinning, their carriage is ſuch, that they render a man deſperately vile. So as that a man can at no time know what hee is or would be.</p>
               <p>And is't not hence that he one while hopes, and another while
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:96098:111"/>
fears, now preſumes, and anon deſpaires, is one while as high as Heaven, another while as low as hell in his owne account.</p>
               <p>And here's the miſery while we are in the fleſh, we cannot or will not ſee into them; and have right thoughts of them<hi>:</hi> but in glory wee ſhall know what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides wee had before wee came there, &amp; how much more vile we would have been here, had not God reſtrain'd us: yea, and that we had in us as bad natures as the worſt of men, before grace made the difference. And ſhall we not then ſee how great a mercie and favour the Lord vouchſafed us, when he <hi>pull'd us out of the fire,</hi> our <hi>legs</hi> out <hi>of the ſtocks,</hi> and our whole man out of the chaines of darkneſſe, clawes &amp; jawes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and from under the <hi>power of ſinne?</hi> but chiefly for that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty gift we receiv'd, when the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made Chriſt our own. And all this that we may give thankes
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:96098:111"/>
to the Father, who ha's made us meet being vile ſinners, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come glorious Saints; That we may clearely ſee what cauſe wee have given us to magnifie the Compaſſions, cares, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Trinity, for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp; advancement in the Paradice of God. And that wee ſhould eternally ſing <hi>Halelujahs to the Lamb that ſits on the Throne</hi> of matchleſſe Majeſty; wee ſhall <note place="margin">Non eſt bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, eſſe quiſe non putat.</note> know our ſelves, and that we are in an eſtate of Bliſſe.</p>
               <p>Wee'l ſay no more of the firſt kind of perfection, <hi>viz.</hi> exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite knowledge, which the whole man poſſeſſing, is thereby very glorious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Perfect holineſſe, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <note place="margin">Spiritualia erunt, non quia corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeſſe deſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſed quia ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu vivicante ſubſiſtent. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> and ſpirituality. Happineſs puts not an end to holineſſe, but makes it perfect. Holineſſe is moſt perfect in Heaven, &amp; ther's no ſight of holieſt Majeſty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. This ſhall be both of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and actions; croſſeneſſe and
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:96098:112"/>
foulneſſe of nature cannot enter into thoſe places which are on high. Our natures ſhal be ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and our actions they ſhall be blameleſſe. There's nothing done in glory that can be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy: but to this purpoſe wee ſpake before.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Superiority. No man ſhal be under the juriſdiction of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; all Saints are ſuperiours in Heaven; ther's no difference betwixt him that was the Maſter and him that was the Servant. He that was a King on earth, fare's no better in glorie, then do's the meaneſt ſubject in reſpect of command. Saints are all fellows in Heaven; Yea thoſe wealthy Chriſtians, which here will ſcarce vouchſafe to look upon the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of their fellow members in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> wretched thing that it is<hi>!</hi> ſhall in that day ſee thoſe poore ones of Chriſt eyed, and priz'd of God in glory as much as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſhall ſeee them as
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:96098:112"/>
rich, and as well Crown'd and Thron'd, as he that was willingly ignorant of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doubtleſſe thou art our Father,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>though</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of us, &amp;</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledgeth us not: thou O Lord art our Father, and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi> ſaid the Prophet. Though the Brethren wil not know them, the Father will; doubtleſſe hee'l doe like himſelfe. And then all Oeconomicall, Politicall, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Relations ſhall ceaſe. There ſhall be none to command, nor any to bee obeyed but the Lord, and his Chriſt, our Jeſus. There the poore ſhall not feare the frownes of the rich, dread their threats, nor want their aids: but poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall ſit downe with rich <hi>Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the King on the ſame Throne, in the Kingdome of his Father. And the poore widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> as well as rich <hi>Dorcas</hi> of <hi>Joppa,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 36. 39</note> ſhall have a Throne, and a crown
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:96098:113"/>
in glory: For <hi>God is no reſpecter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>of perſons:</hi> Saints ſhall be all alike in preferment there: the Lord makes no difference in giving grace, nor will he do't in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring glory. <hi>Hee put no difference betweene us and them, purifying our hearts by ſaith,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks. <hi>Peter</hi> had truth of grace, and they had it too; God minded not their perſons. Though <hi>Peter</hi> and ſome of the reſt had beene his ancient ſervants, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ne're ſeene the inſide of his houſe, God purg'd them as well as the Apoſtles; 'tis ſo in glory, all ſhall ſit as neer to <hi>Chriſt</hi> as can be. For the weak and poor Chriſtian is as much allied to Chriſt and as deare to him, as the ſtrong and wealthy can bee. Chriſt ſhed as many teares, ſweat as many drops, endur'd as many ſtripes, and paid as great a price for the one as for the other. And in glory it ſhall be known, how hee <hi>takes his Lambes in his armes,</hi>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:96098:113"/>
                  <hi>carries them in his boſome, and leades gently thoſe that are with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>young.</hi> Adde to this Dominion perfect rule o're the Creatures, which we loſt in our firſt Parents. <hi>He that overcommeth,</hi> &amp; is crown'd with glory, <hi>ſhall have power over</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Nations, and ſhall rule with a rod of Iron,</hi> as 'tis ſaid.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, an orient ſplendor, and peereleſſe brightneſſe of reſplendent light, ſhall cover the whole man as a garment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.43.</note> 
                  <hi>forth as the Sunne in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of their Father: Who hath ears to heare, let him heare.</hi> And will not this, even this, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion an infinite, unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unparallel'd gladneſſe <note place="margin">Nonquia ſolis etiam ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem non ſuperabunt, ſed quando nihil fulgentius ſole videmus, proptereà re a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiſſimâ nobis ad exprimendum uſus eſt. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> Hom. 12.</note> throughout the very ſoule, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and whole man?</p>
               <p>In a word, there ſhall bee firſt, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a neceſſary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:96098:114"/>
of outward things.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Gods favour, and having a good aſpect from God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, or right acting accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the emminencies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>Thus of the parts of glory; a word or two of the adjuncts, and we apply the whole.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'tis a coherent glory, ſuch as agrees with, and is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto the whole man. For a man to be cloathed with the perfections of Plants, or Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malls, that will not make him glorious, the perfections of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things will not doe it, it muſt bee ſuch as is ſutable to him as he's a man, even a man renewed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, 'tis emminent, ha's worth in't, for glory is the moſt lofty condition, a thing that's better then a man's ſelfe. All the creatures beſides man, are
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:96098:114"/>
inferiour to a ſoule; an unſeen ſoule can't be advanc'd with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeene ſubſtance, for ſhee is more noble then any ſuch thing: And things below the ſoul can't ſet the ſoule aloft, it muſt be ſomething better then a ſoule which can do that. Now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but God is better: and he'l do it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, 'tis a contenting good, cauſing calmeneſſe, and ſerenity of ſpirit, ſo that when once the ſoule ha's what ſhee likes and loves, and is aſſur'd of the ſufficiency thereof, knows ſhe's not to ſeek, hath, and lyes on her Center: This makes her eſtate delectable, full, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and well-pleaſing; and as hee ſaid in a bad ſence, ſo may a glorified perſon ſay in a good ſence; <hi>Soule take thine eaſe.</hi> And with the Prophet; <hi>Soule returne to thy reſt, for the LORD hath dealt bountifully</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>with thee,</hi> and ha's <hi>delivered my</hi>
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:96098:115"/>
                  <hi>ſoule from Death, mine eyes from teares, and my feet from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, perfect love, there ſhall bee no jarres, nor ſtirres in glory, no heart-burnings, and evill ſurmiſings againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there ſhall bee no proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity that can bee envied, nor ſhall there bee any adverſity to bee deſpiſed: but of this before.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, laſting, everlaſting, it ha's perennity and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity in it: and thus the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is made apparent, which is found betwixt things above, and things below, things of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and things of the earth.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, and all this is made ours by it's conjunction with us, as the conjunction of the ſoul with Chriſt, and Chriſt with the ſoul, is a means to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the proprieties of them both, which they have in each other: ſo the good things of Chriſt and glory being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:96098:115"/>
with us, doe make them our owne.</p>
               <p>O glory, glory! thou art ſought of many after a ſort: but enjoy'd only of a few that ſeek thee rightly. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons up no leſſe then 288. opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of ſeverall learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers about happineſs, ſome placing it in one thing, ſome in another thing, being every one different in their conceits, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what each other held.</p>
               <p>And yet they did but beate the aire, and were in a Lab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, not being able to get out. Surely if naturall parts, and helpes of nature could fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom the depths of ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſuch great witts might have accompliſhed it: But 'tis only the gracious, that can tell what 'tis to be glorious.</p>
               <p>Now let all who expect to be and doe ſo well as they ſhould in life and death, and after the Judgement, premize theſe things
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:96098:116"/>
of weight and worth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their <hi>Pondus</hi> ſincerely. Oh! who minding theſe things can have the heart to harme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with making Idolls of inferiour things, and placing ſoules happineſſe in outward en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and ne're advance fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or riſe higher.</p>
               <p>I Remember a ſaying of a Philoſopher, who ſeing great poſſeſſions which hee had loſt, ſpake thus. Had not theſe things periſht, I could not have been ſafe. So great an obſtruction is the cleaving to theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">Non eſſem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſalvus, niſi iſtae perjiſſent Anaxagoras.</note> things, unto the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the inner man. Good Lord! what fooles are men, that ſeeke ſo much for a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Creatures, and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for an Intereſt in thee? If <hi>thy love bee beter then life,</hi> then thy diſlike is more bitter then death; What then's thy fury? Theſe things marre the taſte of worldly treaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:96098:116"/>
Firſt, that both in the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and alſo in the keeping of ſuch things, a man's always prone to offend his God. And who would live to injure his God, vexe his ſpirit, ſtaine his nature, and procure his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure? yet all this moves not ungodly men to ſeek for a Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a man's ſtill ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be diſpleas'd by the Lord. Men are uſually croſs'd every moment, and every day hath it's evill both of ſinne and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; ſometimes wee are <note place="margin">Matth. 6. ult.</note> croſs'd in things wee moſt like, A man ſets not his love large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on a Wife, Childe, Friend, or pleaſant and pleaſing thing, but ordinarily 'tis taken from him, or elſe hee'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tooke from them. At other times a man deſires things not attaineable, which is a very great, but a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret vexation. And is not all time laid out in bewailing what's
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:96098:117"/>
paſt, a loathing what wee have taſted, and a longing for what we have not taſted? which were it had, would no more fil us, then this we have already.</p>
               <p>We alas! are like men ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, who ſhift from roome to roome to finde eaſe: but whilſt the winds ariſe, and the waters ſwell, humours are but ſtirr'd, not taken away. And oft times wee waite for better dayes: but they are hid from our eyes. Thus we are catch'd like birds in a ſnare, yet skip up and down as if nothing ail'd us. And which is worſe, the joyes of Gods preſence are for the greateſt part kept from us here, which made <hi>Monica</hi> the Mother of <hi>Auſtin</hi> crie out <note place="margin">Quid hic fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciemus? cur non ocyus migtamus? Cur non hinc avolamus?</note> heartily; What doe wee here? why depart we not ſwifter? why ſlye wee not hence?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, outward things are not as they ſeeme, and are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd, they have indeed a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:96098:117"/>
ſhewes, and are admired<hi>:</hi> but <hi>inſpice ea,</hi> view their inſides and you will finde that they fill the head with cares, and the heart with vexation.</p>
               <p>'Twas a good ſpeech of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, whatſoever hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was<hi>:</hi> you (ſaid hee) gaze on my purple Robe, and Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Crown: but did you know what cares are under it, you would not take it up from the ground to have it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Heavenly or earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advancement is not in them. To Heaven they helpe not, for riches availe not in the day of wrath. Advance on Earth they ſhall not, for 'tis the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative onely, to doe that for men. <hi>Promotion commeth neither</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 75. 6, 7</note> 
                  <hi>from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South: but God's the Judge, he pulleth downe one, and ſetteth up another,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, they are unſuitable
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:96098:118"/>
to the nature of a ſoule, and her ſublimitie. And can you thinke that the Lord brought us into the World only to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the Carkaſſe with things ſuitable thereunto? The ſoule muſt have a <hi>bonum congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> ere ſhee can bee glorious, or begin to bee ſo; But theſe things accord not with her. For is not the ſoul of an immortal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? then how can dying things nouriſh &amp; refreſh a living ſoul? ſhee cannot get or make a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out of all ſeen things i'th world, nor can ſhee live to her liking on ſweeteſt huskes that be here. Shee's but <hi>hoſpes corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and that may pleaſe the Hoſt, which cannot pleaſe or pleaſure the Gueſt; and that may fat the carkaſſe, which ſtarves the ſoule. A man may have <hi>the deſires of his heart</hi> in theſe things, and ſtill <hi>retaine leane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his ſoul.</hi> Wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proves it to be true in ſome.
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:96098:118"/>
Beſides, good things of this life are but particular, can only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply particular wants: but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the ſoule are univerſall after good, and all good. God is all good to the renewed ſoule. Oh then let's not purſue the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">Tanquam haec ſit noſtri medicina do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris.</note> ſo, as though that would cure our maladies, heal our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and bring us to glory.</p>
               <p>And now wretched ſinners be perſwaded, <hi>lay not out ſtrength,</hi> &amp; time <hi>on that which is not bread,</hi> and <hi>on that which ſatisfieth not, neither kill your ſelves</hi> and ſouls careleſly: but walke in the wayes of the Lord, for he meeteth every one that worketh righteouſneſſe, and remembreth him in his ways. Be no longer your owne foes to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon,</hi> with the loſſe of the Pleaſures and Treaſures of Heaven for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and let God become your friend, who can <hi>ſtand you in ſtead in the evill day.</hi> Conſider, hee's ſuch a friend as is both wealthy,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:96098:119"/>
and helpfull; If a poor man hath a rich friend, and one that's help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full too, then his heart is eas'd.</p>
               <p>A Courtier in the Court of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> being upbraided with the meaneneſſe of his eſtate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed thus; What need I care, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Cyrus</hi> is my frend. When a man is ſanctified, and in Gods favour, ha's not hee much more cauſe to ſay ſo of God? When hee wants, let him ſay, God's my friend, when Satan, ſin, and the world play the part of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, ſay, wel, but God is mine; and all Saints in all places may crye out <hi>Emanuel,</hi> oh! how great a conſolation is this? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, hee's alwayes one and the ſame to a return'd backſlider, he's a friend in adverſity, ſuch an one is worth the prizing, he'l be in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with his as well as in peace, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as he ſaid, where God is, ther's hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. If a man goes to priſon, and God goes thither with him, and
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:96098:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtayes there by him, hee then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes a Heaven. Oh then prize him, prize him, for every one prizeth ſomething, and ſome things that are worth nothing: Let Chriſtians then much more prize him who's more then all things, &amp; worth more then all things; for no man was ever curs'd that had him, nor was ever any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without him.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Soli Sapienti Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
